<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://mourjo.me/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://mourjo.me/blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-11-13T13:31:31+01:00</updated><id>https://mourjo.me/blog/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Mourjo Sen’s Blog</title><subtitle>Thoughts of a software engineer about life, tech and everything in between. A place to put down my thoughts for my own recollection more than anything else. If you like it, be sure to drop me an email!</subtitle><author><name>{&quot;twitter&quot; =&gt; &quot;mourjo_sen&quot;}</name></author><entry><title type="html">Impact Of A Pivot</title><link href="https://mourjo.me/blog/musings/2025/09/28/impact-of-a-pivot/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Impact Of A Pivot" /><published>2025-09-28T05:55:32+02:00</published><updated>2025-09-28T05:55:32+02:00</updated><id>https://mourjo.me/blog/musings/2025/09/28/impact-of-a-pivot</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mourjo.me/blog/musings/2025/09/28/impact-of-a-pivot/"><![CDATA[<p>The average child’s greatest obstacle is blissful unawareness of their own passions. I was never particularly outstanding at anything. From my vantage point, expecting that I might find passion in anything felt like a bleak endeavour. While I was surviving high school from one test to the next, a pivot changed my life forever.</p>

<p>A decision is obvious – it presents you with alternatives. A pivot hides itself in the cacophony of life. It is a choice that remains dormant, unless someone steps in to recognize the need to change course. In class 7, we were first introduced to the subject of Computer Science. Back then, it was just another subject I needed to pass.</p>

<p>I still get goosebumps thinking about the day I received an abysmal score of 20%. Baba came home that warm humid evening after a busy day and told Ma that there must be something that is not clicking for me. He had taken introductory CS lessons back in college I think and he was convinced that my poor result was a symptom of not understanding the fundamental concepts of the subject.</p>

<p>As a soon-to-be parent, what I find remarkable in that exchange is while it would have been easy to blame my lackadaisical nature for the test results, Baba took a deeper look at things. He decided to teach himself Java while also explaining the course material to me, step by step, one day at a time. That changed everything. I make a living doing something I genuinely love – all because that day, Baba looked out for me in a way I didn’t know I needed. You can never connect the dots looking forward, you can only connect them looking backwards, Steve Jobs famously said. The weight of that pivot is apparent to me today, some 20 years later.</p>

<p>Baba was always a gifted teacher – many fondly recall his physics lessons. Much more than the lessons themselves, what I takeaway is his silent watchfulness throughout my growing years – being the pivot and the nurturing support the shy indecisive kid needed more than anything. While the rest of my friends were duty-bound to follow the grueling path of competitive examinations, Baba’s calm guidance offered me a different path. He always encouraged me to find something I enjoyed. That quiet but radical permission to explore took me from English majors, trying a degree in Law, switching back to CS majors and later securing a funded masters degree abroad.</p>

<p>Today I am one of the few who can, from the bottom of their hearts, say they love what they do for a living. All of it traces back to that warm sultry evening back home and Baba’s thoughtful intervention – a pivot – that changed the trajectory of my life to ultimately find that one thing I am ever so slightly better at than the next person. An average kid’s dream.</p>

<p>Sometimes all you need is someone to tell you that it’s not your fault and that they have your back. Baba went beyond that – by sitting next to me every Sunday morning since that soul-crushing 20% score and explaining the fundamentals of Computer Science to me. Week after week, he wasn’t just teaching me – he was kindling a spark that would grow into a lifelong passion.</p>

<p>Baba is my pivot, my rock and the reason I am not lost in the dust today.</p>]]></content><author><name>{&quot;twitter&quot; =&gt; &quot;mourjo_sen&quot;}</name></author><category term="musings" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The average child’s greatest obstacle is blissful unawareness of their own passions. I was never particularly outstanding at anything. From my vantage point, expecting that I might find passion in anything felt like a bleak endeavour. While I was surviving high school from one test to the next, a pivot changed my life forever.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Feeling Of Being Tiny</title><link href="https://mourjo.me/blog/musings/2025/08/05/the-feeling-of-being-tiny/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Feeling Of Being Tiny" /><published>2025-08-05T06:51:14+02:00</published><updated>2025-08-05T06:51:14+02:00</updated><id>https://mourjo.me/blog/musings/2025/08/05/the-feeling-of-being-tiny</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mourjo.me/blog/musings/2025/08/05/the-feeling-of-being-tiny/"><![CDATA[<p>With every clikety-clack of the train inching deeper into the mountainous terrain, I felt myself shrinking – a fleeting, precious feeling of insignificance. Engulfed in the colossal landscape, a quiet introspection took hold.</p>

<p>At Lauterbrunnen, I stood in front of unyielding and majestic mountains. I had to crane my neck to even have a glimpse of the sky. Feeling tiny and irrelevant was a humbling and grounding experience.</p>

<p>The Alps stood for thousands of years. My ambition, fears and achievements – which seemed to be all-important just days ago – now were laughably small. That smallness felt like freedom. Freedom from the shackles of expectation, replaced with profound insignificance.</p>

<p>The immutable mountains were stoic, impervious and unperturbed. Nothing I do will ever change the Alps. My successes will not make them taller, my failures will not make them crumble.</p>

<p>I suddenly didn’t feel afraid of failing, taking chances, experimenting. There was no duress of expectation in Lauterbrunnen – there was only the indifferent beauty in the quiet vastness of the world.</p>

<p>Feeling tiny was liberating. Empowering. Unlimited.</p>

<p><img src="/blog/images/2025-08-05-the-feeling-of-being-tiny-1.jpeg" alt="Image Description" /></p>]]></content><author><name>{&quot;twitter&quot; =&gt; &quot;mourjo_sen&quot;}</name></author><category term="musings" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[With every clikety-clack of the train inching deeper into the mountainous terrain, I felt myself shrinking – a fleeting, precious feeling of insignificance. Engulfed in the colossal landscape, a quiet introspection took hold.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Reasons To Believe</title><link href="https://mourjo.me/blog/musings/2025/07/26/reasons-to-believe/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Reasons To Believe" /><published>2025-07-26T11:24:00+02:00</published><updated>2025-07-26T11:24:00+02:00</updated><id>https://mourjo.me/blog/musings/2025/07/26/reasons-to-believe</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mourjo.me/blog/musings/2025/07/26/reasons-to-believe/"><![CDATA[<p>The dawn quietly crept in through the cracked windows. Lazy and exhausted from a week-long trip, I teetered on the precipice of skipping the weekly workout class. My muscles whispered for a softer start to the weekend. Yet, propelled by some unseen force, I went. And there, amidst the prosaic mundanity of a routine class, something profound unravelled.</p>

<p>Five minutes into the class, Mr O., our instructor, a strong disciplinarian, whispered something in Dutch into the microphone. To my utter bewilderment, he then began to sing. A ripple of confused expressions spread through the room, mirroring my own confusion. The reason unfurled itself as my eyes scanned the class. One of our classmates, recently diagnosed with liver cancer, had achieved the impossible. After months of what I can only imagine to be a despairing hell, she stood among us, miraculously returned.</p>

<p>Mr O.’s song was a standing ovation to her perseverance and her indomitable spirit – a spirit that eclipses any strength training session. If such a moment doesn’t stir the soul, ignite a longing for a higher purpose, to be a better self, to find meaning in the ordinary, what possibly could?</p>

<p>I missed both classes last week and I almost didn’t go today – yet, through some inexplicable coincidence, I was there, just where I needed to be – to be part of something bigger, to get a chance to cry with someone, to partake in the celebration of life. Call it coincidence, call it divine intervention, call it a miracle. Just another Saturday’s prosaic mundanity transcended into poetic resurgence.</p>

<p>If you need reasons to believe, it’s right there – you just need to look.</p>]]></content><author><name>{&quot;twitter&quot; =&gt; &quot;mourjo_sen&quot;}</name></author><category term="musings" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The dawn quietly crept in through the cracked windows. Lazy and exhausted from a week-long trip, I teetered on the precipice of skipping the weekly workout class. My muscles whispered for a softer start to the weekend. Yet, propelled by some unseen force, I went. And there, amidst the prosaic mundanity of a routine class, something profound unravelled.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">S3: Secure Serverless Shortlinks On AWS</title><link href="https://mourjo.me/blog/musings/2025/07/10/secure-serverless-shortlinks-on-aws/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="S3: Secure Serverless Shortlinks On AWS" /><published>2025-07-10T05:54:18+02:00</published><updated>2025-07-10T05:54:18+02:00</updated><id>https://mourjo.me/blog/musings/2025/07/10/secure-serverless-shortlinks-on-aws</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mourjo.me/blog/musings/2025/07/10/secure-serverless-shortlinks-on-aws/"><![CDATA[<p>Inspiration is hard to come by in many fields – but not so in software engineering. When I attended a course on AWS offerings last year, I decided to try it out myself. With a little bit of hard work, the result was a serverless URL shortener built on AWS called shortener called <a href="https://liliput.mourjo.me">Liliput</a>.</p>

<p>A URL shortener is not an uncommon project but I wanted to focus specifically on:</p>
<ul>
  <li><strong>Security</strong>: All operations in Liliput put security as a primary concern.</li>
  <li><strong>Atomicity</strong> with DyanamoDB for unique short links: DynamoDB supports <a href="https://docs.aws.amazon.com/amazondynamodb/latest/developerguide/WorkingWithItems.html#WorkingWithItems.AtomicCounters">atomic counters</a>, that is used in the link generation logic</li>
</ul>

<p>The source code is on <a href="https://github.com/mourjo/liliput">Github</a>. The home screen looks like this:</p>

<p><img src="/blog/images/2025-07-10-secure-serverless-shortlinks-on-aws-1.webp" alt="Image Description" /></p>

<h2 id="what-liliput-does">What Liliput does</h2>
<p>Liliput is a secure, serverless shortener of URLs with the following features:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Logged-in users can create short links (like <a href="https://liliput.mourjo.me/l/G4LZ1a">liliput.mourjo.me/l/G4LZ1a</a>)</li>
  <li>Logged-in users can also view their previously created links</li>
  <li>Anonymous users can visit shortlinks</li>
  <li>All short links are unique to a user - if the same long link is shorted multiple times, the same short URL is returned</li>
  <li>Usage counts (expansion count) are tracked and displayed on the UI</li>
  <li>Links can be expanded at most 25 times to prevent illegitimate usage (spam and phishing)</li>
  <li>Verified users can create links that can be expanded unlimited times (verification process is through the source code)</li>
</ul>

<p>Here is <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=EzdWG2OjYpE">a video</a> that demoes the application.</p>

<h2 id="focus-on-security">Focus on Security</h2>
<p>This application is secure because of the following features:</p>
<ul>
  <li>To create short links, you need a valid Google account</li>
  <li>Signing into Google uses the OAuth 2.0 with <a href="https://www.perplexity.ai/search/what-is-pkce-authentication-iipO5PXWQ.KvOOZvx_CQ7A">PKCE</a></li>
  <li>All cookies are<a href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/mourjo/liliput/refs/heads/master/images/cookies.png"> HTTP-only</a> (Javascript cannot access it)</li>
  <li>Links can only be expanded 25 times to prevent misuse, unless the user is verified</li>
  <li>All APIs are rate limited and alerts for when rate limit is breached</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="system-design">System Design</h2>
<p>The system is built using the following:</p>
<ul>
  <li>DynamoDB for storage</li>
  <li>Amazon Cognito and Google Oauth for login flows</li>
  <li>Lambda functions for logic implementation (shown below)</li>
  <li>API gateway for mapping lambda functions to routes</li>
  <li>Authorizer in API gateway with another Lambda function</li>
  <li>Public DNS (<a href="https://liliput.mourjo.me">liliput.mourjo.me</a>) for APIs</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="logged-in-flows">Logged In Flows</h4>
<p><img src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/mourjo/liliput/refs/heads/master/images/flowchart_01_homepage.svg" /></p>

<p><img src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/mourjo/liliput/refs/heads/master/images/flowchart_02_create_link.svg" /></p>

<h4 id="anonymous-flows">Anonymous Flows</h4>
<p><img src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/mourjo/liliput/refs/heads/master/images/flowchart_03_expand_link.svg" /></p>

<h2 id="learnings">Learnings</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Amazon Cognito integration with Google OAuth and managing login state in <a href="https://github.com/mourjo/liliput/blob/master/src/main/resources/index.html">a single-page Javascript</a> between the OAuth dance</li>
  <li>The authorizer middleware in API gateway with Lambda function</li>
  <li>Generating IAM policy document for giving access to only verified users</li>
  <li>Startup with Java based Lambda functions was quite slow</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="whats-next-for-liliput">What’s next for Liliput</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Verification without source code change</li>
  <li>Disable link expansions explicitly</li>
  <li>Switching between multiple Google accounts</li>
  <li>Searching for links shortened</li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name>{&quot;twitter&quot; =&gt; &quot;mourjo_sen&quot;}</name></author><category term="musings" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Inspiration is hard to come by in many fields – but not so in software engineering. When I attended a course on AWS offerings last year, I decided to try it out myself. With a little bit of hard work, the result was a serverless URL shortener built on AWS called shortener called Liliput.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">I spoke at Techcamp Hamburg</title><link href="https://mourjo.me/blog/musings/2025/07/08/property-based-tests-to-preserve-invariants-talk-at-techcamp-hamburg/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="I spoke at Techcamp Hamburg" /><published>2025-07-08T21:51:06+02:00</published><updated>2025-07-08T21:51:06+02:00</updated><id>https://mourjo.me/blog/musings/2025/07/08/property-based-tests-to-preserve-invariants-talk-at-techcamp-hamburg</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mourjo.me/blog/musings/2025/07/08/property-based-tests-to-preserve-invariants-talk-at-techcamp-hamburg/"><![CDATA[<p>“Accidental quality” — that’s what I call the hidden trap in traditional example-based tests.</p>

<p>In my recent talk at Techcamp Hamburg, I spoke about how enumerating test cases creates a dangerous illusion of safety, while the real bugs hide in the blindspots we never think to check.</p>

<p>Property-based testing flips the narrative: it searches for bugs instead of just testing for them. If you have 1000 users and you are writing 50 handpicked test cases - are you sure you are not missing any particular use-case?</p>

<iframe width="100%" height="669" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/5tCzdkPPX_s" title="Property Based Testing to Preseve Invariants - Fachtalk mit Mourjo Sen beim techCamp" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>]]></content><author><name>{&quot;twitter&quot; =&gt; &quot;mourjo_sen&quot;}</name></author><category term="musings" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[“Accidental quality” — that’s what I call the hidden trap in traditional example-based tests. In my recent talk at Techcamp Hamburg, I spoke about how enumerating test cases creates a dangerous illusion of safety, while the real bugs hide in the blindspots we never think to check. Property-based testing flips the narrative: it searches for bugs instead of just testing for them. If you have 1000 users and you are writing 50 handpicked test cases - are you sure you are not missing any particular use-case?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Winning the InfoQ Writing Contest</title><link href="https://mourjo.me/blog/musings/2025/05/30/i-won-2025-infoq-writing-contest/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Winning the InfoQ Writing Contest" /><published>2025-05-30T22:36:22+02:00</published><updated>2025-05-30T22:36:22+02:00</updated><id>https://mourjo.me/blog/musings/2025/05/30/i-won-2025-infoq-writing-contest</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mourjo.me/blog/musings/2025/05/30/i-won-2025-infoq-writing-contest/"><![CDATA[<p>Back in 2010, I decided to switch from an English Literature degree to a Computer Science Bachelor’s degree – but I never lost touch with writing and today I am still pinching myself to realize that I won the second prize for InfoQ’s writing contest in 2025!</p>

<p><img src="/blog/images/2025-05-30-i-won-2025-infoq-writing-contest-1.jpeg" style="border: 2px solid black;" /></p>

<p>Check out <a href="https://www.infoq.com/articles/flow-metrics-microservices/">the article here</a> and the announcement of the winners on LinkedIn:</p>

<iframe src="https://www.linkedin.com/embed/feed/update/urn:li:share:7334265349820866561" height="700" width="100%" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="" title="Embedded post" style="border: 2px solid black;"></iframe>]]></content><author><name>{&quot;twitter&quot; =&gt; &quot;mourjo_sen&quot;}</name></author><category term="musings" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Back in 2010, I decided to switch from an English Literature degree to a Computer Science Bachelor’s degree – but I never lost touch with writing and today I am still pinching myself to realize that I won the second prize for InfoQ’s writing contest in 2025!]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Quick Meetings: Why You Need Property Based Tests</title><link href="https://mourjo.me/blog/tech/2025/05/25/quick-meetings-why-you-need-property-based-tests/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Quick Meetings: Why You Need Property Based Tests" /><published>2025-05-25T09:04:24+02:00</published><updated>2025-05-25T09:04:24+02:00</updated><id>https://mourjo.me/blog/tech/2025/05/25/quick-meetings-why-you-need-property-based-tests</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mourjo.me/blog/tech/2025/05/25/quick-meetings-why-you-need-property-based-tests/"><![CDATA[<p>Today I am open-sourcing my <a href="https://github.com/mourjo/quick-meetings">quick-meetings</a> repository. It has one aim - to show the importance of property based testing (or generative testing).</p>

<p>At its core, this project allows you to create meetings. It is a very simple application. What could possibly go wrong?</p>

<p><img src="/blog/images/2025-05-25-quick-meetings-why-you-need-property-based-tests-1.png" alt="Image Description" /></p>

<h2 id="bug-1-non-json-response-body">Bug 1: Non-JSON response body</h2>
<p>If the accept header is something like <code>text/html</code>, Spring will try to return an HTML page, which is not what we want from an API - causing errors like this for the client:</p>
<pre><code>com.fasterxml.jackson.core.JsonParseException:
  Unexpected character ('&lt;' (code 60)): expected a valid value (JSON String, Number, Array, Object or token 'null', 'true' or 'false')
  at [Source: (String)"&lt;html&gt;&lt;body&gt;&lt;h1&gt;Whitelabel Error Page&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;p&gt;This application has no explicit mapping for /error, so you are seeing this as a fallback.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div id='created'&gt;Sat May 24 14:11:11 CEST 2025&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;There was an unexpected error (type=Method Not Allowed, status=405).&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/body&gt;&lt;/html&gt;"; line: 1, column: 1]
</code></pre>

<p>Check out this <a href="https://github.com/mourjo/quick-meetings/tree/demo-1-server-never-returns-5xx">branch</a> on how this was detected with property based testing.</p>

<h2 id="bug-2-nullpointers-and-5xx">Bug 2: NullPointers and 5xx</h2>
<p>Your code should never return a 5xx for any kind of request - a catch-all response code like 5xx should only be reserved for infrastructure issues what you genuinely cannot predict.</p>

<p>But if you send a payload like this, the response will be – quite sadly – a 5xx:</p>

<pre><code>curl -X 'POST' 'http://localhost:9981/meeting' -s \
  -H 'Content-Type: application/json' \
  -d '{
  "userId": 260754,
  "name": "Bobby'\''s meeting"
}' | jq .

{
  "timestamp": "2025-05-25T07:14:37.890+00:00",
  "status": 500,
  "error": "Internal Server Error",
  "trace": "java.lang.NullPointerException: Cannot invoke \"me.mourjo.quickmeetings.web.dto.MeetingDuration.from()\" because..."
}
</code></pre>

<p>Check out this <a href="https://github.com/mourjo/quick-meetings/tree/demo-1-server-never-returns-5xx">branch</a> on how property based tests found and resolved this bug.</p>

<h2 id="bug-3-gap-in-daylight-savings">Bug 3: Gap in Daylight Savings</h2>
<p>In the following snippet, a meeting creation request specifies the start-time at <strong>02:34</strong> and end-time at <strong>03:04</strong>, the error thrown says the start time is after the end time.</p>

<pre><code>Original Sample
---------------
  meetingArgs:
    MeetingArgs[fromDate=2025-03-30, fromTime=02:34:31, toDate=2025-03-30, toTime=03:04:31, timezone=Europe/Amsterdam]

  Original Error
  --------------
  java.lang.AssertionError:
    Expecting actual:
      "{"message":"Meeting cannot start (2025-03-30T03:34:31+02:00[Europe/Amsterdam]) after its end time (2025-03-30T03:04:31+02:00[Europe/Amsterdam])"}"
    to contain at least one of the following elements:
      ["Meeting created"]
    but none were found
</code></pre>

<p>This happens when the start or end time falls in a local timezone which is a “gap” due to daylight savings. On 30 March 2025, at <code>02:00:00</code> clocks in France were turned forward 1 hour to <code>03:00:00</code> - the time between 2 and 3 does not exist and is a gap.</p>

<p>This is caught again by property-based tests in <a href="https://github.com/mourjo/quick-meetings/tree/demo-2-invalid-date-range">this branch</a>.</p>

<h2 id="bug-4-query-to-check-overlapping-meetings">Bug 4: Query to check overlapping meetings</h2>

<p>The following query has a bug - it is quite hard to catch it at first glance (<code>$1</code> and <code>$2</code> are placeholders for the start and end time of a new meeting being created):</p>

<pre><code class="language-sql">SELECT *
FROM
meetings existing_meeting JOIN user_meetings um ON existing_meeting.id = um.meeting_id
WHERE (
  (existing_meeting.from_ts &lt;= $1 AND existing_meeting.to_ts &gt;= $1)
  OR
  (existing_meeting.from_ts &lt;= $2 AND existing_meeting.to_ts &gt;= $2)
)
</code></pre>

<p>Property based tests in <a href="https://github.com/mourjo/quick-meetings/tree/demo-3-meeting-creation-scenarios">this branch</a> reports the minimal case when this happens. This test fails when the second meeting is overlapping with the first but only if the second meeting <strong>starts before</strong>and <strong>ends after</strong> the first - note how the original sample finds a larger time overlap but the shrunk example finds the smallest failing case:</p>

<pre><code>Shrunk Sample (130 steps)
-------------------------
  meeting1Start: 2025-01-01T10:00:01
  meeting1DurationMins: 1
  meeting2Start: 2025-01-01T10:00
  meeting2DurationMins: 2

Original Sample
---------------
  meeting1Start: 2025-01-01T20:09:29
  meeting1DurationMins: 6
  meeting2Start: 2025-01-01T19:55:33
  meeting2DurationMins: 49
</code></pre>

<h2 id="bug-5-accepting-a-meeting-causes-an-overlap">Bug 5: Accepting a meeting causes an overlap</h2>

<p>In the previous bug, the fix ensured that the query to check overlapping meeting is correct but it is still possible to have overlapping meetings - as caught by property based tests in <a href="https://github.com/mourjo/quick-meetings/tree/demo-4-meeting-acceptations">this branch</a>.</p>

<p>Complex interleaving of user interactions – creating meetings, inviting others to meetings and accepting meeting invites – breaks the invariant that no person can be in two meetings at the same time. But which sequence of actions?</p>

<p><a href="https://github.com/mourjo/quick-meetings/tree/demo-4-meeting-acceptations">Property based tests</a> find minimal subset of operations that trigger the failure:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Alice and Charlie create overlapping meetings - this is okay because our invariant is no person can be at the same meeting, but if the attendees are different (here Alice and Charlie), it is perfectly fine</li>
  <li>It is also not a problem when Charlie is invited to Alice’s meeting</li>
  <li>It becomes a problem when Charlie accepts that meeting - because it overlaps with the meeting he created</li>
  <li>This is the minimal set of operations that shows the bug</li>
</ul>

<pre><code>OperationsGenTests.noOperationCausesAnOverlap:63 Invariant failed after the following actions: [
    Inputs{action=CREATE, user=alice, from=2025-06-09T10:21Z, to=2025-06-09T10:22Z}
    Inputs{action=INVITE, user=charlie, meetingIdx=0}
    Inputs{action=CREATE, user=charlie, from=2025-06-09T10:21Z, to=2025-06-09T10:22Z}
    Inputs{action=ACCEPT, user=charlie, meetingIdx=0}
]
</code></pre>

<p>But there are other more nuanced cases like this which sometimes get reported as well:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Charlie creates a meeting 0</li>
  <li>Bob is invited to meeting 0</li>
  <li>Alice creates a meeting 1 (overlapping with meeting 0)</li>
  <li>Bob is invited to meeting 1</li>
  <li>Bob accepts the invitation to meeting 0 (still no overlap)</li>
  <li>Bob accepts the invitation to meeting 1 (this causes an overlap for Bob)</li>
</ul>

<pre><code>OperationsGenTests.noOperationCausesAnOverlap:67 Invariant failed after the following actions: [
    Inputs{action=CREATE, user=charlie, from=2025-06-09T10:21Z, to=2025-06-09T10:22Z}
    Inputs{action=INVITE, user=bob, meetingIdx=0}
    Inputs{action=CREATE, user=alice, from=2025-06-09T10:21Z, to=2025-06-09T10:22Z}
    Inputs{action=INVITE, user=bob, meetingIdx=0}
    Inputs{action=ACCEPT, user=bob, meetingIdx=0}
    Inputs{action=ACCEPT, user=bob, meetingIdx=1}
]
</code></pre>

<h2 id="bug-6-empty-meetings">Bug 6: Empty meetings</h2>
<p>Once we have a way to test interleaving of operations, it is easy to extend that same framework - for example to preserve the invariant of no meeting should be empty.</p>

<p>While this seems like a gross miss, when we work on individual features, it is difficult to keep track of the larger product’s vision or expectations. This branch is the same - once we allow people to reject meeting invites, this bug manifests itself.</p>

<p>The minimal set of operations that fail is simple - this is provided by the test output as well:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Alice creates a meeting</li>
  <li>Alice rejects that same meeting</li>
</ul>

<pre><code>OperationsGenTests.noOperationCausesEmptyMeetings:70 Invariant failed after the following actions: [
    Inputs{action=CREATE, user=alice, from=2025-06-09T10:21Z, to=2025-06-09T10:22Z}
    Inputs{action=REJECT, user=alice, meetingIdx=0}
]
</code></pre>

<p>Check <a href="https://github.com/mourjo/quick-meetings/tree/demo-5-empty-meetings">this branch</a> for the details.</p>

<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>Testing invariants is different from example based tests. It requires you to think of what the product you are building <em>should</em> do instead of <em>how</em> it should do it. As we saw above, it is very hard to both build a new feature and ensure there are no obscure bugs (like daylight savings) and that it performs as expected in the face of complex interleaving of actions (like accepting meetings which overlap with existing meetings).</p>

<p>Property based testing encourages you to think of your code as a black box of logic - to test its limits with permutations of inputs (both user input and state) - which is simply not possible to enumerate manually.</p>

<p>If you like this topic, I am going to be speaking at TechCamp in Hamburg in June - hope to see you there!</p>

<p><img src="/blog/images/2025-05-25-quick-meetings-why-you-need-property-based-tests-2.jpeg" alt="Image Description" /></p>]]></content><author><name>{&quot;twitter&quot; =&gt; &quot;mourjo_sen&quot;}</name></author><category term="tech" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Today I am open-sourcing my quick-meetings repository. It has one aim - to show the importance of property based testing (or generative testing).]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">OSS is a Humbling and Character Building Experience</title><link href="https://mourjo.me/blog/musings/2025/05/17/humbling-oss-experience/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="OSS is a Humbling and Character Building Experience" /><published>2025-05-17T06:52:07+02:00</published><updated>2025-05-17T06:52:07+02:00</updated><id>https://mourjo.me/blog/musings/2025/05/17/humbling-oss-experience</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mourjo.me/blog/musings/2025/05/17/humbling-oss-experience/"><![CDATA[<p>Carl Sagan said astronomy is a humbling and character-building experience. I think it is very apt for open-source contributions too. Software building is as much about the human society we live in, as it is about the engineering of it.</p>

<p>Giving back – even in its tiniest form – reaps happiness, fulfillment and on some level, a connection with people who share our tiny slice of Earth’s unending history.</p>

<p>A long time ago, I wrote a small utility, very specific for <a href="https://medium.com/helpshift-engineering/a-study-in-parallelising-tests-b5253817beae">my (very niche) use case</a>. I had no expectation of anyone even hearing about it, let alone use it. The idea was simple - a mechanism to concurrently redefine a function in Clojure. There was only one intended user: me. But for some inexplicable reason, in 2019, I put it out in the open as a <a href="https://gist.github.com/mourjo/c7fc03e59eb96f8a342dfcabd350a927">Github gist</a>.</p>

<p>I recall Matthew Davidson reaching out to me to extract it into <a href="https://github.com/mourjo/dynamic-redef/tree/main">a library</a>, which Matthew also mentioned in a <a href="https://modulolotus.net/blog/2022-06-22-tidd/">blog post</a> in 2022. Today, the original gist has 29 chats and the library has been <a href="https://clojars.org/me.mourjo/dynamic-redef">downloaded 509 times</a> and with 19 stars on Github.</p>

<p>It’s not a lot, but to me, it means the world: 19 people found the idea interesting, which is 19 more than what I had anticipated. If you would like to <a href="https://github.com/mourjo/dynamic-redef/tree/main">contribute</a>, you will forever have my gratitude, as do the authors of all the open source libraries I use every day.</p>]]></content><author><name>{&quot;twitter&quot; =&gt; &quot;mourjo_sen&quot;}</name></author><category term="musings" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Carl Sagan said astronomy is a humbling and character-building experience. I think it is very apt for open-source contributions too. Software building is as much about the human society we live in, as it is about the engineering of it.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A Look Back On Bill Gates’ New Rules</title><link href="https://mourjo.me/blog/musings/2025/03/15/bill-gates-new-rules-in-2025/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Look Back On Bill Gates’ New Rules" /><published>2025-03-15T15:13:58+01:00</published><updated>2025-03-15T15:13:58+01:00</updated><id>https://mourjo.me/blog/musings/2025/03/15/bill-gates-new-rules-in-2025</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mourjo.me/blog/musings/2025/03/15/bill-gates-new-rules-in-2025/"><![CDATA[<p><em>This is article captures my notes and excerpts from Bill Gates’ 1999 article, <a href="https://time.com/archive/6955032/bill-gates-new-rules-2/">New Rules</a>, about how businesses should transform themselves in the new millennium.</em></p>

<p><em>I find these particularly enlightening in 2025 as AI takes centre stage for businesses – just like the internet did in in the late 90s.</em></p>

<h1 id="knowledge-is-not-power--shared-knowledge-is">Knowledge is Not Power – Shared Knowledge Is</h1>
<p>The old saying “knowledge is power” sometimes makes people hoard knowledge. It is wrong to believe that knowledge hoarding makes one indispensable. Power comes not from knowledge kept but from knowledge shared. A collaborative culture, reinforced by information flow, makes it possible for smart people all over a company to be in touch with each other. Our aim should be to enhance the way people work together, share ideas, sometimes wrangle and build on one another’s ideas–and then act in concert for a common purpose.</p>

<h1 id="bad-news-is-a-feedback-mechanism">Bad News is A Feedback Mechanism</h1>
<p>We have to be consistently receptive to bad news, and then you have to act on it  – without murdering the messenger of the bad news. The most important job as CEO is to listen for bad news. If the leader doesn’t act on it, people will eventually stop bringing bad news to their attention. And that’s the beginning of the end.</p>

<h1 id="unhappy-customers-are-our-greatest-opportunity">Unhappy Customers are Our Greatest Opportunity</h1>
<p>Listening to customers means hearing their complaints about current product shortcomings without feeling bad. Unhappy customers are always a concern. They’re also our greatest opportunity.</p>

<h1 id="understanding-the-scale-of-numbers-is-important">Understanding the Scale of Numbers is Important</h1>
<p>Knowing our numbers is a fundamental precept of business. We need to gather data at every step of the way. Crucially, we also need to understand what the data means: 5K and 50K should evoke a different reaction inside without having to think about it.</p>

<h1 id="empower-others-expect-ownership-and-belonging">Empower Others: Expect Ownership and Belonging</h1>
<p>In the new organisation, the worker is no longer a cog in the machine but is an intelligent part of the overall process. If we give people more sophisticated jobs and better tools, people will become more responsible and bring more intelligence to their work. In the digital age, we need to make knowledge workers out of every employee possible.</p>

<h1 id="motivation-needs-to-be-rewarded">Motivation Needs to be Rewarded</h1>
<p>Allowing motivated people to take on responsibility is not a question of organisational structure so much as organisational attitude. If the right people can be working on the issues within hours instead of days, a business obtains a huge advantage.</p>

<h1 id="flexibility-succeeds">Flexibility Succeeds</h1>
<p>We need to be flexible in the face of evolving requirements. We should have a crisp decision process to evaluate change, including a provision for re-evaluating our original project goals.</p>

<h1 id="the-internet-did-not-replace-people">The Internet Did Not Replace People</h1>
<p>The Internet helped create Adam Smith’s ideal marketplace, in which buyers and sellers can easily find one another without taking much time or spending much money. Business today is characterised as different combinations of interactions between people: face-to-face, ear-to-ear and keyboard-to-keyboard. The Internet did not replace people. It made them more efficient.</p>

<h1 id="dont-be-lulled-into-inaction">Don’t be Lulled into Inaction</h1>
<p>We always overestimate the change that will occur in the next two years and underestimate the change that will occur in the next 10. Prepare for change – don’t let yourself be lulled into inaction.</p>

<h1 id="business-at-the-speed-of-thought">Business at the Speed of Thought</h1>
<p>You know you have built an excellent digital nervous system when information flows through the organisation as quickly and naturally as thought in a human being – when you can use technology to marshal and coordinate teams of people as quickly as you can focus an individual on an issue. It’s business at the speed of thought.</p>]]></content><author><name>{&quot;twitter&quot; =&gt; &quot;mourjo_sen&quot;}</name></author><category term="musings" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This is article captures my notes and excerpts from Bill Gates’ 1999 article, New Rules, about how businesses should transform themselves in the new millennium.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What Flow Metrics Teaches Us About Designing Resilient Systems</title><link href="https://mourjo.me/blog/musings/2025/03/14/monster-scale-summit-flow-metrics-resilience/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What Flow Metrics Teaches Us About Designing Resilient Systems" /><published>2025-03-14T06:17:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-03-14T06:17:00+01:00</updated><id>https://mourjo.me/blog/musings/2025/03/14/monster-scale-summit-flow-metrics-resilience</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mourjo.me/blog/musings/2025/03/14/monster-scale-summit-flow-metrics-resilience/"><![CDATA[<p>In March this year, I spoke at the Monster Scale Summit 2025, organised by ScyllaDB. It was a career high point to be in this picture – an elite line of speakers, whose books and talks quite literally taught me the craft of software engineering.</p>

<p><img src="/blog/images/2025-03-14-monster-scale-summit-flow-metrics-resilience-1.png" alt="Image Description" /></p>

<p>About sharing the stage with stalwarts of the industry, I got mentioned in a <a href="https://github.com/niledatabase/niledatabase/commit/2301291de907034f3d987ff1e8f0988c0e49ce0b">commit</a> by Gwen Shapira (also a speaker at this conference) for flagging a typo in Nile’s <a href="https://www.thenile.dev">website</a> – a fanboy moment for me!</p>

<p>Anyway, I digress – here is the video to my talk.</p>

<iframe width="100%" height="415" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/aDqtSvORFJc?si=jpmKwAhWVfcChBPM" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>]]></content><author><name>{&quot;twitter&quot; =&gt; &quot;mourjo_sen&quot;}</name></author><category term="musings" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In March this year, I spoke at the Monster Scale Summit 2025, organised by ScyllaDB. It was a career high point to be in this picture – an elite line of speakers, whose books and talks quite literally taught me the craft of software engineering.]]></summary></entry></feed>