<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://mourjo.me/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://mourjo.me/blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-02-15T07:19:20+05:30</updated><id>https://mourjo.me/blog/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Mourjo Sen’s Blog</title><subtitle>Thoughts of a software engineer about life, tech and everything in between. A place to put down my thoughts for my own recollection more than anything else. If you like it, be sure to drop me an email!</subtitle><author><name>{&quot;twitter&quot; =&gt; &quot;mourjo_sen&quot;}</name></author><entry><title type="html">How A Screen Protector Increased My Productivity</title><link href="https://mourjo.me/blog/musings/2025/02/13/how-a-screen-protector-increased-my-productivity/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How A Screen Protector Increased My Productivity" /><published>2025-02-13T09:38:22+05:30</published><updated>2025-02-13T09:38:22+05:30</updated><id>https://mourjo.me/blog/musings/2025/02/13/how-a-screen-protector-increased-my-productivity</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mourjo.me/blog/musings/2025/02/13/how-a-screen-protector-increased-my-productivity/"><![CDATA[<p>“If you care about keeping your phone code secret, you should use this”, the seller said, emphatically pointing to the privacy screen guard. I knew about privacy-protecting screen guards, but I was not looking to buy one when I was at <a href="https://www.tripadvisor.in/Attraction_Review-g304558-d6412735-Reviews-Gariahat_Market-Kolkata_Calcutta_Kolkata_District_West_Bengal.html">Gariahat</a> market a couple of weeks ago. Reluctantly, I gave in and got one for myself. It made my phone miserable to use – yet, it was the best decision I made in the past few weeks.</p>

<p>With a privacy screen protector, other than the person holding a phone, no one can see what is on its screen. I had never used one, so I did not know about its drawbacks – the screen became noticeably dimmer and the resolution worsened resembling a phone from the 2000s. I have to admit, I was quite fond of my new phone’s screen, but with this protector on it, I kept having to zoom in and squint my eyes to read text. Accustomed to a crisp bright display, I now had to make my peace with seeing individual pixels on the screen – it broke my heart.</p>

<p>I made up my mind to remove the protector entirely, but having paid a premium price for it, I decided to keep it on for a week, during which a most surprising turn of events took place. I subconsciously started spending less time on the phone. The lesser appeal of the screen and just that slight struggle to view content nudged me towards spending time doing other – more productive – things than looking at reels on Youtube.</p>

<p>Since that day at Gariahat – two weeks ago now – I have been more present in conversations, more attentive, faster at reading technical documents, getting more sleep, working out more regularly, finished reading the long-pending book <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/list/149264531-mourjo-sen?utf8=✓&amp;utf8=✓&amp;shelf=read&amp;title=mourjo-sen&amp;sort=date_read&amp;order=d">Hail Mary</a>, started reading the <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/68428.Mistborn">Mistborn</a> series and finished preparing my presentation for my upcoming talk at <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=al8Zp3sBYQM&amp;list=PLSV-L4GsXwgn6rhNyjnLMLEtU4cNCPpdB&amp;index=3">Monster Scale 2025</a>. Doing all of this in a span of two weeks, while traveling, would sound undoable to me just a month ago.</p>

<p>In my defense, I never doom scroll on Instagram or spend hours on my phone. I do however look at my phone every now and then – watching videos or scrolling through Bluesky or Reddit in the form of breaks from my day-to-day tasks. I realize now, that it is not the amount of time I spend on the phone that is detrimental to my productivity – it is the frequent interruptions to my flow of work that is. A screen that takes away some of the gratification of social media by adding a little bit of struggle to use the phone, quite counter-intuitively, lowers my urge to use my phone, giving me back precious time I can spend doing just about anything else. I now use my phone when I need to get something done, not for entertainment – or worse, for procrastination.</p>

<p>I want phones to become what they were always intended to be – devices to help us with our daily tasks, instead of the addiction that they have become. Therefore, I wish today’s smart phones had poorer screens, but without sacrificing any of the features that form the foundation of our digital lives – like a great camera, location sharing or biometric authentication. But I doubt that the phone industry will allow phones to become less appealing – after all, one person’s addiction is another person’s source of revenue. It is thus on us to find ways to make our phones less pleasureful. My awful screen guard did just that and I am thankful for it.</p>

<p>Next time you are at the market, consider getting yourself a privacy screen protector – not because you need the privacy, but because you want to get back your productivity.</p>]]></content><author><name>{&quot;twitter&quot; =&gt; &quot;mourjo_sen&quot;}</name></author><category term="musings" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[“If you care about keeping your phone code secret, you should use this”, the seller said, emphatically pointing to the privacy screen guard. I knew about privacy-protecting screen guards, but I was not looking to buy one when I was at Gariahat market a couple of weeks ago. Reluctantly, I gave in and got one for myself. It made my phone miserable to use – yet, it was the best decision I made in the past few weeks.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">I Am Selfish - So I Want To Help You</title><link href="https://mourjo.me/blog/musings/2025/01/26/i-am-selfish-so-i-help-you/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="I Am Selfish - So I Want To Help You" /><published>2025-01-26T10:52:09+05:30</published><updated>2025-01-26T10:52:09+05:30</updated><id>https://mourjo.me/blog/musings/2025/01/26/i-am-selfish-so-i-help-you</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mourjo.me/blog/musings/2025/01/26/i-am-selfish-so-i-help-you/"><![CDATA[<p>I am a software engineer for ten years now. Over these years, I have worked with a number of people to help them navigate the landscape of the industry.</p>

<p>This includes teaching, coaching, mentoring, brainstorming, mock interviews, blog post reviews and career planing. However, I do not do this out of a sense of altruism. The truth is, I benefit from this much more than those who I have helped.</p>

<h3 id="people-take-precedence-over-tech-in-a-tech-industry">People take Precedence Over Tech in a Tech Industry</h3>

<p>The longer I spend in the tech industry, the more I realize that in the grander scheme of things, engineering is more about the people than the software. To that end, the more I help someone the more I understand about the industry.</p>

<p>I want to get ahead. If that means I should help people, I will. Ultimately I want to understand how this complex corporate machine works, how human psychology shapes teams and departments, and at the end of the day how I can become better because of it.</p>

<p>The amount of impact I have as an engineer is limited fundamentally by how fast I can type. The impact increases if I take the limiting factor out of it – eight typing hands are faster than two. To make my vision a reality through others, I need to learn how to communicate my vision to other humans and become the proverbial force-multiplier.</p>

<p>The first step to becoming a better communicator is to offer to listen – to lend a hand to another person, expecting nothing in return but the chance to understand someone’s situation, and when appropriate, offer my advice.</p>

<h3 id="past-experience-is-linear">Past Experience is Linear</h3>

<p>The experiences I have had so far in my life is linear, shaped by the events that happened to me. Some were curated because of the choices I made but most were just luck. If I unlink the past, the future has infinite possibilities, some of which will remain as unknown unknowns if I do not consciously open myself to experiences of others. Simply put, I have a better shot at being successful if I could access other people’s viewpoint of the world.</p>

<p>Many people look back on their experience to take better calls in the present. But experience is linear. You only lived once. By talking to people and by understanding their situation, I am part of a whole different arc of experience. The best thing about this is, while I’m helping someone succeed I am really helping myself.</p>

<p>My mental model of the how the corporate business works gets better with more input signals. If my honest advice helped someone succeed then I have one substantial evidence that my mental model works – and if my advice did not work, my mental model needs to be updated. For example, if I am able to predict a bottleneck in your career growth, and it actually turns out to be so, I can work around it with the next person I mentor – or better yet, I can fix career progression plans for my team/organization.</p>

<h3 id="experience-is-currency-that-can-be-traded-for-perspective">Experience is Currency that can be Traded for Perspective</h3>

<p>As an introvert, communication is the hardest thing I have had to do in my career. Deciding to do so voluntarily was a pivotal moment in career.</p>

<p>It started with writing blog posts like this one. The idea then was to get the learnings out of my head and onto a piece of paper. Of course, imposter syndrome was not easy to overcome, but owing to a few good leaders, I got the courage to spread the word.</p>

<p>After getting a few thousand reads on <a href="http://mourjo.medium.com/">Medium</a>, I ventured into speaking at conferences and then mentoring junior engineers. At that point I discovered a citical flaw in how I wrote or how I spoke — I had inadvertently made the narrative about myself. When I learn something, or when I make changes to a codebase, that is about me. But when I write and when I speak, it is about the reader and listener – that demands a different focus.</p>

<p>A particularly harsh critique of how my mentoring style highlighted to me that the narrative had to be external to myself. Thus came the epiphany – when the perspective that matters is external, and all I have is my internal thinking ability, I need a way to learn how others perceive what I write, say or do. I cannot probe into the thinking process of others, I can only think for myself — I needed to have that external vantage point and perspective.</p>

<p>There are no free lunches. The only way I would earn an external perspective was by putting something worth on the table for someone else. That is when it hit me – my five years of experience was the currency I could trade for that external perspective. I scratch your back, you scratch mine.</p>

<h3 id="not-everything-is-measurable---nor-should-it-be">Not Everything is Measurable - Nor Should It Be</h3>

<p>During a phase in my early career, I became so consumed with the pursuit of perfecting my end-of-year performance score that I lost sight of everything else – doing to the letter only those things that I thought moved the scoring needle.</p>

<p>One day, the expectation of my job changed overnight – as a senior engineer, my performance was not so much about my technical abilities as much as it was about my contributions to the larger team. Everything I had been doing thus far in my career fell flat on its face because the evaluation criteria changed and I was not prepared for it.</p>

<p>Getting caught in the labyrinth of changing expectations brought me dangerously close to a burnout – only to be saved by a revelation that came to me not as a sudden burst of light but as a gradual dawn. My definition of success was not well-founded.</p>

<p>An organization begins at the individual’s limits – we cannot do on our own what we can do together. Just like the neurons in our brains communicate with each other to form consciousness, so do social interactions form the substrate of collective success. As I relied on my performance score, I missed the larger picture – the ultimate goal for anyone is to add value for the organization. Realizing that the performance score was not the goal unlocked my mental block that social interactions are where collective success sprouts. And that cannot be measured – nor should it be.</p>

<h3 id="i-advise-you-to-be-selfish">I Advise You to be Selfish</h3>
<p>Capitalism works. While it makes a few people very rich, through natural market forces, capitalism also incentivises building good products. A company ultimately wants to maximise its profits (thus being selfish), but the way to increase profits is to build products that solve problems for people. True profit lies in the creation of value. It is a virtuous cycle that does not work if one is not selfish – building good products earns profit which enables making even better products.</p>

<p>If, while prioritizing my own growth, I am able to contribute more effectively to my organization, elevate my personal brand, and improve my performance, then such self-interest is not only justified but is essential to create a virtuous cycle of value addition.</p>

<p>I am selfish and I advise you to be selfish too.</p>]]></content><author><name>{&quot;twitter&quot; =&gt; &quot;mourjo_sen&quot;}</name></author><category term="musings" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I am a software engineer for ten years now. Over these years, I have worked with a number of people to help them navigate the landscape of the industry.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Overcoming Barriers To Entry: Writing With Obsidian</title><link href="https://mourjo.me/blog/musings/2025/01/08/overcoming-barriers-to-entry-writing-with-obsidian/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Overcoming Barriers To Entry: Writing With Obsidian" /><published>2025-01-08T17:56:53+05:30</published><updated>2025-01-08T17:56:53+05:30</updated><id>https://mourjo.me/blog/musings/2025/01/08/overcoming-barriers-to-entry-writing-with-obsidian</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mourjo.me/blog/musings/2025/01/08/overcoming-barriers-to-entry-writing-with-obsidian/"><![CDATA[<p>“In ten years you’ll see me as a writer”. My 2008 yearbook would be disappointed in how things turned out. But it is the new year and it is never too late to start.</p>

<p>If I am being honest, though, I have not entirely lost touch with writing – only that today it serves quite a different purpose. Back in school, I wrote because I found it to be the easiest way of expressing myself. Today, writing has become the fabric for a structured thinking process.</p>

<p>I do not write as much as I had wanted to in 2008 – at least not for the joy of it. Take this post as a rite of passing to find my way back to writing for the joy of it – not long-form technical articles or mindmaps which require a lot of effort and research, but reflections and musings – an evolutionary next step from my short-form LinkedIn posts.</p>

<h1 id="why-write-at-all-active-externalism">Why Write at all: Active Externalism</h1>

<p>Putting pen to paper lays structure to otherwise haphazard thought processes — a structure with a clear narrative that is consumable for others. Engineers do not work in isolation, and in order to collaborate, a structured thinking is key. Writing is one way to put structure to haphazard thoughts.</p>

<p>While at the surface writing does not seem to be a hard requirement of the software engineer’s job, structured thinking is. Writing helps convoluted, passing thoughts take a more permanent form, which my future self can come back to – ideas fleet, written artefacts remain. In fact, the permanence of written artefacts has influenced in setting better goals for myself – from haphazard maybes to definitive idea execution plans.</p>

<p>In the 1998 paper <a href="https://www.alice.id.tue.nl/references/clark-chalmers-1998.pdf">“The extended mind”</a>, Clark and Chalmers posit that our human minds go beyond the boundaries of skin and skull – that elements in our environment play a great role in driving our cognitive processes.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Where does the mind stop and the rest of the world begin? The human organism is linked with an external entity in a two-way interaction, creating a coupled system that can be seen as a cognitive system in its own right. All the components in the system play an active causal role, and they jointly govern behaviour in the same sort of way that cognition usually does.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The authors call this active externalism – an extension of our cognitive processes. Writing in some way has been an extension of my cognitive process, just like the calculator became an integral part of my math classes. Just like me being faster at typing with qwerty keyboards now than writing with my own hands.</p>

<p>The process of note-taking has become an extension of my thought process.</p>

<h1 id="writing-for-myself">Writing for Myself</h1>
<p>Reflecting on things is one way to get self feedback. Looking back is a way to improve myself going forward. Writing about things as I look at them today after my ten years of experience may help you, perhaps it won’t. Perhaps in another ten years, I will see how naive I am today and advise you to do better – or perhaps not. Perhaps, perhaps, perhaps… But it definitely won’t help you or me if what I write never sees the light of day.</p>

<p>Unfortunately most of what I wrote over the years stayed private or got lost – imposter syndrome is not easy to escape. This changed over the course of 2024. I started with short-form LinkedIn posts, which did not need much scrutiny or proof reading. I got few likes on those posts and that reinforced my loosely held belief that it is better to write than to perfect writing.</p>

<h1 id="idea-capturing-where-do-good-ideas-come-from">Idea Capturing: Where do Good Ideas come from?</h1>
<p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=NugRZGDbPFU">Good ideas come from hunches</a> - and hunches consistently occur to me when and where I least expect it – in the middle of the night while getting a glass of water, on the commute back home after a tough day at the office, atop the snowy peaks of the <a href="https://mourjo.me/blog/non-tech/2024/12/29/alluring-austria/">Austrian Alps</a>.</p>

<p>It is not guaranteed by any stretch of the imagination that I will recall any of the fleeting ideas the next time I sit at the laptop. This is why I started using <a href="https://obsidian.md">Obsidian</a> to keep a day-to-day log of thoughts on the go – it simply works on every device I own – making idea capturing possible anywhere.</p>

<h1 id="idea-presenting-breaking-the-barrier-to-writing">Idea Presenting: Breaking the Barrier to Writing</h1>
<p>Writing is not just about the idea, writing is equally about the presentation. “Write without inhibition, edit with clarity”, as Jared explains in <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ZcljLAmDIY4">this video</a>. Again, Obsidian plays a key role for me here.</p>

<p>I maintain a static blog built with <a href="https://jekyllrb.com">Jekyll</a>. Both use <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Markdown">Markdown</a> files but because Markdown is primarily a text based format, the blog-writing experience on Markdown is suboptimal:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Pasting images is not easy – even less so if it involves the additional step of transferring photos from my mobile phone to my laptop</li>
  <li>Pasting links on like <a href="https://mourjo.me">this</a> needs to be done in the esoteric Markdown syntax, which breaks the flow of writing</li>
  <li>No direct support for code formatting</li>
  <li>Markdown tables are not easy to work with</li>
  <li>Text wrapping, bold fonts, italics and live preview requires manual setup</li>
</ul>

<p>I would not like to spend too much time on the mechanics of the writing – I would much rather spend the time in the narrative of it –  as the New York Times bestseller <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Fr5kWGWCcMs">Joshua Fields Millburn puts it</a> , “if it doesn’t push the narrative forward, then it doesn’t have the urgency you need to be compelling for your readers”.</p>

<h1 id="the-writing-process">The Writing Process</h1>

<p>I am writing this post on Obsidian - with the help of <a href="https://github.com/mourjo/blog/blob/master/copy_from_obsidian.py">a simple Python script</a>, I can migrate a file that <a href="https://gist.githubusercontent.com/mourjo/3698cef9dc1c9fff79ea98b8f9337f41/raw/7fd22fcfd76f2cfad1e4a1587a01a12a4c36f002/2025-01-06-overcoming-barriers-to-entry-writing-with-obsidian.md">looks like this</a> to Jekyll (the idea came from <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=dnE7c0ELEH8">this video</a> by NetworkChuck). This script allows me to keep my writing experience entirely on Obsidian.</p>

<p>Following are a few indications of making writing a joy with Obsidian and publishing to my blog.</p>

<h3 id="code-blocks">Code Blocks</h3>
<p>Most markdown flavours support code blocks, but again, it’s the experience of writing that seals the deal.</p>

<pre><code class="language-java">public class HelloWorld {
	public static void main(String args[]) {
		System.out.println("Hello, world!");
	}
}
</code></pre>

<h3 id="tables">Tables</h3>
<p>Often used but tables in Markdown are notoriously hard to get right, especially in simple text editors. Obsidian’s preview makes tables as friendly as Google docs. Well almost.</p>

<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>No</th>
      <th>Topic</th>
      <th>Description</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>1</td>
      <td>Obsidian - tips and tricks</td>
      <td>Basics of using a note-taking tool</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>2</td>
      <td>Effective writing</td>
      <td>Quickly jotting notes down that later become full fledged blog posts</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<h3 id="mermaid-diagrams">Mermaid Diagrams</h3>

<p>It is a super power to generate scalable <a href="https://mermaid.js.org">Mermaid images</a> like this:</p>

<pre><code class="language-mermaid">pie
    title Writing Use Cases
    "Experience Report" : 56
    "Code Snippets" : 180
    "Reflection" : 386 
</code></pre>

<h3 id="informational-callouts">Informational Callouts</h3>
<p>A simple format like Markdown doesn’t support much more than basic formatting. But sometimes I have found myself using call-outs to draw attention to an idea or mark an open question - like the one below.</p>

<div class="callout callout-question">
  <div class="callout-title">Idea for writing?</div>
  <div class="callout-content">- A <a href="https://github.com/mourjo/blog/blob/master/_plugins/obsidian_callouts_converter.rb">plugin</a> that converts Obsidian callouts to Jekyll</div>
</div>

<h3 id="math">Math</h3>
<p>A software engineer is bound to encounter math in some shape or form. But even if you don’t like Math, you have got to admire the LaTex style of mathematical equations:</p>

\[P(A∣B)=\frac{P(A \cap B)}{P(B)}\]

<h3 id="images">Images</h3>

<p>I’m writing this post on my mobile, while pasting an image as I would with my private notes. Without me ever having to transfer it, the same image is copied and published to this blog with <a href="https://github.com/mourjo/blog/blob/master/copy_from_obsidian.py">a Python script</a>.</p>

<p><img src="/blog/images/2025-01-08-overcoming-barriers-to-entry-writing-with-obsidian-1.jpeg" alt="Image Description" /></p>

<h1 id="conclusion-why-writing-matters">Conclusion: Why Writing Matters</h1>
<p>Last month I went to Austria with my family – a much needed break to heaven on Earth. I took down <a href="https://mourjo.me/blog/non-tech/2024/12/29/alluring-austria/">a few notes</a> about what I want to recall looking back – and a picture for each day. It has been just a few weeks and I have already started forgetting the details – that is why writing matters – <strong>to put a more permanent form to fleeting thoughts.</strong></p>

<p>Though I do not believe in new year’s resolutions, this is a promise and a way forward to writing more in 2025.</p>]]></content><author><name>{&quot;twitter&quot; =&gt; &quot;mourjo_sen&quot;}</name></author><category term="musings" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[“In ten years you’ll see me as a writer”. My 2008 yearbook would be disappointed in how things turned out. But it is the new year and it is never too late to start.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Having Some Fucking Fun</title><link href="https://mourjo.me/blog/musings/2025/01/05/having-some-fucking-fun/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Having Some Fucking Fun" /><published>2025-01-05T16:10:28+05:30</published><updated>2025-01-05T16:10:28+05:30</updated><id>https://mourjo.me/blog/musings/2025/01/05/having-some-fucking-fun</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mourjo.me/blog/musings/2025/01/05/having-some-fucking-fun/"><![CDATA[<p>A day in a software engineer’s week becomes blurry from one another. It is not uncommon to get caught up in the rut of things. Today happens to be one of those slow Sunday mornings at the end of a busy week. I have a lot of reading to catch up on, but I just cannot concentrate on any of it.</p>

<p>Sure, I do many things at my job that I have grown to love (the yellows) – writing about software, designing systems, technical leadership, planning… But all of the things I have grown to love have their roots somehow to the crux of what I truly enjoy doing (the greens): writing code – for no reason, for no outcome, for no one – just me building something where there was nothing.</p>

<p><img src="/blog/images/2025-01-05-having-some-fucking-fun-1.png" alt="Image Description" /></p>

<p>On good weeks, the yellows often become greens, and the reds start looking like yellows. I know I am having a bad day when the yellows start resembling the reds. As I grow older, I start recognising – and thereby paying homage – to the few constants I can rely on on a cold slow Sunday – the never-changing greens.</p>

<p><img src="/blog/images/2025-01-05-having-some-fucking-fun-2.png" alt="Image Description" /></p>

<p>In the show, Ted Lasso, football is to the players, what software engineering is to me – I do it because I enjoy it. In all honesty though, I would be lying if I said I love every bit of it.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>During my career, when I was going through a bad patch, I’d come back here and play.</p>

  <p>I brought you here to remind you that football is a fucking game that you used to play as a fucking kid because it was fun. Even when you were getting your fucking legs broken or your fucking feelings hurt. So fuck your feelings, fuck your overthinking, fuck all that bullshit. Go back out there and have some fucking fun.</p>

  <p>– Roy Kent (Ted Lasso)</p>
</blockquote>

<p>For me, having fun means going back to writing code – leaving all the rest aside. To that end, today I <a href="https://github.com/mourjo/monster-scale-2025">wrote a load-shedding server using Spring Boot</a>.</p>

<p>For anyone who needs this: If you are in a rut, find your never-changing greens, <em>go back out there and have some fucking fun.</em></p>]]></content><author><name>{&quot;twitter&quot; =&gt; &quot;mourjo_sen&quot;}</name></author><category term="musings" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A day in a software engineer’s week becomes blurry from one another. It is not uncommon to get caught up in the rut of things. Today happens to be one of those slow Sunday mornings at the end of a busy week. I have a lot of reading to catch up on, but I just cannot concentrate on any of it.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Alluring Austria</title><link href="https://mourjo.me/blog/non-tech/2024/12/29/alluring-austria/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Alluring Austria" /><published>2024-12-29T21:13:42+05:30</published><updated>2024-12-29T21:13:42+05:30</updated><id>https://mourjo.me/blog/non-tech/2024/12/29/alluring-austria</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mourjo.me/blog/non-tech/2024/12/29/alluring-austria/"><![CDATA[<p>I woke up at the wee hours of the morning, excited to finally take the trip to Austria, which we had been planning for months. The last few weeks were quite stressful at work, and I was very earnestly looking forward to a break. Any vacation would have been the break I needed but Austria was nothing short of alluring.</p>

<h1 id="22nd-december---arriving-in-austria">22nd December - Arriving in Austria</h1>

<p>The flight from Amsterdam to  the captivating city of Vienna was an hour-and-a-half long. The temperature was colder than in Amsterdam but there is no wind. Still, with the same amount of rain and absence of the sun, it felt much more comfortable here.</p>

<p>We dropped our bags at the hotel and went for a walk around the city centre (a UNESCO world heritage site), discovering the awe-striking architecture and jubilating Christmas spirit. I was transfixed at the thought that Vienna played a critical role in both world wars, houses United Nations headquarters, and is the city of both Mozart and Beethoven. It is certainly an old city hiding many stories, countless struggles and much wisdom.</p>

<p>Although we were naturally tired from the day’s travels, we made it a point to go to Vienna’s famous Christmas market in front of the glowing parliament building. To conclude the day, we partook in the city’s coffeehouse culture and dined at the famous Café Landtmann.</p>

<p><img src="/blog/images/2024-12-29-alluring-austria-1.jpeg" alt="Image Description" /></p>

<h1 id="23rd-december---viennas-wonder">23rd December - Vienna’s Wonder</h1>
<p>I woke up with a mild headache, perhaps from last night’s cold – I remember it being chilly and windy, not unlike Amsterdam. The wind reduces the temperature by five degrees, it feels.</p>

<p>The trams in Vienna go through narrow inner streets, quite hard to imagine it’s the same city with five-lane main roads. Different parts of the city have their own distinguishing character, and they coexist in harmony. The city has a blend of historical charm and modern vibrancy – buildings and telephone booths of decades past in coexistence with fast cars and modern camera phones in the hands of its citizens.</p>

<p>Our first stop today was Schönbrunn Palace. We bought a couple of jars of very spicy pickle made from Habanero (a type of Capsicum) from the Christmas market in the palace grounds. In the Christmas market, there were bales of hay for children to climb on, reminding me of the episode from The Office where Dwight builds a hay palace in the parking lot. We then went to Belvedere Palace, which although not as famous, had a much more scenic (and possibly larger) garden. Right across from Belvedere Palace was a Greek restaurant, which served us a really hearty chicken soup. But frankly, the warmth of the cafe made us much happier than the food!</p>

<p>In the evening, to commemorate the trip I gifted Mohana a ring made by the Austrian jewellery brand Swarovski. I had been wanting to gift her one for six months, ever since I first went to a Swarovski store in Amsterdam to buy a wedding gift for Ritvika. Prior to that, I never had the courage or the intent to buy jewellery from such an expensive luxury brand! Today though, I could afford to get one for my wife. Happy days. Of all the things I look forward to in life, all the promotions, all the bonuses, none of it will have been worth it if I could not get something nice for her. Come layoffs or not, today was a fulfilling day.</p>

<p><img src="/blog/images/2024-12-29-alluring-austria-2.jpeg" alt="Image Description" /></p>

<h1 id="24th-december---infatuated-by-innsbruck">24th December - Infatuated by Innsbruck</h1>

<p>We left Vienna for Innsbruck today, which I knew to be a much colder and smaller city. On the one hand, I am not very fond of small towns, even less so coming from the grand architectural backdrop of Vienna. On the other hand, I was quite excited about the prospect of visiting a snowy Alpine town that was twice a home to the Winter Olympics.</p>

<p>As the train approached the town, the density of snow on the ground kept rising - by the time we reached, everything was covered in a feet of snow, it was quite the view! My enthusiasm was at par with that of the youngest member of our group - five year old Brinda. Nature’s ability to captivate us transcends barriers of age.</p>

<p>In the afternoon, we found ourselves quite puzzled that there were no open restaurants or grocery stores. After a while of wandering the empty streets, we shared Italian pizzas for lunch at the only open eatery we could find, and even they insisted on closing shop soon. We learned later that in Austria, Christmas is celebrated widely on the eve much more than on the day.</p>

<p><img src="/blog/images/2024-12-29-alluring-austria-3.jpeg" alt="Image Description" /></p>

<h1 id="25th-december---my-first-white-christmas">25th December - My first white Christmas</h1>

<p>It was Christmas morning in the snow-clad village of Innsbruck. Mohana and I left the warm hotel room to take a walk in -8 degrees. We saw the sunrise reflect on the grand white mountain peaks, we slipped on the snow, we held hands in allure of this mortal world’s incomprehensible beauty. Neither pictures nor words could capture the scenic marvel.</p>

<p>After a sumptuous breakfast at the hotel, we went to the old town centre at Innsbruck in the sun as the snow glistened and the mountains in the backdrop looked upon us. We spent some time in the city and then went to a ski resort — as we played with snowballs and made snow-angels, I recognized that this was my first white Christmas – with not a speck of green grass visible.</p>

<p>As I beheld the majestic mountains, my thoughts turned to my childhood. One of the many great things my father taught me is to seek out inner peace and inner happiness, thereby unburdening myself of seeking external admiration – just as the mountains surely do not stand there for our admiration. After all these years, I think all of it made sense right then and there - we are just insignificant footnotes in the face of nature’s vast allure. I felt a touch of inner peace at the sight of these massive snow-draped ranges.</p>

<p>When we came back, we played the game of Dixit and had dinner at the hotel.</p>

<p><img src="/blog/images/2024-12-29-alluring-austria-4.jpeg" alt="Image Description" /></p>

<h1 id="26th-december---leaving-the-mountains-behind">26th December - Leaving the mountains behind</h1>

<p>The sun rose quietly in Innsbruck, afraid of waking the sleeping mountains. There was a constant calmness that came with the cold morning air. At a distance, a church bell’s toll sheared the stillness of the cold atmosphere – as if to acknowledge an onlooker’s gaze.</p>

<p>We left the snow capped hills behind as we headed towards Salzburg. I did not yet know what was in store after Innsbruck but I would be lying if I said I was happy to leave. Innsbruck was heaven on earth, in every sense of the word. Every sight was a postcard, every photograph a masterpiece. Majestic mountains at the distance, at its foot the little houses in the valley – paying homage to the might of the giant hills. The mountains in turn protecting the valley from the rest of the world. A harmony borne of balance and mutual respect. Behind them all was a clear blue sky and a golden sun’s morning rays reflecting on a landscape coated in icing sugar. A chime of wrens flew by, celebrating just another day in paradise.</p>

<p>The train shot away at 250 kilometres an hour, ploughing through a snow covered land, from the window it looked like airplanes going through white clouds. I really liked the coniferous trees with snow resting on its branches giving it a shaded look from afar. Forests look like wolves with coloured fur.</p>

<p>When we finally reached the city of sound of music, Salzburg, we went to Fortress Hohensalzburg, the view was breathtaking but soon it became very cold. Battling the cold, we sat down to enjoy a hot wiener sausage and called it a day. Back in the hotel, we gathered around like old friends, and chatted about life in Amsterdam and Singapore and of the days of boyhood wonder and childish pranks in the streets of Calcutta. Sometimes that is all you need, the quiet embrace of family and familiarity.</p>

<p><img src="/blog/images/2024-12-29-alluring-austria-5.jpeg" alt="Image Description" /></p>

<h1 id="27th-december---a-snow-kissed-village">27th December - A Snow-kissed Village</h1>

<p>We went to an UNESCO village called Halstad from Salzburg. On the way to Halstad, the sun rose as we climbed the mountains, golden sun rays gently caressing the untouched snow. Standing before us, was a wonderful view of a frozen village – beautifully nestled in the Alps covered in snow next to a lake. Honestly, I thought this trip would be good. But even in my most hopeful optimism, I didn’t think it would be this good. I consider this to be the best trip I have ever taken thus far, including Switzerland, Egypt and incredible India.</p>

<p>It is hard to believe such an alluring land gave birth to one of humanity’s most tyrannical leaders. No one spec of dirt can diminish the enduring splendour of this land. I guess kindness always prevails, humanity always prevails, beauty always prevails notwithstanding the worst son of Austria.</p>

<p>We came back to Salzburg in the afternoon with a twinkle in our eyes. The ride back to Salzburg was a peek into nature’s unspoilt beauty – the bus ride went through hilly coniferous forests and vast trenches of land completely covered in snow. We walked around Salzburg, went to Mirabel garden, visited Mozart house (where he was born) and then to a pebble beach and threw skipping stones into the river. Simple pleasures of life. </p>

<p><img src="/blog/images/2024-12-29-alluring-austria-6.jpeg" alt="Image Description" /></p>

<h1 id="28th-december---a-misdirection">28th December - A Misdirection</h1>

<p>We left from the hotel at Salzburg on the way to Vienna, one last huzzah before we head back to Amsterdam. As fate would have it, a couple of us got on the wrong train! We went ahead of the group with the intention of reserving window seats. Little did we know that there was another train at the same platform to same destination at the same time. Once the train pulled away earlier than our expectations, we discerned our blunder. We pulled the SOS button in the hope of stopping the train and we got seriously reprimanded by the ticket checker! We got off at the next station at Linz and joined the rest of our group when our intended train arrived – thankfully both trains did stop at the same station.</p>

<p>While we were on the wrong train, we worried that we might be charged a fine for sounding the alarm. We spoke about how life often gives us situations beyond our control. Somehow, my thoughts went to Negi, a friend of my brother, who tragically lost his life to a silent brain tumour, life can be harsh if it so wants and there is nothing one can do about it. One of us brought up the story of a cancer survivor, who fought for fifteen years but in the end, fortune was on his side. রাখে হরি মারে কে, মারে হরি রাখে কে?</p>

<p>As the correct train approached Linz, we almost missed the train again because it was only a minute’s stop. Although we managed to get on the right train at Linz. Unfortunately, we were separated from the rest of the group because the train had two parts with an engine in the middle. Therefore, it was not possible to go where the rest of them are sitting! So at the station after Linz, we again went out of the train, and finally made it to the right compartment in the right train! We did finally return to Vienna - the city’s architecture never ceased to catch my awe – even after our little trainwreck.</p>

<p>After reaching Vienna, we went to Kunsthistorisches Museum Wien (Art History Museum). We saw items from ancient Egypt, ancient Greece, Roman era, and paintings. Of all the artefacts, the one that caught my eye was called “Triumph of St. Michael over Satan” by 
Johann Schnegg. It was a statue made of ivory, depicting St. Michael in white and Satan in black – an yin-yang of a different kind.</p>

<p>We realised soon that owing to the train debacle earlier in the morning, we blissfully forgot about lunch and all of us were hungry - we had to rush to a restaurant from the museum – we had dinner at six in the evening, a quite hearty meal, like all hungry stomachs deserve.</p>

<p>Soon after, I slept off early to catch the morning flight back to Amsterdam.</p>

<p><img src="/blog/images/2024-12-29-alluring-austria-7.jpeg" alt="Image Description" /></p>]]></content><author><name>{&quot;twitter&quot; =&gt; &quot;mourjo_sen&quot;}</name></author><category term="non-tech" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I woke up at the wee hours of the morning, excited to finally take the trip to Austria, which we had been planning for months. The last few weeks were quite stressful at work, and I was very earnestly looking forward to a break. Any vacation would have been the break I needed but Austria was nothing short of alluring.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">On Never Being The Smartest Person In The Room</title><link href="https://mourjo.me/blog/musings/2024/12/07/on-never-being-the-smartest-person-in-the-room/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On Never Being The Smartest Person In The Room" /><published>2024-12-07T12:18:59+05:30</published><updated>2024-12-07T12:18:59+05:30</updated><id>https://mourjo.me/blog/musings/2024/12/07/on-never-being-the-smartest-person-in-the-room</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mourjo.me/blog/musings/2024/12/07/on-never-being-the-smartest-person-in-the-room/"><![CDATA[<p>I am never the smartest person in the room – and that’s okay. I am almost never the tallest person in the room either.</p>

<p>It is a lost game, in my opinion, the pursuit of being the best at anything in a world of 8 billion people. Trying to be the best or rather, trying to <em>be portrayed to be the best</em>, incentivises the wrong behaviour. Admitting that I am not the smartest person in the room unburdens me from proving to an external observer and to myself, that I am the smartest.</p>

<p>I can instead utilise every opportunity to learn from anyone who has an interesting idea – be it the college graduate who only joined the team last week or the veteran who has been often called an outdated dinosaur. Here is a list of things I would never have learnt about if smartness ego battles got in the way (battles I would have miserably lost):</p>
<ul>
  <li>Communicating sequential processes and <a href="https://github.com/clojure/core.async">core/async</a> in Clojure</li>
  <li>The practice of note-taking in <a href="https://obsidian.md/">Obsidian</a> and the <a href="https://www.buildingasecondbrain.com/">second brain</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://medium.com/booking-com-development/hexagonal-architecture-a-practical-guide-5bc6d5a6a056">Hexagonal architecture</a></li>
  <li>A <a href="https://medium.com/curious-burrows/the-story-of-open-source-so-far-bfcb685d85a4">laser printer’s</a> relation to open source</li>
  <li>Better command line tools <a href="https://zaiste.net/posts/shell-commands-rust/">written in Rust</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://otee.dev/2021/12/31/looking-back-2021.html">Courage</a> to do the right thing when it is not easy</li>
</ul>

<p>I am <em>never going to be the smartest person in the room</em>, but I can be the person who wants to learn the most in the room – and then come out of that room a <em>relatively smarter version of myself</em>.</p>]]></content><author><name>{&quot;twitter&quot; =&gt; &quot;mourjo_sen&quot;}</name></author><category term="musings" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I am never the smartest person in the room – and that’s okay. I am almost never the tallest person in the room either.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Relevance of Developer Tooling in the Age of AI</title><link href="https://mourjo.me/blog/musings/2024/12/06/dev-tooling-in-the-age-of-ai/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Relevance of Developer Tooling in the Age of AI" /><published>2024-12-06T11:52:50+05:30</published><updated>2024-12-06T11:52:50+05:30</updated><id>https://mourjo.me/blog/musings/2024/12/06/dev-tooling-in-the-age-of-ai</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mourjo.me/blog/musings/2024/12/06/dev-tooling-in-the-age-of-ai/"><![CDATA[<p>I have worked with unconventional languages all <a href="https://mourjo.me/cv.pdf">throughout my career</a> - from Clojure and Elixir to bash and lately, Perl. Whether statically typed or not, the success of a language today <em>depends heavily on the developer tooling and developer experience</em>.</p>

<p>Code is only just a means to an end — the end being value addition for the customer. Languages with extensive tooling make it easier for developers, thereby increasing their value proposition to the business. I find that the effectiveness of the median developer is dependent on a language’s tooling support - finding usages of a method, renaming a method, stepping through a codepath just to see where something gets updated, and so on…</p>

<p>This is the kind of <a href="https://www.markhneedham.com/blog/2010/03/18/essential-and-accidental-complexity/">accidental complexity</a> that today’s tech ecosystem is ossified by – <strong>missing language capabilities being solved with tooling has led to an over-reliance of developers on the tooling rather than the language itself</strong>. Think about it — would you write Java without Lombok or boilerplate code generation?</p>

<blockquote>

  <p>It’s hard to imagine a surer sign that one is dealing with an irrational economic system than the fact that the prospect of eliminating drudgery is considered to be a problem.</p>

  <p>– David Graeber, <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/38217638-bullshit-jobs">Bullshit Jobs: A Theory</a></p>

</blockquote>

<p>With LLMs to assist developers writing code, I think <em>the value proposition of developer tooling will take a new shape</em>. There will always be a need for some sort of tooling, but it may turn out to be <em>general-purpose tools</em>, rather than <em>language-specific ones</em> that win.</p>

<p>In a world where the barrier to entry into coding is lower, the test of a language’s success will depend solely (and rightly) on its ability to deliver business value. If a language is fundamentally more effective in doing so – irrespective of its tooling – it may come out on top in the age of AI.</p>

<p>After years of working with Java (and relying heavily on the tooling ecosystem), I will now be betting on Clojure.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>It is just simpler, and easier, and less occluding to write expressive code in Clojure. It requires fewer lines. It requires fewer characters. It requires fewer hours. It requires fewer mental gymnastics. Lisp (Clojure) is functional. And the future is looking very functional to me.</p>

  <p>– <a href="https://blog.cleancoder.com/uncle-bob/2019/08/22/WhyClojure.html">Uncle Bob</a></p>
</blockquote>]]></content><author><name>{&quot;twitter&quot; =&gt; &quot;mourjo_sen&quot;}</name></author><category term="musings" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I have worked with unconventional languages all throughout my career - from Clojure and Elixir to bash and lately, Perl. Whether statically typed or not, the success of a language today depends heavily on the developer tooling and developer experience.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Motivation Is Not Everything</title><link href="https://mourjo.me/blog/musings/2024/12/04/motivation-is-not-everything/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Motivation Is Not Everything" /><published>2024-12-04T00:01:00+05:30</published><updated>2024-12-04T00:01:00+05:30</updated><id>https://mourjo.me/blog/musings/2024/12/04/motivation-is-not-everything</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mourjo.me/blog/musings/2024/12/04/motivation-is-not-everything/"><![CDATA[<p>This year, I did not miss a <em>single</em> day of learning French on Duolingo, even though sometimes only for five minutes. Through it, I learnt a lot about the process of learning, looking back:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Motivation</strong> comes and goes, relying on motivation alone is unsustainable</li>
  <li>There will be good days and there will be better days</li>
  <li><strong>Showing up every day</strong> is winning half the battle</li>
  <li>I overestimated what I can do in a day</li>
  <li>I underestimated what I can do in a year</li>
</ul>

<p>There are very few things that pay off as much as self discipline and <a href="https://mourjo.me/blog/non-tech/2021/10/25/on-building-habits/">habit forming</a>.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Some people say the most important thing a fighter can have is heart. Frankie’d say: show me a fighter who was nothing but heart and I’ll show you a man waiting for a beating.
– Million Dollar Baby</p>
</blockquote>

<p><img src="/blog/images/2024-12-04-motivation-is-not-everything-1.png" alt="Image Description" /></p>]]></content><author><name>{&quot;twitter&quot; =&gt; &quot;mourjo_sen&quot;}</name></author><category term="musings" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This year, I did not miss a single day of learning French on Duolingo, even though sometimes only for five minutes. Through it, I learnt a lot about the process of learning, looking back: Motivation comes and goes, relying on motivation alone is unsustainable There will be good days and there will be better days Showing up every day is winning half the battle I overestimated what I can do in a day I underestimated what I can do in a year There are very few things that pay off as much as self discipline and habit forming.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">In memoriam</title><link href="https://mourjo.me/blog/non-tech/2024/01/04/in-memoriam/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="In memoriam" /><published>2024-01-04T01:07:12+05:30</published><updated>2024-01-04T01:07:12+05:30</updated><id>https://mourjo.me/blog/non-tech/2024/01/04/in-memoriam</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mourjo.me/blog/non-tech/2024/01/04/in-memoriam/"><![CDATA[<p>The similarity was uncanny. Over the years, I remember comparing my palm side-by-side to his - it is an almost identical copy of Dadua’s. In fact, I would say it with pride – a cherished emblem that I carried with a sense of honour. When I heard the heartbreaking news at three in the morning, my immediate response was to look at my own palm in the dim light of the smartphone, not knowing what this meant or how to feel about it.</p>

<p><em>I kept staring at my palm in the engulfing darkness of the cold Dutch night.</em></p>

<p>As a child of parents with transferable jobs, my boyhood unfolded across various locations: Alipore, Birbhum, Bardhaman and Salt Lake. One place that was constant throughout was Lake Temple Road and Dadua. My earliest memories as a child were with Dadua. His cane with an elephant’s trunk curve at the end, his fast strides which were so hard for my short legs to keep up with, the crisp morning air of Rabindra Sarobar lake before day break, and of course the “notun jinish dekhbo” which was an euphemism for toys without my mother realising I am asking for something new.</p>

<p>While I was too young to fully remember the morning walks I took with Dadua, fragments of those memories linger in my mind. I recall moments such as meeting his friends by the lake, to the local chaiwalla who knew precisely what everyone wanted, to the almost superhero names I had for each of his friends (like Amloki-dadu and Bhim-dadu). Sometimes in the evenings he would take me for a walk around the lake as well, but this time, it was not to meet his friends, but to have a Vadilal ice cream and sometimes freshly roasted peanuts. To this day, the smell of warm peanuts takes me back to that time. I was old enough when I got the news of him passing away in his sleep, yet deep down, I was still the little boy who yearns for one more morning walk with his grandfather.</p>

<p><em>I kept staring at my palm in the engulfing darkness of the cold Dutch night.</em></p>

<p>In Bardhaman, we resided in an expansive estate adorned with boundless fields of crops and parks full of flowers and orchards teeming with trees. I remember Dadua took me on a tour of the estate sharing his knowledge about crops and the art of nurturing plant life. As a lifelong gardener himself, he imparted a wealth of wisdom to my uncomprehending preadolescent ears.</p>

<p>Although I may not recall the intricacies of gardening techniques, certain moments are indelibly engraved as if they were from last week. One such recollection is him showing me how to collect dried seeds from different fruits and use them as beads to play with and make little craft items of it. Of all the toys I received as gifts that birthday in Bardhaman, today I seem to only recall this: a concoction of odd plant seeds that remain etched in memory because of the loving embrace of a grandfather and the spark of creativity that was so very characteristic of Dadua.</p>

<p>He not only was creative himself, but ignited creativity in others too. I daresay, my mother’s fondness for recitation was kindled by Dadua. During one summer, I made a toy “smart” watch from a piece of black cardboard and a few hand-drawn digital dials. Mimi took me to a tailor to procure an elastic strap for the watch band, and with Dadua’s assistance, we assembled it all together. While I merely did it to emulate all the watch-wearing grown ups around me, Dadua confided in me that as a boy he also used scrap material as a child to craft things. This early inclination eventually led him to create his vast collection of handmade artefacts. I recall he said to me a few years later that art is different to each of us –  everyone looking at the same tree but since every other person is seeing it from a different vantage point, it is not really the same tree they are looking at – everyone’s impression of the same tree is different.</p>

<p><em>I kept staring at my palm in the engulfing darkness of the cold Dutch night.</em></p>

<p>Atop the four-storey building on Lake Temple Road, was a sanctuary of lush platlife – all meticulously tended to by Dadua. For the longest time, Lake Temple felt akin to the story of Charlie’s chocolate factory, only healthier – abounding with banana, papaya, cauliflower, coriander, mango, pumpkin, chillies, shojne, and the lemons. On numerous occasions, Dadua would take my brother and me to the roof to pick out lemons straight from the tree. As we plucked the fruit from the plant, the natural aroma of the gondhoraj lemons permeated the air while we helped him bag the lemons for us to take home.</p>

<p>At one point of time, there was even a water reservoir to cultivate fish on the same rooftop.
Picture this: smack in the heart of the urban grey slate of Calcutta, a green nugget of nature nestled in the unlikely location of a rooftop, tended to by one man - where plant and waterlife thrived alike. I would call that Eden on Earth, wouldn’t you?</p>

<p style="font-size: 18px; text-align: center;">
আমার মুক্তি আলোয় আলোয় এই আকাশে <br />
আমার মুক্তি ধুলায় ধুলায় ঘাসে ঘাসে
</p>

<p>Dadua was a man at one with nature, and nature reciprocated that connection. He used to often tell us that plants have feelings and plants understand when they are cared for. During his younger days, he ventured far and wide in search of plants that were uncommon and unthinkable to grow on small pots. The mango plant for instance, that grew on a pot and bore fruit all throughout the year, was an accomplishment that filled him particularly with pride.</p>

<p><em>I kept staring at my palm in the engulfing darkness of the cold Dutch night.</em></p>

<p>As I grew from a toddler to “a young man”, as he would phrase it, Dadua shared stories, folktales, Sanskrit slokas and poems with me and my brother. He tried his best to instil in us the wisdom from passages from many pieces of literature. Long before I could grasp the concept of religion, I had already committed to memory some of the verses from Ma Durga’s prayers. Even these days during Ashtami anjali, the verse “Sarbamangala Mangalyay” triggers the memory of Dadua sitting on is armchair, with his red book of Hindu Slokas in his hand reading passages out to us in the backdrop of the soft rustling of leaves from the trees he planted in the driveway of Lake Temple road.</p>

<p>Dadua was known to be a master-reciter, with the innate ability to recall thousand-line poems like he was reading an invisible paper in front of him. Once on Rabindrajayanti at the Lake, he brought me to one of his performances. Although I did not understand the poem, I did understand that everyone’s attention was pinned on his recitation. He taught me many poems from the “Sishu” collection of Tagore’s poems made specifically for children.</p>

<p style="font-size: 18px; text-align: center;">
মনে করো যেন বিদেশ ঘুরে <br />
মাকে নিয়ে যাচ্ছি অনেক দূরে <br />
তুমি যাচ্ছ পালকিতে মা চড়ে <br />
আমি যাচ্ছি রাঙা ঘোড়ার ‘পরে <br />
</p>

<p><em>I kept staring at my palm in the engulfing darkness of the cold Dutch night.</em></p>

<p>Dadua was a captivating storyteller. As I grew older, the stories he told me also took a more mature form. What were stories from the Ramayan and Mahabharat, became anecdotes from his own life and choices that defined who he was. He recounted the river next to his childhood home in Comilla where fishermen sold fish right after catching it, his boyhood days spent in his school Ishwar Pathshala, his meeting Rabindranath Tagore, about his aspirations for going to art school, fond recollections of his mother, whom he lost at an early age, of the stern yet spirited chancellor of BE college of yesteryear and of Vergese Kurian, founder of Amul, who was his classmate at National Dairy Research Institute in Bangalore.</p>

<p>His home in SN Banerjee Road was close to Anadi Cabin. On the day of his graduation from BE College, he recalled how much he enjoyed a plate of Mughlai Parathas – he fondly recalled that the owner of the restaurant (I think Anadi himself) decided not to charge him when he found out it was his graduation day.</p>

<p>I felt a profound connection to his stories, bupt none more than those centred around Kurseong and Keventer’s. Even till this day, a trip to Darjeeling is incomplete without visiting Keventer’s restaurant. His stories always took me to faraway hill stations that he visited – sometimes to supervise tea estates – sometimes to overlook another part of his business. On one occasion, he told us how he found his way to a cabin when his car had broken down in a hilly deserted forest, and in his hour of despair, he met a classmate from BE college.</p>

<p><em>I kept staring at my palm in the engulfing darkness of the cold Dutch night.</em></p>

<p>Mimi’s passing marked the end of what I recall as childhood. The house became quieter and both Dadua and Dia suddenly seemed to age overnight. Thus began a different era in Lake temple. Over the ensuing years, Dadua got ill a few times. After coming back from the hospital one time, he was quite frail and could barely make it to the dining table. Words that will forever keep ringing in my ears were “Dadua kheyecho” (he used to call me “Dadua” as well) – even in the weakest moments, he was still enquiring about my well-being. Lake temple right there, as it was, and as it is today, will always be defined by moments like these – transforming what I used to call “Daduar bari” to much more than a house and into something greater than myself, a cornerstone and source of eternal strength.</p>

<p><em>I kept staring at my palm in the engulfing darkness of the cold Dutch night.</em></p>

<p>The day after I got the news, I was looking for some photos of Dadua – I found many of Dia’s, only a few of Dadua’s. In one of them during bhai-phota, Dadua was there just in the background. I was about to scroll past it when it struck me that that was him in his true essence – ever present and away from the limelight. Even then, there was one photo on a warm summer’s noon, when he was front and centre, smiling as bright as the sun overhead. Being the eldest, I was the first in my generation to get a job. Mimi had long left for the heavenly abode and in the ensuing five years, the deepest sense of pride I ever allowed myself was when using my own money, I bought Dadua a Panjabi and Dia a saree. Oh you should have been there to see his smile. He didn’t have the habit of dressing up or going outside to restaurants but in his words “it’s to celebrate my Dadua’s first job, of course I will dress up”. One of the photos from that day captured his effervescent smile so well that it is being framed to be the photograph to remember him by. To mean as much to someone is not something I know how to put into words.</p>

<p><em>I kept staring at my palm in the engulfing darkness of the cold Dutch night.</em></p>

<p>Mohana met Dadua only after we got married. But she knew of him from our college days – till date, she recalls how awestruck she was hearing of Dadua’s technological prowess. Back in the early 2010s, we were all on the broadband bandwagon and it was liberating to have an omnipresent connection called “wifi”. It might have been considered a young man’s experiment in most households, but not in Lake Temple Road. Not only did Dadua have his own laptop, smartphone and wifi setup, he became quite famous among my friends for insisting to upgrade his poor BSNL network to a faster Airtel one! He honed new ideas for handicraft from the internet and I often got to see him trying new tools like a hot glue gun and coloured glue sticks, which he used to make desk items like pen holders.</p>

<p><em>I kept staring at my palm in the engulfing darkness of the cold Dutch night.</em></p>

<p>If you pass by Shib Mandir, you may be forgiven for not noticing the otherwise unremarkable building that stands at Lake Temple Road. To me though, it is a foundational pillar to who I was as a child and who I became as an adult, and Dadua is an integral part of that and I will forever miss him. I met Dadua for the last time on March 24, 2023. I am still grappling with the harsh reality that I will never see him again. What stays with me are his stories, his lifestyle, his teachings, and his appreciation for the arts. I recall him reciting the following passage often with glistening eyes. Today it holds a very special place as I cling to his memory.</p>

<p style="font-size: 18px; text-align: center;">
ফিরায়ে দিনু দ্বারের চাবি,  রাখি না আর ঘরের দাবি— <br />
সবার আজি প্রসাদবাণী চাই॥ <br />
অনেক দিন ছিলাম প্রতিবেশী, <br />
দিয়েছি যত নিয়েছি তার বেশি। <br />
</p>

<p><em>I kept staring at my palm in the engulfing darkness of the cold Dutch night.</em></p>]]></content><author><name>{&quot;twitter&quot; =&gt; &quot;mourjo_sen&quot;}</name></author><category term="non-tech" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The similarity was uncanny. Over the years, I remember comparing my palm side-by-side to his - it is an almost identical copy of Dadua’s. In fact, I would say it with pride – a cherished emblem that I carried with a sense of honour. When I heard the heartbreaking news at three in the morning, my immediate response was to look at my own palm in the dim light of the smartphone, not knowing what this meant or how to feel about it.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Exposing the page-view analytics of this site</title><link href="https://mourjo.me/blog/tech/2021/11/15/site-analytics/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Exposing the page-view analytics of this site" /><published>2021-11-15T11:07:12+05:30</published><updated>2021-11-15T11:07:12+05:30</updated><id>https://mourjo.me/blog/tech/2021/11/15/site-analytics</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mourjo.me/blog/tech/2021/11/15/site-analytics/"><![CDATA[<p>In this post, I expose the analytics of this site, mostly to convince myself that someone reads this (even if it’s my own private browser sessions)!</p>
<iframe width="100%" height="700" src="https://datastudio.google.com/embed/reporting/7f7b943a-c3a6-401e-9613-8f78b452befc/page/1jWfC" frameborder="0" style="border:0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>]]></content><author><name>{&quot;twitter&quot; =&gt; &quot;mourjo_sen&quot;}</name></author><category term="tech" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In this post, I expose the analytics of this site, mostly to convince myself that someone reads this (even if it’s my own private browser sessions)!]]></summary></entry></feed>