<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://mourjo.me/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://mourjo.me/blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-10-25T10:19:07+05:30</updated><id>https://mourjo.me/blog/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Mourjo Sen’s Blog</title><subtitle>Thoughts of a software engineer about life, tech and everything in between. A place to put down my thoughts for my own recollection more than anything else. If you like it, be sure to drop me an email!</subtitle><author><name>{&quot;twitter&quot;=&gt;&quot;mourjo_sen&quot;}</name></author><entry><title type="html">On building habits</title><link href="https://mourjo.me/blog/2021/10/25/on-building-habits/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On building habits" /><published>2021-10-25T10:07:12+05:30</published><updated>2021-10-25T10:07:12+05:30</updated><id>https://mourjo.me/blog/2021/10/25/on-building-habits</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mourjo.me/blog/2021/10/25/on-building-habits/">&lt;p&gt;During the last five years of my working life, I have come to realise that there are few things that pay off in the long run such as the ability to form habits easily. In retrospect, starting to do something like working out every other day, reading at a particular time of day, preparing for teaching a lesson – all have benefited from repetitive incremental progress through habits. Here are three things that have helped me build habits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Anchoring&lt;/strong&gt;: While building habits, it is easier to associate the new activity to an existing habit that you’re used to. For example, if going out for a run is already part of your day, then adding a post-run task like having your pills is easier than remembering to have it at 7 am. Once a habit becomes part of the day, it can then become an anchor for another new habit.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Planning&lt;/strong&gt;: Part of building a habit is repetition, and for something to be repeatable, it should not change much. That is, chalk out a plan beforehand, maybe the previous day (tweak it if required) but stick to it through thick and thin – i.e., take the thinking or optionality out of the activity. For example, if I am planning to run 5 km in the morning, the option of cutting the run short should not even be present. A more detailed plan, for example, a 1 km pre-run warm up and a post run cool down, takes the thinking out of the picture and knowing it is obligatory even in those days that are tiring, makes build the habit.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reviewing&lt;/strong&gt;: One of the best things a smart watch has helped me with, in so far as workouts are considered, is a review of the last day/week’s activities. If I had been able to do all of my workouts in the week, looking back and reviewing it is a great sense of accomplishment, while not being able to do so is a reason to push harder in the next day/week. In terms of general habit-building, such reviewing of past activities has helped me make a conscious effort for those missed triggers, because as humans those are bound to happen.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>{&quot;twitter&quot;=&gt;&quot;mourjo_sen&quot;}</name></author><summary type="html">During the last five years of my working life, I have come to realise that there are few things that pay off in the long run such as the ability to form habits easily. In retrospect, starting to do something like working out every other day, reading at a particular time of day, preparing for teaching a lesson – all have benefited from repetitive incremental progress through habits. Here are three things that have helped me build habits.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Learning by teaching</title><link href="https://mourjo.me/blog/mentoring/2021/09/23/learning-by-teaching/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Learning by teaching" /><published>2021-09-23T10:07:11+05:30</published><updated>2021-09-23T10:07:11+05:30</updated><id>https://mourjo.me/blog/mentoring/2021/09/23/learning-by-teaching</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mourjo.me/blog/mentoring/2021/09/23/learning-by-teaching/">&lt;p&gt;In an &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/mentoring/2021/06/15/a-personal-challenge/&quot;&gt;earlier post&lt;/a&gt;, I wrote that I was embarking on a journey of teaching the fundamentals of Computer Science to Otee. The journey thus far has been incredible, and it is inspiring to think that in the span of three months, all of the following have happened.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Functional programming&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Advanced data structures (including Bloom filters!)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Two major projects: A &lt;a href=&quot;https://otee.dev/2021/08/24/crisp-a-simple-lisp-interpreter.html&quot;&gt;Lisp interpreter&lt;/a&gt; and a &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/cardimomT&quot;&gt;blog post tweet bot&lt;/a&gt; that I hope will publish this post&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Computer architecture, all the way from the hardware to the instruction execution cycle&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the perks of being able to have the opportunity to teach the fundamentals is that I get to relearn these concepts from a very different perspective, all over again. I have had to research on my own before I feel confident enough to teach and what that has opened up for me, is to see those concepts deep down through the experience of being in the industry for five years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Teaching something convincingly requires research and it is liberating to be able to learn all those things again, and I would highly recommend this to anyone who enjoys this subject. Imagine thinking from first principles and even questioning those first principles. When I was first exposed to the fundamentals, I didn’t know any better than to take things at their face value and that obviously left holes in my knowledge, not to mention all the things I didn’t even remember I had once learned. During the depths of the pandemic, learning by teaching has been one of the most rewarding exercises.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are curious about &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/oteecodes&quot;&gt;Otee’s&lt;/a&gt; journey, you can follow &lt;a href=&quot;https://otee.dev&quot;&gt;him here&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>{&quot;twitter&quot;=&gt;&quot;mourjo_sen&quot;}</name></author><category term="mentoring" /><summary type="html">In an earlier post, I wrote that I was embarking on a journey of teaching the fundamentals of Computer Science to Otee. The journey thus far has been incredible, and it is inspiring to think that in the span of three months, all of the following have happened.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A personal challenge</title><link href="https://mourjo.me/blog/mentoring/2021/06/15/a-personal-challenge/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A personal challenge" /><published>2021-06-15T11:07:11+05:30</published><updated>2021-06-15T11:07:11+05:30</updated><id>https://mourjo.me/blog/mentoring/2021/06/15/a-personal-challenge</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mourjo.me/blog/mentoring/2021/06/15/a-personal-challenge/">&lt;p&gt;Oitee is convinced that he can learn Computer Science basics as a part-time activity. I
decided to help him with this endeavour. Being from a non-technical background, his
knowledge of Computer Science is limited to high school HelloWorlds. It is both a huge
responsibility and honour for me to be part of his journey. My paramount goal is to ensure
the gets a &lt;em&gt;good enough&lt;/em&gt; guidance to venture into this field. The weight of being able to
show the right path is heavy, but it is worth trying.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s what I have in mind (it is probably going to change). I have created the following
broad headings of what I think are the most useful areas to spend time on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;CS fundamentals
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Computer Architecture&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Networking&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Operating Systems&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Databases&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Basics of a compiler&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Programming
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Javascript basics from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.freecodecamp.org/learn/javascript-algorithms-and-data-structures/#claim-cert-block&quot;&gt;FreeCodeCamp&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Data structures&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Algorithms&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Problem solving (something like &lt;a href=&quot;http://leetcode.com&quot;&gt;Leetcode&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Functional languages / OOP&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Tooling workflows
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Linux CLI&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Git&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Visual Studio Code&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Web Development (after 1)
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Server / Client&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Web scale, components, technologies&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I pondered a lot on which language and IDE to suggest for him to learn. Eventually I concluded
that Javascript and VS Code seem to be the most ubiquitous combination there is for web
development. &lt;a href=&quot;https://lambdaschool.com/courses/full-stack-web-development&quot;&gt;Lambda School&lt;/a&gt;
also seems to be favouring Javascript.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The list above is biased on what I think I am good enough to guide with. Much to the same
reason, there is no mention of machine learning or frontend technologies like CSS,
although a bit of that might be necessary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of six months from now, based on the progress, my objective is for him to be
ready for applying to coding bootcamps like &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.recurse.com&quot;&gt;Recurse Centre&lt;/a&gt;. If
not that, then with some more work, a candidate for applying to junior engineering
positions, like I did back in 2015 – only better than what I was back then.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In an effort to prove to myself that I could take on this long and ardous (and eventually
rewarding) journey, I hope to publish regular posts here about the progress I am making as
a guide, so stay tuned and if you’re reading this, wish me luck!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>{&quot;twitter&quot;=&gt;&quot;mourjo_sen&quot;}</name></author><category term="mentoring" /><summary type="html">Oitee is convinced that he can learn Computer Science basics as a part-time activity. I decided to help him with this endeavour. Being from a non-technical background, his knowledge of Computer Science is limited to high school HelloWorlds. It is both a huge responsibility and honour for me to be part of his journey. My paramount goal is to ensure the gets a good enough guidance to venture into this field. The weight of being able to show the right path is heavy, but it is worth trying.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Medium Index</title><link href="https://mourjo.me/blog/hidden/2020/09/03/medium-index/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Medium Index" /><published>2020-09-03T07:14:11+05:30</published><updated>2020-09-03T07:14:11+05:30</updated><id>https://mourjo.me/blog/hidden/2020/09/03/medium-index</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mourjo.me/blog/hidden/2020/09/03/medium-index/">&lt;!-- BLOG-POST-LIST:START --&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/helpshift-engineering/load-shedding-in-clojure-d4857ce11588?source=rss-c69a7b7ed0c5------2&quot;&gt;Load Shedding in Clojure&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;copy&quot;&gt; — 21 Sep 2020&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/helpshift-engineering/load-shedding-in-web-services-9fa8cfa1ffe4?source=rss-c69a7b7ed0c5------2&quot;&gt;Load Shedding in Web Services&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;copy&quot;&gt; — 04 Sep 2020&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/helpshift-engineering/the-convoluted-magic-of-leiningen-test-selectors-2eb6c452dfcf?source=rss-c69a7b7ed0c5------2&quot;&gt;The Convoluted Magic of Leiningen Test Selectors&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;copy&quot;&gt; — 02 May 2020&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/helpshift-engineering/achieving-graceful-restarts-of-clojure-services-b3a3b9c1d60d?source=rss-c69a7b7ed0c5------2&quot;&gt;Killing me softly: Graceful shutdowns in Clojure&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;copy&quot;&gt; — 27 Jan 2020&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/helpshift-engineering/on-the-testability-of-ring-middlewares-in-clojure-6795eae60f2a?source=rss-c69a7b7ed0c5------2&quot;&gt;On the testability of Ring Middlewares in Clojure&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;copy&quot;&gt; — 06 Dec 2019&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/helpshift-engineering/a-study-in-parallelising-tests-b5253817beae?source=rss-c69a7b7ed0c5------2&quot;&gt;A Study in Parallelising Tests&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;copy&quot;&gt; — 15 May 2019&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/helpshift-engineering/scylladb-the-helpshift-story-3d332bf80ce2?source=rss-c69a7b7ed0c5------2&quot;&gt;ScyllaDB: The Helpshift Story&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;copy&quot;&gt; — 03 Apr 2019&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/helpshift-engineering/a-detailed-comparison-between-autocompletion-strategies-in-elasticsearch-66cb9e9c62c4?source=rss-c69a7b7ed0c5------2&quot;&gt;A detailed comparison between autocompletion strategies in ElasticSearch&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;copy&quot;&gt; — 30 Aug 2018&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;!-- BLOG-POST-LIST:END --&gt;</content><author><name>{&quot;twitter&quot;=&gt;&quot;mourjo_sen&quot;}</name></author><category term="hidden" /><category term="hidden" /><summary type="html">Load Shedding in Clojure — 21 Sep 2020 Load Shedding in Web Services — 04 Sep 2020 The Convoluted Magic of Leiningen Test Selectors — 02 May 2020 Killing me softly: Graceful shutdowns in Clojure — 27 Jan 2020 On the testability of Ring Middlewares in Clojure — 06 Dec 2019 A Study in Parallelising Tests — 15 May 2019 ScyllaDB: The Helpshift Story — 03 Apr 2019 A detailed comparison between autocompletion strategies in ElasticSearch — 30 Aug 2018</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Positive feedback loop, Darwin and the IITs</title><link href="https://mourjo.me/blog/tech/2020/06/13/positive-feedback-loop-darwin-and-the-iits/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Positive feedback loop, Darwin and the IITs" /><published>2020-06-13T07:14:11+05:30</published><updated>2020-06-13T07:14:11+05:30</updated><id>https://mourjo.me/blog/tech/2020/06/13/positive-feedback-loop-darwin-and-the-iits</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mourjo.me/blog/tech/2020/06/13/positive-feedback-loop-darwin-and-the-iits/">&lt;p&gt;Being an engineer by profession, I have often battled with the fear of not hailing from an IIT. I cannot lie that no matter how many IITians I meet, I will never stop being self-conscious and intimidated by them. The lingering thought here is that I will never be able to be as successful or technically proficient as someone who studied at a prestigious and &lt;strong&gt;highly regarded&lt;/strong&gt; institute like an IIT. Upon introspection, I have come to the conclusion that Darwin and the theory of natural selection might just be able to explain what I am feeling and ultimately why IITians &lt;strong&gt;are&lt;/strong&gt; a distinguished subset of engineers in India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The success of the IITs is not because of its teachers or research prowess, which is evident in the fact that the IITs never rank high in global University rankings. Any institute held in high regard by large enough number of people, will end up attracting the smartest minds. The invariant here is that &lt;strong&gt;most students&lt;/strong&gt; in a country of India’s size want to study in the IITs. Because of the sheer competition for the very limited number of seats at the IITs, by virtue of the merit-based selection examinations (akin to natural selection in Darwin’s theory of evolution), only the smartest people end up in the IITs. If suddenly, by some divine intervention, all of Indian students stopped thinking of the IITs as the holy grail of undergraduate studies, then I would be very surprised if the best engineers in the country are still IITians. It is not the teachings at IIT that make great engineers, it is a direct correlation to the smartest people ending up in the IITs in the first place. Once a conglomerate of really smart people are formed at the IITs, there is no stopping, they practically shoot themselves into success. By passing the barrier to entry, the very few that get through, they have already proven to the world that they are better than the rest, what happens inside the gates of the IITs is immaterial.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This influences the companies that are looking to recruit engineers as well. Since the institute is perceived highly by the common people, because of competition for the few seats and the merit-based selection exams, only the best people end up there, so the probability of recruiting smart people is much higher at the IITs, so more and more companies look to recruit at the IITs, causing more interest in the IITs among aspiring engineers. The feedback loop reinforces the superiority of the IITs. It doesn’t even have to be an IIT, anything that is perceived as “good” by enough people will eventually attract enough “good people” to actually make the thing “good”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In hindsight, there is perhaps no reason to be intimidated by people from the IITs or to think that one is not technically as proficient as someone from an IIT because not being from an IIT doesn’t necessarily demerit one. But it would be naive and remiss to think that those who have out-raced millions to get into the IITs are not among the distinguished subset of engineers in India.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>{&quot;twitter&quot;=&gt;&quot;mourjo_sen&quot;}</name></author><category term="tech" /><summary type="html">Being an engineer by profession, I have often battled with the fear of not hailing from an IIT. I cannot lie that no matter how many IITians I meet, I will never stop being self-conscious and intimidated by them. The lingering thought here is that I will never be able to be as successful or technically proficient as someone who studied at a prestigious and highly regarded institute like an IIT. Upon introspection, I have come to the conclusion that Darwin and the theory of natural selection might just be able to explain what I am feeling and ultimately why IITians are a distinguished subset of engineers in India.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Pale blue dot: A Covid-19 perspective</title><link href="https://mourjo.me/blog/non-tech/2020/05/12/pale-blue-dot/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Pale blue dot: A Covid-19 perspective" /><published>2020-05-12T17:14:11+05:30</published><updated>2020-05-12T17:14:11+05:30</updated><id>https://mourjo.me/blog/non-tech/2020/05/12/pale-blue-dot</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mourjo.me/blog/non-tech/2020/05/12/pale-blue-dot/">&lt;p&gt;In his famous book “The pale blue dot”, Carl Sagan &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.planetary.org/explore/space-topics/earth/pale-blue-dot.html&quot;&gt;wrote&lt;/a&gt; about our unremarkable position in the Universe as human beings. This photo shows the pale blue dot; the image taken by the space probe Voyager 1 on February 14, 1990. As the spacecraft left our planetary neighborhood for the fringes of the solar system, NASA turned it around for one last look at our home planet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/images/Pale_Blue_Dot.png&quot; alt=&quot;Pale Blue Dot&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the world plunges into the unthinkable crisis of Covid-19, it is hard to find hope and courage to dream of a better day. Everything we know and love, our way of life, has reached a point of existential crisis. While many of our livelihoods are affected, many others are paying the dearest price of having to lose their loved ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Look again at that dot. That’s here. That’s home. That’s us. On it everyone you love, everyone you know, everyone you ever heard of, every human being who ever was, lived out their lives. The aggregate of our joy and suffering, thousands of confident religions, ideologies, and economic doctrines, every hunter and forager, every hero and coward, every creator and destroyer of civilization, every king and peasant, every young couple in love, every mother and father, hopeful child, inventor and explorer, every teacher of morals, every corrupt politician, every “superstar,” every “supreme leader,” every saint and sinner in the history of our species lived there–on a mote of dust suspended in a sunbeam.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If our species reaches an end to life as we know it, what stories will we tell our children? If our lives are chained by a Virus that we cannot even see, would we be able to look back and say that our hay day on Earth was well spent?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Think of the rivers of blood spilled by all those generals and emperors so that, in glory and triumph, they could become the momentary masters of a fraction of a dot. Think of the endless cruelties visited by the inhabitants of one corner of this pixel on the scarcely distinguishable inhabitants of some other corner, how frequent their misunderstandings, how eager they are to kill one another, how fervent their hatreds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We, who can fly to the moon, take photos of black holes, detect gravitational waves, have been stripped of our imaginary pedestal to be at the mercy of the littlest of the little things on Earth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Our posturings, our imagined self-importance, the delusion that we have some privileged position in the Universe, are challenged by this point of pale light. Our planet is a lonely speck in the great enveloping cosmic dark. In our obscurity, in all this vastness, there is no hint that help will come from elsewhere to save us from ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Covid-19 is Nature’s revenge on our arrogance and narrow-mindedness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There is perhaps no better demonstration of the folly of human conceits than this distant image of our tiny world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But hope springs eternal. In our battle against the Covid-19 virus, we must become cognizant of and believe in our collective good to spend the remainder of our alloted time here on Earth, not as masters of the planet, but as children of nature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;To me, it underscores our responsibility to deal more kindly with one another, and to preserve and cherish the pale blue dot, the only home we’ve ever known.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><author><name>{&quot;twitter&quot;=&gt;&quot;mourjo_sen&quot;}</name></author><category term="non-tech" /><summary type="html">In his famous book “The pale blue dot”, Carl Sagan wrote about our unremarkable position in the Universe as human beings. This photo shows the pale blue dot; the image taken by the space probe Voyager 1 on February 14, 1990. As the spacecraft left our planetary neighborhood for the fringes of the solar system, NASA turned it around for one last look at our home planet.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">[recurrent] Stuff I am reading</title><link href="https://mourjo.me/blog/tech/2019/09/20/reading-list/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="[recurrent] Stuff I am reading" /><published>2019-09-20T23:14:11+05:30</published><updated>2019-09-20T23:14:11+05:30</updated><id>https://mourjo.me/blog/tech/2019/09/20/reading-list</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mourjo.me/blog/tech/2019/09/20/reading-list/">&lt;p&gt;This is a list of readings I have found to be extremely useful and
hence I am bookmarking them here, for my future self mostly. This is
an ever-increasing unordered list, which I am constantly trying to keep up with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last update: April 15, 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;conceptual&quot;&gt;Conceptual&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Critical Rendering Path &lt;a href=&quot;https://developers.google.com/web/fundamentals/performance/critical-rendering-path/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://developers.google.com/web/fundamentals/performance/critical-rendering-path/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Algebraic Effects for the Rest of Us &lt;a href=&quot;https://overreacted.io/algebraic-effects-for-the-rest-of-us/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://overreacted.io/algebraic-effects-for-the-rest-of-us/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cryptographic Attacks: A Guide for the Perplexed &lt;a href=&quot;https://research.checkpoint.com/cryptographic-attacks-a-guide-for-the-perplexed/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://research.checkpoint.com/cryptographic-attacks-a-guide-for-the-perplexed/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Introduction to Transaction Isolation Levels &lt;a href=&quot;http://dbmsmusings.blogspot.com/2019/05/introduction-to-transaction-isolation.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;http://dbmsmusings.blogspot.com/2019/05/introduction-to-transaction-isolation.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Stop using JWT for sessions &lt;a href=&quot;http://cryto.net/~joepie91/blog/2016/06/13/stop-using-jwt-for-sessions/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;http://cryto.net/~joepie91/blog/2016/06/13/stop-using-jwt-for-sessions/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What every computer science major should know &lt;a href=&quot;http://matt.might.net/articles/what-cs-majors-should-know/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;http://matt.might.net/articles/what-cs-majors-should-know/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Introduction to HTTP/2 &lt;a href=&quot;https://developers.google.com/web/fundamentals/performance/http2&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://developers.google.com/web/fundamentals/performance/http2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Latacora - A Child’s Garden of Inter-Service Authentication Schemes &lt;a href=&quot;https://latacora.micro.blog/a-childs-garden/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://latacora.micro.blog/a-childs-garden/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Javascript Object Signing and Encryption is a Bad Standard That Everyone Should Avoid &lt;a href=&quot;https://paragonie.com/blog/2017/03/jwt-json-web-tokens-is-bad-standard-that-everyone-should-avoid&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://paragonie.com/blog/2017/03/jwt-json-web-tokens-is-bad-standard-that-everyone-should-avoid&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Password expiration is dead, long live passwords &lt;a href=&quot;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=20077967&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=20077967&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;CPU Clocks and Clock Interrupts, and Their Effects on Schedulers &lt;a href=&quot;https://accu.org/index.php/journals/2185&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://accu.org/index.php/journals/2185&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;WebSockets - A Conceptual Deep-Dive &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ably.io/concepts/websockets&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://www.ably.io/concepts/websockets&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sticky Sessions are Evil – Chaos in Computing &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.chaosincomputing.com/2012/05/sticky-sessions-are-evil/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;http://www.chaosincomputing.com/2012/05/sticky-sessions-are-evil/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Why You Don’t Roll Your Own Crypto &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.vice.com/en_us/article/wnx8nq/why-you-dont-roll-your-own-crypto&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://www.vice.com/en_us/article/wnx8nq/why-you-dont-roll-your-own-crypto&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Hard Parts of JWT Security Nobody Talks About &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pingidentity.com/en/company/blog/posts/2019/jwt-security-nobody-talks-about.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://www.pingidentity.com/en/company/blog/posts/2019/jwt-security-nobody-talks-about.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Distributed consensus revised – Part I &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.acolyer.org/2019/05/07/distributed-consensus-revised-part-i/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://blog.acolyer.org/2019/05/07/distributed-consensus-revised-part-i/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Advanced Data Structures - MIT OpenCourseWare &lt;a href=&quot;https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/electrical-engineering-and-computer-science/6-851-advanced-data-structures-spring-2012/lecture-videos/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/electrical-engineering-and-computer-science/6-851-advanced-data-structures-spring-2012/lecture-videos/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A Generalised Solution to Distributed Consensus &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/1902.06776&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://arxiv.org/abs/1902.06776&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Making reliable distributed systems in the presence of software errors &lt;a href=&quot;http://erlang.org/download/armstrong_thesis_2003.pdf&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;http://erlang.org/download/armstrong_thesis_2003.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Linux Kernel Teaching — The Linux Kernel  documentation &lt;a href=&quot;https://linux-kernel-labs.github.io/refs/heads/master/index.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://linux-kernel-labs.github.io/refs/heads/master/index.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Quantum computing for the very curious &lt;a href=&quot;https://quantum.country/qcvc&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://quantum.country/qcvc&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Overview of Consistency Levels in Database Systems &lt;a href=&quot;http://dbmsmusings.blogspot.com/2019/07/overview-of-consistency-levels-in.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;http://dbmsmusings.blogspot.com/2019/07/overview-of-consistency-levels-in.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Wrong Abstraction — Sandi Metz &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sandimetz.com/blog/2016/1/20/the-wrong-abstraction&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://www.sandimetz.com/blog/2016/1/20/the-wrong-abstraction&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Christopher Batey - DYNAMO: the paper that changed the database world &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/hMt9yFp0JKM&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://youtu.be/hMt9yFp0JKM&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;CQRS &lt;a href=&quot;https://martinfowler.com/bliki/CQRS.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://martinfowler.com/bliki/CQRS.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;infrastructure&quot;&gt;Infrastructure&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Vulcanizer: a library for operating Elasticsearch &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.blog/2019-03-05-vulcanizer-a-library-for-operating-elasticsearch/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://github.blog/2019-03-05-vulcanizer-a-library-for-operating-elasticsearch/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Modern applications at AWS &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.allthingsdistributed.com/2019/08/modern-applications-at-aws.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://www.allthingsdistributed.com/2019/08/modern-applications-at-aws.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What comes after Serverless? &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@doctor_julz/what-comes-after-serverless-840032dd4ba8&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://medium.com/@doctor_julz/what-comes-after-serverless-840032dd4ba8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;IPA: invariant-preserving applications for weakly consistent replicated databases &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.acolyer.org/2019/09/02/ipa/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://blog.acolyer.org/2019/09/02/ipa/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;DDSketch: a fast and fully-mergeable quantile sketch with relative-error guarantees &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.acolyer.org/2019/09/06/ddsketch/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://blog.acolyer.org/2019/09/06/ddsketch/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Isolating workloads with Systemd slices &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scylladb.com/2019/09/25/isolating-workloads-with-systemd-slices/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://www.scylladb.com/2019/09/25/isolating-workloads-with-systemd-slices/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Dark emerges from stealth with unique ‘deployless’ software model &lt;a href=&quot;https://techcrunch.com/2019/07/29/dark-emerges-from-stealth-with-unique-deployless-software-model/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://techcrunch.com/2019/07/29/dark-emerges-from-stealth-with-unique-deployless-software-model/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We had issues with Monzo on 29th July. Here’s what happened, and what we did to fix it. &lt;a href=&quot;https://monzo.com/blog/2019/09/08/why-monzo-wasnt-working-on-july-29th/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://monzo.com/blog/2019/09/08/why-monzo-wasnt-working-on-july-29th/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Using GraphQL to Improve Data Hydration in our Customer Care Platform and Beyond &lt;a href=&quot;https://eng.uber.com/graphql-data-hydration-customer-care/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://eng.uber.com/graphql-data-hydration-customer-care/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;One Misconfig (JIRA) to Leak Them All- Including NASA and Hundreds of Fortune 500 Companies! &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@logicbomb_1/one-misconfig-jira-to-leak-them-all-including-nasa-and-hundreds-of-fortune-500-companies-a70957ef03c7&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://medium.com/@logicbomb_1/one-misconfig-jira-to-leak-them-all-including-nasa-and-hundreds-of-fortune-500-companies-a70957ef03c7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Netflix: What Happens When You Press Play? - High Scalability -  &lt;a href=&quot;http://highscalability.com/blog/2017/12/11/netflix-what-happens-when-you-press-play.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;http://highscalability.com/blog/2017/12/11/netflix-what-happens-when-you-press-play.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Streaming Cassandra at WePay - Part 1 &lt;a href=&quot;https://wecode.wepay.com/posts/streaming-cassandra-at-wepay-part-1&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://wecode.wepay.com/posts/streaming-cassandra-at-wepay-part-1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Streaming Cassandra at WePay - Part 2 &lt;a href=&quot;https://wecode.wepay.com/posts/streaming-cassandra-at-wepay-part-2&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://wecode.wepay.com/posts/streaming-cassandra-at-wepay-part-2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The boring technology behind a one-person Internet company &lt;a href=&quot;https://broadcast.listennotes.com/the-boring-technology-behind-listen-notes-56697c2e347b&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://broadcast.listennotes.com/the-boring-technology-behind-listen-notes-56697c2e347b&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Zen and the Art of Scaling - A Koan and Epigram Approach - High Scalability -  &lt;a href=&quot;http://highscalability.com/blog/2012/2/27/zen-and-the-art-of-scaling-a-koan-and-epigram-approach.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;http://highscalability.com/blog/2012/2/27/zen-and-the-art-of-scaling-a-koan-and-epigram-approach.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Software/site reliability of distributed systems &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=grEgDJVNIS0&amp;amp;list=PL279M8GbNsesB7sxLO5zNbBHkOVvb7uvy&amp;amp;index=5&amp;amp;t=0s&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=grEgDJVNIS0&amp;amp;list=PL279M8GbNsesB7sxLO5zNbBHkOVvb7uvy&amp;amp;index=5&amp;amp;t=0s&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cloud Native DevOps With Kubernetes &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nginx.com/resources/library/cloud-native-devops-with-kubernetes/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://www.nginx.com/resources/library/cloud-native-devops-with-kubernetes/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Everything You Need To Know About Networking On AWS &lt;a href=&quot;https://grahamlyons.com/article/everything-you-need-to-know-about-networking-on-aws&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://grahamlyons.com/article/everything-you-need-to-know-about-networking-on-aws&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;PostgreSQL vs. fsync &lt;a href=&quot;https://fosdem.org/2019/schedule/event/postgresql_fsync/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://fosdem.org/2019/schedule/event/postgresql_fsync/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Supercell – Scaling Mobile Games (GAM301) &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=wqz7AunrzcU&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=wqz7AunrzcU&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How to Scale WebSockets &lt;a href=&quot;https://hackernoon.com/scaling-websockets-9a31497af051&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://hackernoon.com/scaling-websockets-9a31497af051&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How to scale a distributed system &lt;a href=&quot;https://cdn.oreillystatic.com/en/assets/1/event/244/How%20to%20scale%20a%20distributed%20system%20Presentation.pdf&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://bit.ly/2msquzp&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A Brief History of High Availability - Cockroach Labs &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cockroachlabs.com/blog/brief-history-high-availability/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://www.cockroachlabs.com/blog/brief-history-high-availability/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Elastic Scaling in the Streams API in Kafka - Confluent &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.confluent.io/blog/elastic-scaling-in-kafka-streams/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://www.confluent.io/blog/elastic-scaling-in-kafka-streams/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Open Distro for Elasticsearch &lt;a href=&quot;https://opendistro.github.io/for-elasticsearch/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://opendistro.github.io/for-elasticsearch/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;New – Open Distro for Elasticsearch – AWS &lt;a href=&quot;https://aws.amazon.com/blogs/aws/new-open-distro-for-elasticsearch/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://aws.amazon.com/blogs/aws/new-open-distro-for-elasticsearch/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Smart sticky sessions using HAProxy for Apache Phoenix &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/helpshift-engineering/smart-sticky-sessions-using-haproxy-for-apache-phoenix-911bdca7e2c&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://medium.com/helpshift-engineering/smart-sticky-sessions-using-haproxy-for-apache-phoenix-911bdca7e2c&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How to get HTTPS working on your local development environment in 5 minutes &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.freecodecamp.org/news/how-to-get-https-working-on-your-local-development-environment-in-5-minutes-7af615770eec/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://www.freecodecamp.org/news/how-to-get-https-working-on-your-local-development-environment-in-5-minutes-7af615770eec/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Elle: Inferring Isolation Anomalies from Experimental Observations &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2003.10554&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://arxiv.org/abs/2003.10554&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Quest for the master algorithm &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=qIZ5PXLVZfo&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=qIZ5PXLVZfo&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What we learnt building BHIM in just 3 weeks - Vimal Kumar &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=uaQ_jNgw6F0&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=uaQ_jNgw6F0&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;JVM Anatomy Quarks &lt;a href=&quot;https://shipilev.net/jvm/anatomy-quarks/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://shipilev.net/jvm/anatomy-quarks/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;(A few) Ops Lessons We All Learn The Hard Way &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.netmeister.org/blog/ops-lessons.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://www.netmeister.org/blog/ops-lessons.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Managing the development of large systems &lt;a href=&quot;http://www-scf.usc.edu/~csci201/lectures/Lecture11/royce1970.pdf&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;http://www-scf.usc.edu/~csci201/lectures/Lecture11/royce1970.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Load Testing Back to Basics: Avoiding the KeepAliveTimeout Race Condition - Web Performance &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.webperformance.com/load-testing-tools/blog/2011/01/load-testing-back-to-basics-avoiding-the-keepalivetimeout-race-condition/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://www.webperformance.com/load-testing-tools/blog/2011/01/load-testing-back-to-basics-avoiding-the-keepalivetimeout-race-condition/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sharing SQLite databases across containers is surprisingly brilliant &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@rbranson/sharing-sqlite-databases-across-containers-is-surprisingly-brilliant-bacb8d753054&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://medium.com/@rbranson/sharing-sqlite-databases-across-containers-is-surprisingly-brilliant-bacb8d753054&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Nubank’s basic Microservice example &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/nubank/basic-microservice-example&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://github.com/nubank/basic-microservice-example&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Microservices and the First Law of Distributed Objects &lt;a href=&quot;https://martinfowler.com/articles/distributed-objects-microservices.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://martinfowler.com/articles/distributed-objects-microservices.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What do you mean by “Event-Driven”? &lt;a href=&quot;https://martinfowler.com/articles/201701-event-driven.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://martinfowler.com/articles/201701-event-driven.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;architecture&quot;&gt;Architecture&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Why our team cancelled our move to microservices &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@steven.lemon182/why-our-team-cancelled-our-move-to-microservices-8fd87898d952&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://medium.com/@steven.lemon182/why-our-team-cancelled-our-move-to-microservices-8fd87898d952&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Architecture of a Database System &lt;a href=&quot;http://db.cs.berkeley.edu/papers/fntdb07-architecture.pdf&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;http://db.cs.berkeley.edu/papers/fntdb07-architecture.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Event Sourcing You are doing it wrong by David Schmitz &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=GzrZworHpIk&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=GzrZworHpIk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Stateful stream processing with Apache Flink &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.infoworld.com/article/3267966/stateful-stream-processing-with-apache-flink.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://www.infoworld.com/article/3267966/stateful-stream-processing-with-apache-flink.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Improving key expiration in Redis &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.twitter.com/engineering/en_us/topics/infrastructure/2019/improving-key-expiration-in-redis.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://blog.twitter.com/engineering/en_us/topics/infrastructure/2019/improving-key-expiration-in-redis.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Distributed systems for fun and profit &lt;a href=&quot;http://book.mixu.net/distsys/intro.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;http://book.mixu.net/distsys/intro.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Goodbye Microservices: From 100s of problem children to 1 superstar &lt;a href=&quot;https://segment.com/blog/goodbye-microservices/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://segment.com/blog/goodbye-microservices/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Notes on Distributed Systems for Young Bloods – Something Similar &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.somethingsimilar.com/2013/01/14/notes-on-distributed-systems-for-young-bloods/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://www.somethingsimilar.com/2013/01/14/notes-on-distributed-systems-for-young-bloods/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Software Architects Newsletter &lt;a href=&quot;https://assets.infoq.com/newsletter/architect/en/newsletter_sample/21Architects_NL-April2019.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://assets.infoq.com/newsletter/architect/en/newsletter_sample/21Architects_NL-April2019.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How to Design a Good API &amp;amp; Why it Matters  &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.infoq.com/presentations/effective-api-design&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://www.infoq.com/presentations/effective-api-design&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Online Event Processing - ACM Queue &lt;a href=&quot;https://queue.acm.org/detail.cfm?id=3321612&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://queue.acm.org/detail.cfm?id=3321612&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mastering Chaos - A Netflix Guide to Microservices &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=CZ3wIuvmHeM&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=CZ3wIuvmHeM&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Data-Driven Storytelling &lt;a href=&quot;http://learn.stanford.edu/data-driven-storytelling-live-reg-0420.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;http://learn.stanford.edu/data-driven-storytelling-live-reg-0420.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How to Build a Cloud Data Platform Part 1 Architecture &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/uhVpLwjEOKU&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://youtu.be/uhVpLwjEOKU&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Snap: a microkernel approach to host networking &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.acolyer.org/2019/11/11/snap-networking/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://blog.acolyer.org/2019/11/11/snap-networking/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;programming&quot;&gt;Programming&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;On the Perils of Dynamic Scope &lt;a href=&quot;https://stuartsierra.com/2013/03/29/perils-of-dynamic-scope&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://stuartsierra.com/2013/03/29/perils-of-dynamic-scope&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Secure Programming HOWTO &lt;a href=&quot;https://dwheeler.com/secure-programs/Secure-Programs-HOWTO/index.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://dwheeler.com/secure-programs/Secure-Programs-HOWTO/index.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mockers - overcoming testing challenges at Grab &lt;a href=&quot;https://engineering.grab.com/mockers&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://engineering.grab.com/mockers&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Python at Netflix &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/netflix-techblog/python-at-netflix-bba45dae649e&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://medium.com/netflix-techblog/python-at-netflix-bba45dae649e&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Zen of Python &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zen_of_Python&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zen_of_Python&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Is It Time to Rewrite the Operating System in Rust? &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=HgtRAbE1nBM&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=HgtRAbE1nBM&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Clojure Compilation: Parenthetical Prose to Bewildering Bytecode &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.ndk.io/clojure-compilation.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://blog.ndk.io/clojure-compilation.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Organizing Functional Code for Parallel Execution; or, foldl and foldr Considered  Slightly Harmful &lt;a href=&quot;https://vimeo.com/6624203&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://vimeo.com/6624203&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Software disenchantment &lt;a href=&quot;http://tonsky.me/blog/disenchantment/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;http://tonsky.me/blog/disenchantment/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Lockfree Algorithms - 1024cores &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.1024cores.net/home/lock-free-algorithms/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;http://www.1024cores.net/home/lock-free-algorithms/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Why Why Functional Programming Matters Matters &lt;a href=&quot;http://raganwald.com/2014/12/20/why-why-functional-programming-matters-matters.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;http://raganwald.com/2014/12/20/why-why-functional-programming-matters-matters.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Java at Speed &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ot3PESmNXhE&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ot3PESmNXhE&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Java SE Lesson: Concurrency &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.oracle.com/javase/tutorial/essential/concurrency/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://docs.oracle.com/javase/tutorial/essential/concurrency/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What Clojure needs to grow — a boring web framework and boring data science &lt;a href=&quot;https://lispcast.com/clojure-needs-grow-boring-web-framework-boring-data-science/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://lispcast.com/clojure-needs-grow-boring-web-framework-boring-data-science/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Working Effectively with Legacy Code &lt;a href=&quot;http://ptgmedia.pearsoncmg.com/images/9780131177055/samplepages/0131177052.pdf&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;http://ptgmedia.pearsoncmg.com/images/9780131177055/samplepages/0131177052.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Best Refactoring You’ve Never Heard Of &lt;a href=&quot;https://web.archive.org/web/20190719160744/http://www.pathsensitive.com/2019/07/the-best-refactoring-youve-never-heard.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://web.archive.org/web/20190719160744/http://www.pathsensitive.com/2019/07/the-best-refactoring-youve-never-heard.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Lets make a Binary Search Tree &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/reasontraining/lets-make-a-reasonable-binary-search-tree-35628b2c78f7&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://medium.com/reasontraining/lets-make-a-reasonable-binary-search-tree-35628b2c78f7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Clojure Compilation: Parenthetical Prose to Bewildering Bytecode &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.ndk.io/clojure-compilation.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://blog.ndk.io/clojure-compilation.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Refactoring the Worst Code I’ve Ever Written &lt;a href=&quot;https://dev.to/jnschrag/refactoring-the-worst-code-i-ve-ever-written-42c7&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://dev.to/jnschrag/refactoring-the-worst-code-i-ve-ever-written-42c7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Clean Coder Blog &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.cleancoder.com/uncle-bob/2012/08/13/the-clean-architecture.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://blog.cleancoder.com/uncle-bob/2012/08/13/the-clean-architecture.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Complex Made Bearable - Lucas Cavalcanti &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ct5aWqhHARs&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ct5aWqhHARs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Programming Algorithms Book &lt;a href=&quot;http://lisp-univ-etc.blogspot.com/2019/07/programming-algorithms-book.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;http://lisp-univ-etc.blogspot.com/2019/07/programming-algorithms-book.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Building an Effective Test Pipeline in a Service Oriented World &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/airbnb-engineering/building-an-effective-test-pipeline-in-a-service-oriented-world-6968c513c6bd&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://medium.com/airbnb-engineering/building-an-effective-test-pipeline-in-a-service-oriented-world-6968c513c6bd&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Missing Semester of Your CS Education &lt;a href=&quot;https://missing.csail.mit.edu/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://missing.csail.mit.edu/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Practical Test Pyramid &lt;a href=&quot;https://martinfowler.com/articles/practical-test-pyramid.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://martinfowler.com/articles/practical-test-pyramid.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Birth &amp;amp; Death of JavaScript &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.destroyallsoftware.com/talks/the-birth-and-death-of-javascript&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://www.destroyallsoftware.com/talks/the-birth-and-death-of-javascript&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Unit, Functional, Integration? You are doing it wrong &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.7mind.io/constructive-test-taxonomy.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://blog.7mind.io/constructive-test-taxonomy.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The inflection point hypothesis: a principled approach to finding the root cause of a failure &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.acolyer.org/2019/11/08/the-inflection-point-hypothesis/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://blog.acolyer.org/2019/11/08/the-inflection-point-hypothesis/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;William Byrd on “The Most Beautiful Program Ever Written” &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=OyfBQmvr2Hc&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=OyfBQmvr2Hc&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Beating C with 80 lines of Haskell: wc &lt;a href=&quot;https://chrispenner.ca/posts/wc&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://chrispenner.ca/posts/wc&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Practical Common Lisp &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.gigamonkeys.com/book/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;http://www.gigamonkeys.com/book/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;miscellaneous&quot;&gt;Miscellaneous&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;TextRank for Text Summarization &lt;a href=&quot;https://nlpforhackers.io/textrank-text-summarization&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://nlpforhackers.io/textrank-text-summarization&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It was a really bad month for the internet &lt;a href=&quot;https://techcrunch.com/2019/07/05/bad-month-for-the-internet/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://techcrunch.com/2019/07/05/bad-month-for-the-internet/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;7 absolute truths I unlearned as junior developer &lt;a href=&quot;https://monicalent.com/blog/2019/06/03/absolute-truths-unlearned-as-junior-developer/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://monicalent.com/blog/2019/06/03/absolute-truths-unlearned-as-junior-developer/&lt;/a&gt;
p- Designing Data-Intensive Application and its related books &lt;a href=&quot;https://anvaka.github.io/greview/ddia/1/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://anvaka.github.io/greview/ddia/1/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Get your work recognized: write a brag document &lt;a href=&quot;https://jvns.ca/blog/brag-documents/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://jvns.ca/blog/brag-documents/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Human-Centric Machine Learning Infrastructure @Netflix &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=XV5VGddmP24&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=XV5VGddmP24&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Correctness proofs of distributed systems with Isabelle - Strange Loop &lt;a href=&quot;https://thestrangeloop.com/2019/correctness-proofs-of-distributed-systems-with-isabelle.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://thestrangeloop.com/2019/correctness-proofs-of-distributed-systems-with-isabelle.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Feature Toggles (aka Feature Flags) &lt;a href=&quot;https://martinfowler.com/articles/feature-toggles.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://martinfowler.com/articles/feature-toggles.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Finding the Order in Chaos &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.usenix.org/conference/srecon16/program/presentation/lueder&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://www.usenix.org/conference/srecon16/program/presentation/lueder&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A Note About Git Commit Messages &lt;a href=&quot;http://tbaggery.com/2008/04/19/a-note-about-git-commit-messages.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;http://tbaggery.com/2008/04/19/a-note-about-git-commit-messages.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Michelangelo Palette: A Feature Engineering Platform at Uber  &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.infoq.com/presentations/michelangelo-palette-uber&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://www.infoq.com/presentations/michelangelo-palette-uber&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Visualizing Systems with Statemaps &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.slideshare.net/bcantrill/visualizing-systems-with-statemaps&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://www.slideshare.net/bcantrill/visualizing-systems-with-statemaps&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Numbers Every Programmer Should Know By Year &lt;a href=&quot;https://people.eecs.berkeley.edu/~rcs/research/interactive_latency.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://people.eecs.berkeley.edu/~rcs/research/interactive_latency.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Things I Learnt from a Senior Software Engineer &lt;a href=&quot;https://neilkakkar.com/things-I-learnt-from-a-senior-dev.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://neilkakkar.com/things-I-learnt-from-a-senior-dev.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Rise and Fall of Server-Side Sessions &lt;a href=&quot;http://codematters.tech/the-rise-and-fall-of-server-side-sessions-part-1-when-the-cookie-crumbles/&quot;&gt;http://codematters.tech/the-rise-and-fall-of-server-side-sessions-part-1-when-the-cookie-crumbles/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Weird Rules I Set Myself That Got Me a Job &lt;a href=&quot;https://dev.to/healeycodes/the-weird-rules-i-set-myself-that-got-me-a-job-2g9m?fbclid=IwAR2xKqcEAEKJBE08CFRekWorouNWNN19WKb392qf0urhDjimVWUnqdyV0Rs&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://dev.to/healeycodes/the-weird-rules-i-set-myself-that-got-me-a-job-2g9m?fbclid=IwAR2xKqcEAEKJBE08CFRekWorouNWNN19WKb392qf0urhDjimVWUnqdyV0Rs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Technical Writing Google Developers &lt;a href=&quot;https://developers.google.com/tech-writing/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://developers.google.com/tech-writing/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Conway’s law is real &lt;a href=&quot;https://goodroot.ca/post/2018/10/13/practicality-metaphysics-conways-law/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://goodroot.ca/post/2018/10/13/practicality-metaphysics-conways-law/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What it’s like to work for Stripe &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.alexmaccaw.com/stripes-culture&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://blog.alexmaccaw.com/stripes-culture&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Notation as a Tool of Thought  &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.eecg.toronto.edu/~jzhu/csc326/readings/iverson.pdf&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;http://www.eecg.toronto.edu/~jzhu/csc326/readings/iverson.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A Large Scale Study of Programming Languages and Code Quality in Github &lt;a href=&quot;https://web.cs.ucdavis.edu/~filkov/papers/lang_github.pdf&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://web.cs.ucdavis.edu/~filkov/papers/lang_github.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Why Devs (Should) Like Estimates - Stack Overflow Blog &lt;a href=&quot;https://stackoverflow.blog/2019/10/23/why-devs-should-like-estimates/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://stackoverflow.blog/2019/10/23/why-devs-should-like-estimates/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>{&quot;twitter&quot;=&gt;&quot;mourjo_sen&quot;}</name></author><category term="tech" /><summary type="html">This is a list of readings I have found to be extremely useful and hence I am bookmarking them here, for my future self mostly. This is an ever-increasing unordered list, which I am constantly trying to keep up with.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Avoiding the road to perdition: The conundrum of choice</title><link href="https://mourjo.me/blog/non-tech/2019/09/20/avoiding-road-to-perdition/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Avoiding the road to perdition: The conundrum of choice" /><published>2019-09-20T23:14:11+05:30</published><updated>2019-09-20T23:14:11+05:30</updated><id>https://mourjo.me/blog/non-tech/2019/09/20/avoiding-road-to-perdition</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mourjo.me/blog/non-tech/2019/09/20/avoiding-road-to-perdition/">&lt;p&gt;There are few junctures in life which are as significant choosing what you do right after school. Your parents have told you this, your teachers keep telling you this and deep down, you either believe them and slog your way through the two final years of school, or if you are like me, don’t believe a word of what everyone else is saying and hope to wiggle your way into the adult world some way or another. The second approach — my approach — isn’t for the faint-hearted, and it carries with it a bucketful of enormous risks. I wouldn’t advise it to myself if I could travel back in time. But in an odd way, I am thankful for the way things turned out. The thing about taking risks is, if it pans out for you, the reward is the justification, but paradoxically, the promise of the same reward is not enough to risk it all. This is the story of such a journey: a teacher who was so good, he almost ruined my life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was never the smartest student in class, and looking back, I perhaps wasn’t even trying to be one, in spite of my mother’s hopes and dreams. I had to be forced to sit down to study, and even if I was sitting down, I would rather daydream about the “Swat Kats” cartoon show or think about my Pokemon card collection while I was forced to fixate on reading the “Adventures of Huckleberry Finn” or solve compound interest problems. I just didn’t get the point of studying anything. That was until class eight, when we were introduced to the subject of Computer Science.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the beginning, I didn’t really understand anything that was taught in class. Later, I realised, much of my disconnection from classwork was due to unmotivational teaching methods, but one could always argue against it. After all, there were still kids excelling subjects in the class with the same teaching methods. Anyway, the mystery that shrouded subjects like Mathematics and Chemistry, also cast its shadow on this new subject of “Computer Science”. For the longest time, I couldn’t figure out why there were no computers used in the class of “Computer Science”. After months of getting twos and threes out of fifty in class tests, my father, in a desperate attempt to make something positive out of my schoolwork, started teaching me Computer Science, recalling his early days of programming as a Physics student.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the next six months, he showed me how to express logic in a way a computer would understand. It was then that it dawned on me that this seemingly tasteless subject is actually very interesting, because here and here alone, I could create something out of nothing. I found solace in it from the dry nature of the rest of my coursework. Being able to apply lessons to a whole different problem had gotten me very excited. What the confines of the classroom and limits of textbooks could not contain, the promise of embarking on an adventurous quest certainly captured the interest of my non-studious mind. I felt the first sense of vastness of the subject, like a sailor at sea and in the vastness, a sense of exploration, when my father would ask me to write a computer program that I had never even thought a computer could do, like talking to a human being and having a back and forth conversation. Though it was the same conversation every time, to my young sailor mind, which never knew nothing outside of questions at the end of chapters, this was nothing short of Vasco da Gama’s voyage to the East. As I look back now, my most rewarding failure was perhaps that class test I scored two out of fifty, because of which my father took me under his tutelage. The rest, as they say, was supposed to be history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But life went on. From class eight to class twelve, I found my love for computer programming, but I still had to study other subjects. Growing up, especially during those formative teenage years, it is extremely difficult to distinguish between influence and interest, and I got caught in the middle of it. In class eleven, we had Mr Andrews as our English teacher. He was unorthodox in his teaching methods and focused on not just explaining the piece we were supposed to be taught, but also the state of the mind of the author or poet and the thought process that led him/her to write the piece. In a sense, this was similar to the thrill of solving problems through computer programming. I remember this one section from “Macbeth” where Banquo talks about how “instruments of darkness” betray us in times of “deepest consequence”. While it seemed like just another English essay, Mr Andrews’ explanation of how Shakespeare wanted to portray the internal struggle and mental state of a man who is about to commit treason took me to a whole new dimension. This became even more captivating to me in times when he would ask us to go home and write a “critical appreciation” of a piece. One such sultry pensieve summer evening, critiquing Shakespeare, Yeates and Wordsworth, I decided to take up English as my subject in college. Little did I know that I was about to make the biggest blunder in my life. As poignant as it can be, in the words of Shakespeare, “violent delights have violent ends. The sweetest honey is loathsome in its own deliciousness. And in the taste, destroys the appetite.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had been told that taking up language studies in college was a humbling and character-building experience, as one would step into the shoes of bards and authors, and as if through the moulding effect of fire, become like the glass that provides the reflection of society through literature. However, within a month of going to English honours classes in college, I started feeling the disconnection from what I had been promised by the likes of teachers like Mr Andrews and what it really meant to study English as a subject. During the breaks between classes, I would meet my friends from the Computer Science department. Hearing them talk about the courses they were taking reminded me of the thrill I felt as a child conquering the uncharted waters like Vasco da Gama. Those breaks between classes made me hear a voice that wouldn’t whispering inside me, telling me that I belonged there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a long battle convincing the Dean and the Vice-Principal, I was permitted to change my stream from Humanities to Science, and on to familiar ground of Computer Science. And I never looked back since. Finally, I was finally home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My quest has taken me from the careless student, to the joyful explorer to the easily-influenced teenager to the college student who could finally sit down and enjoy a subject in its most enthralling form as well as its most unforgiving form. Unlike many people, I was extremely lucky in finding a subject I truly loved. If I have any advice to give to young students, it is that finding one’s calling is as important as not being led to believe someone else’s love for something as one’s own. A teacher can be a guide in helping you find your calling or alienate you from your calling or project their calling onto you. It’s up to you to distinguish between the three and find your true calling, without which you might end up taking the road to perdition in the rat race to a “good career”.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>{&quot;twitter&quot;=&gt;&quot;mourjo_sen&quot;}</name></author><category term="non-tech" /><summary type="html">There are few junctures in life which are as significant choosing what you do right after school. Your parents have told you this, your teachers keep telling you this and deep down, you either believe them and slog your way through the two final years of school, or if you are like me, don’t believe a word of what everyone else is saying and hope to wiggle your way into the adult world some way or another. The second approach — my approach — isn’t for the faint-hearted, and it carries with it a bucketful of enormous risks. I wouldn’t advise it to myself if I could travel back in time. But in an odd way, I am thankful for the way things turned out. The thing about taking risks is, if it pans out for you, the reward is the justification, but paradoxically, the promise of the same reward is not enough to risk it all. This is the story of such a journey: a teacher who was so good, he almost ruined my life.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The fairy tale of life</title><link href="https://mourjo.me/blog/non-tech/2012/11/12/the-fairy-tale-of-life/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The fairy tale of life" /><published>2012-11-12T11:55:10+05:30</published><updated>2012-11-12T11:55:10+05:30</updated><id>https://mourjo.me/blog/non-tech/2012/11/12/the-fairy-tale-of-life</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mourjo.me/blog/non-tech/2012/11/12/the-fairy-tale-of-life/">&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Heaven’s morning breaks and earth’s vain shadows flee;
&lt;br /&gt;
In life, in death, O Lord, abide with me.”&lt;br /&gt;
- Henry Francis Lyte&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mimi (my mother’s sister)’s health had been silently deteriorating from inside during the last two months. Medical treatment came with her daily bread all throughout her life, and probably that’s why I had initially not been much alarmed by her failing health as narrated by my mother, who had been her guide through thick and thin, especially after her trip to Thailand. But none of us, not even she herself, expected it to end all when it did. A dear one’s death, of course is never easy to accept. When her lifeless body was brought home for everyone to pay their respects, I felt a lump in my throat, but I knew that now she rests beneath the heavenly skies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I tried writing about her life because I trust her life deserves to be told but I soon gathered that the profundity of the agony that was her life cannot be appreciated nor valued by simple narration. So I look at it from a different angle – investigating how altered her life and everyone’s around her would be if she was not so ill fated to have been a victim of immuno-suppressive disease &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Xeroderma_pigmentosum&quot;&gt;xeroderma pigmentosum&lt;/a&gt; – the lifelong battle to which she finally had to succumb to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have analysed many people, including my father, who had a rich, memorable childhood with cousins from the paternal as well as the maternal side. If the heavens were sympathetic enough to grant Mimi a ‘normal’ life, she might have had her own family with a husband, children and her own self-sustaining life and I would probably have a few cousins of my own. Maybe one of them would also share my passion for computer science and we could share ideas just like my father and mother do with their cousins. Bhaiphota and Bijoya Dashami reunions would be days of excitement, fun and frolic and the house would be full of people spreading enjoyment – it would be as charming as flowers blooming on a country churchyard. Children running around, mother and Mimi engaged in organising the Bijoya dinner party and my father and Mesho (as Mimi’s husband would be called) sitting at the drawing room sofa discussing matters that we young people consider boring is a most common sight at every mamabari – but not mine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have seen my Thamma going often to her brothers’ and sisters’ places to spend an evening, a day or sometimes even a week just for a change of air. Picturing my mother going to my Mesho’s house to spend a day or two, or to help Mimi shop for the Pujo, or help her decide the wedding dress for Mimi’s eldest daughter is what I would pray to God for my mother because just like any other sibling, she deserves such joys. My mother and Mimi might also together have arranged a trip for my grandparents to Thailand, instead of just my mother. Mimi, if her health had permitted, could’ve turned out to be a professor of Geography, or might have worked at a corporate office and the two sisters could collaborate and share their work experiences with each other – as I have noticed my father does with his siblings. But that was what one can have hoped – the truth is far from it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having all children successful in their own lives, managing their own family, and living happily is what every parent wants to see. I remember Dadu had said, after my uncle got married and settled down, that he had nothing else to worry about in his life. Seeing the realisation of the well wishes of a parent for the eldest child was never to be so for my grandparents. Seeing the excitement that we as children spark in my grandparents’ faces, I can hardly envision how fulfilling it would make them feel to have four or five grandchildren from both their daughters gather around and listen to the stories of mythical creatures and scientific discoveries of the past that they told me when I was a child. My grandfather would have more grandchildren to distribute the priceless fruits of his rooftop garden while my grandmother would probably have a granddaughter to teach how to wear a saree and how to look like a princess. If all of that were to happen, Dadua and Dida would, like Dadu, have nothing else to worry about for the rest of their lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most common things one associates life with – a job, professional life, marriage, family and children of one’s own – were way out of reach for her. If the stars hadn’t given her such a painful life, then like my mother, even she would have, above all, her own wing of the family tree. Maybe in her college days, she might even have met her soul mate, who she would later marry and have a love story to tell her grandchildren! She might also have perfected her praiseworthy skills in embroidery to run a small scale successful business. In short, she would have a world of her own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Words are incapable to describe how spectacularly different Mimi’s life would be if her well-being was guaranteed. Although she survived for 48 years, much unlike the doctors’ predictions when she was first diagnosed with the disease, it deprived her of the basic joys of life. Apart from the rewards of an average life, she would also be happily ignorant of a disease called Xeroderma Pigmentosa and blissfully unfamiliar with eye institutes like the L. V. Prasad Eye Institute in Hyderabad that one would go to for treating tumours in eyes and be relieved of the excruciating pain that is accompanied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Imagination, once unleashed, is in its nature to run beyond the boundaries of reality. Mimi’s fate was such that at the age two years, the stars decided that she would be deprived of the things one would expect to have in life and was left alone, diseased, with a crippled vision. Instead of children, she had medicines – steroids for her eyes that would have to be applied every fifteen minutes all throughout the day and night like a new born baby needs attention all through the day; instead of her own family, she had appointments with doctors; in place of a job, she had corneal grafting in her eyes in multiple occasions; instead of her own wedding, she missed some of her younger sister’s wedding ceremonies because of the critical condition of her eyes. Xeroderma pigmentosum is said to occur in one individual for every 250,000 and on top of that, it is roughly six times more common in Japanese people than in other groups. It has been said with truth that fate is never without a sense of irony.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I have illustrated here is not the life of a queen, but one that every common man lives and takes for granted. Even an ordinary life was too good to be true for her, like a fairy tale – one she might only dream of, but never make real. But even if we do not consider the fruits of normal life, she had to fight for the very things that we take for granted from birth – her eyesight became steadily weaker year after year. There was a time when she exclaimed with joy that she could make out if there was a car a few feet ahead of her and she considered that day to be lucky to have even that little vision. Because the battle that she had to put up with all through her life, she understood the sick and the needy better than anyone else I know. She had always put her best foot forward to help those who needed her even before they could call for help – be it my brother while having a minor surgery, or the poor children of Kathamrita Shangha who were cold and needed warm clothes in winter – she herself went and cared however she could, often transcending her own physical limitations. Sometimes the little things that one do make one great. Her memory will live on through us and her story deserves to be told and listened. But more than that, there’s a lot to learn from her that the Divine Providence taught her – “to give and not to count the cost, to fight and not to heed the wounds, to toil and not to seek for rest, to labour and not to ask for reward”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have seen so many people who have so much to be happy about but still mourn the smallest of things that they couldn’t have. The struggle that she knew life to be from the tender age of two years is an example how one who had almost nothing in her life could still be content with it. All her life, in spite of the pain she had a firm belief in the Almighty. Although she was put through what seems almost too much, she never lost her faith, and it was that faith that carried her forward and gave her the will to fight and the zeal to survive. I am left in utter amazement and respect for her as my grandmother narrates how painful her childhood, adolescence and adulthood were. All along, her constant companion was pain. I can vividly recall the last few days of her life in the ICU – the strong odour of antibiotics, medicines and disinfectants or the smell of death as I now call it, made me dizzy but she fought on, with determination in her spirit and to the daze of the doctors, till her last breath for she was born into a world to fight, struggle and return triumphant like the charge of the Light Brigade in the battle of Balaclava in 1854. I feel her life was not a journey, it was a test of her endurance – a test by God Himself to see how long before she breaks – and she never did, she never gave up – not even on her deathbed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;“When can their glory fade?&lt;br /&gt;
O the wild charge they made!&lt;br /&gt;
All the world wonder’d.”&lt;br /&gt;
- Lord Alfred Tennyson&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>{&quot;twitter&quot;=&gt;&quot;mourjo_sen&quot;}</name></author><category term="non-tech" /><summary type="html">“Heaven’s morning breaks and earth’s vain shadows flee; In life, in death, O Lord, abide with me.” - Henry Francis Lyte</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A different kind of nostalgia</title><link href="https://mourjo.me/blog/non-tech/2012/10/11/a-different-kind-of-nostalgia/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A different kind of nostalgia" /><published>2012-10-11T11:55:10+05:30</published><updated>2012-10-11T11:55:10+05:30</updated><id>https://mourjo.me/blog/non-tech/2012/10/11/a-different-kind-of-nostalgia</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mourjo.me/blog/non-tech/2012/10/11/a-different-kind-of-nostalgia/">&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Whoever loved that loved not at first sight?”&lt;br /&gt;
- William Shakespeare&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I must have been eight or nine when my parents took me and my brother for a trip to the northern hills. As far as I can recall, we were a lively family group of nine. The trip was centred on Sikkim. When my mother first told me of the trip to the hills, I had pictured myself with a ruck sack and climbing up the rocks of the mountains. Unfortunately the reality didn’t remotely resemble that. In its place, to my utter dissatisfaction, I had to endure five-hour rides in ancient land rovers every day from one hill station to another. I didn’t particularly enjoy that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nothing in that trip was exceptional. Yes, a group of fun-loving folk is always much of a pleasure to be a part of even if you are an introvert but apart from the merry and the mirth that my family always brings to me, nothing in that portion of the trip was so fulfilling that I would write about twelve years later. To my wonder, the part of the tour that I least expected from became what I remember that trip by, even today. Life surprises us from where we least expect it to – one might call that divine comedy. As per plan, my parents, my brother and I extended our trip by a few more days after the rest of the group had gone back to Kolkata. The four of us yet again embarked on another of those long jeep-rides to Darjeeling. Quite naturally I didn’t think Darjeeling, which I had first heard of only a few months back, would be any different from the places we’d already been to. Never had I been so pleased to have been proven wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On our way to Darjeeling, I had slept off in the first half of the journey so can’t recollect much. However, I do remember that after travelling quite a large section of the journey, my father started telling us how Darjeeling was not just another tourist destination for him. I listened intently and got deeply absorbed into everything he was saying. Much too soon, as it seemed, the driver called to me as we were nearing a bend, pointing his index finger straight at the hills at a distance. I could see a town sitting on the ridges of the gorgeous hills afar, like a child sleeping quietly on her mother’s lap. “Do you see that?” he said to me, “That is Darjeeling”. Everything about that trip changed that instant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every time I tell the story of why Darjeeling is special, for some very peculiar reason, I refer to it in first person, though I shouldn’t, technically, as it was all about long before I was born. I learned, for the first time, that we once lived there. That is, when my grandfather was of my age, the family lived in Darjeeling in a moderately sized middle-class house known as ‘Senabash’, meaning home to the Sen Family. The name itself felt enchanting to my ears. Later on in the tour, we had visited the ruins of the still standing storm-wrecked Senabash.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Senabash is located at Ghoom, the station before Darjeeling railway station and isn’t very far from the town centre of Darjeeling. As the story goes, the members of the then joint Sen Family used to run their own indigenous businesses like a dairy called ‘Kanchan Dairy’, which was highly reputed among the people of the town for its quality, a poultry farm, and a piggery among others. My grandfather’s uncle (passionately called ‘Naw-kaka’), who became the head of the house after the demise of my great grandfather, was a believer in Acharya Prafulla Chandra Ray’s ideals of Bengalis becoming entrepreneurs. When there was no one to maintain the family businesses, under his able leadership, it flourished to newer heights. But, with drift of the rural population slowly shifting towards the urban areas after independence, the flow also caught our family. Soon, the young generation in the family were drawn to more economically promising lands like Kolkata and government jobs with their guaranteed salary at the end of the month seemed to be an easier livelihood. But the very thought of living in the hills of Darjeeling with our own family, self-sustaining small scale businesses left me in wonder of how beautifully simple life could be – every member works in their own way throughout the day from early in the morning and rejoice in the unadorned joy of being together in the evening. The fast moving urban lifestyle takes the living out of life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The wooden house of Senabash was where my grandfather had grown up and my father, too, had spent a portion of his childhood there. The weather in Darjeeling is often very damp and one has to befriend the rain if one is to survive in a hill station like Darjeeling. Indeed that is why there was a room dedicated for umbrellas at Senabash! The other room that I have often heard of is Naw-kaka’s room. It is said that also my grandfather, the eldest of his brothers and sisters, feared to tread when he was at meditation. Respect sometimes is mistaken for fear. On the table in Naw-kaka’s room one would always find a bronze Buddha, as I am told. His sturdy belief in the Buddha (as evident from his daily meditation sessions) has reflected on my father –he, too, keeps a metallic Buddha at his study. As I have never had the pleasure to have entered it, Senabash is a palace of dreams. Like many a child, I had the habit of weaving images of what I heard as stories and from what I heard about our association with Darjeeling, I couldn’t wait to visit Senabash. Those images still take me back to past that I was not a part of but somehow I feel I belong there. Anyway, we contacted my father’s uncle (also called ‘Mejo-kaka’) who at that time still lived at a house next to Senabash and finally visited the ancestral home. Standing in front of it, the depth of its history made me feel very trivial in the sands of time, and also at the same time, a part of something great. There were two V-shaped diverging small flights of stairs leading to the front porch of the house. I found out that throughout its history, the members of the extended Sen Family would come from different parts of the country to Senabash for a family reunion once or twice a year. It was a time of immense festivity at Senabash, as my father recalls, with everyone having so much to share and even more to catch up with. On that same V-shaped stairs, on such reunions, typical family photographs would be taken each time, which became a tradition. As we stood there before what was left of Senabash, we too abided by that tradition and had a group photo in that exact same arrangement as it would be during the glorious days of Senabash. It was as if I could hear voices from inside the house and visualise the revelry of getting together, as we stood there. To a passer-by, it would be just the ruins of an old house but for me it was materialisation of our past and everything I heard and imagined about Senabash. I could stand there and revere it all day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mejo-kaka’s house overlooked the picturesque Batasia loop where the toy train would take a round in a loop and return back. The toy train is the pride of Darjeeling. It was a sight to behold. The view from hill resplendent as it was, it was not the most famous view of Batasia loop – what I saw was a foggy view of the faintly visible toy train making the loop. The occasional wooing sound of the whistle of the toy train ruptured the silence of the hills as the train broke through a wall of fog. Every time the whistling stopped, silence descended on the hills like night falls on a desert after a hot afternoon. It was reverence – the sight, the sound and the silence. The reason it is so distinctive is because the atmosphere itself was very typically Darjeeling – misty, moist and mysteriously amazing. My father every so often tells us that Batasia loop was far more splendid when he was of my age and the beautification has robbed it of its natural beauty. In spite of that, it was a spectacle I recall often in my mind and it always brings a smile to my face – it is my host of golden daffodils:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;“For oft, when on my couch I lie&lt;br /&gt;
In vacant or in pensive mood,&lt;br /&gt;
They flash upon that inward eye,&lt;br /&gt;
Which is the bliss of solitude”&lt;br /&gt;
– William Wordsworth&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the bond with Darjeeling that I cherish, to the walks along the undulating roads of the town and the flat paradise of the mall, from Keventer’s to Glenary’s, from the Darjeeling railway station to the Ghoom monastery – everything in Darjeeling has attached with it fondness, love and emotion. After that trip, I had been to Darjeeling about six times and every time I reach the queen of the hills, I don’t want to come back. It so happened that on one such trip to Darjeeling, due to terrible weather conditions, we couldn’t leave on the day we had to. And that was a godsend for me. I prayed that it would rain like that for the next few days too – unfortunately that didn’t happen!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The term nostalgia describes a sentimental longing for the past, typically for a period or place with happy personal associations. But for me, although I do not have any factual personal associations, the heritage of Senabash and every story I heard of it has helped bridge the divide between what is real and what is felt only in the mind. Every time I think about Senabash, I feel that even I am a part of its legacy – or rather it is a part of me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It might be a cliché to say so but from the first moment I saw Darjeeling, I fell in love with her. For me, coming to Darjeeling is not a tour to the northern hills – it is homecoming.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>{&quot;twitter&quot;=&gt;&quot;mourjo_sen&quot;}</name></author><category term="non-tech" /><summary type="html">“Whoever loved that loved not at first sight?” - William Shakespeare</summary></entry></feed>