<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://mourjo.me/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://mourjo.me/blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-12-05T18:02:45+01:00</updated><id>https://mourjo.me/blog/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Mourjo Sen’s Blog</title><subtitle>Thoughts of a software engineer about life, tech and everything in between. A place to put down my thoughts for my own recollection more than anything else. If you like it, be sure to drop me an email!</subtitle><author><name>{&quot;twitter&quot;=&gt;&quot;mourjo_sen&quot;}</name></author><entry><title type="html">Motivation Is Not Everything</title><link href="https://mourjo.me/blog/non-tech/2024/12/03/motivation-is-not-everything/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Motivation Is Not Everything" /><published>2024-12-03T19:31:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-12-03T19:31:00+01:00</updated><id>https://mourjo.me/blog/non-tech/2024/12/03/motivation-is-not-everything</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mourjo.me/blog/non-tech/2024/12/03/motivation-is-not-everything/"><![CDATA[<p>This year, I did not miss a single day of learning French on Duolingo, even if only for five minutes. Through it, I learnt a lot about the process of learning, looking back:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Motivation</strong> comes and goes, relying on motivation alone is unsustainable</li>
  <li>There will be good days and there will be better days</li>
  <li><strong>Showing up every day</strong> is winning half the battle</li>
  <li>I overestimated what I can do in a day</li>
  <li>I underestimated what I can do in a year</li>
</ul>

<p>There are very few things that pay off as much as self discipline and habit forming.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Some people say the most important thing a fighter can have is heart. Frankie’d say: show me a fighter who was nothing but heart and I’ll show you a man waiting for a beating.</p>

  <p>– Million Dollar Baby</p>
</blockquote>

<p><img src="/blog/images/duolingo.png" alt="Image Description" /></p>]]></content><author><name>{&quot;twitter&quot;=&gt;&quot;mourjo_sen&quot;}</name></author><category term="non-tech" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This year, I did not miss a single day of learning French on Duolingo, even if only for five minutes. Through it, I learnt a lot about the process of learning, looking back: Motivation comes and goes, relying on motivation alone is unsustainable There will be good days and there will be better days Showing up every day is winning half the battle I overestimated what I can do in a day I underestimated what I can do in a year There are very few things that pay off as much as self discipline and habit forming.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">In memoriam</title><link href="https://mourjo.me/blog/non-tech/2024/01/03/in-memoriam/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="In memoriam" /><published>2024-01-03T20:37:12+01:00</published><updated>2024-01-03T20:37:12+01:00</updated><id>https://mourjo.me/blog/non-tech/2024/01/03/in-memoriam</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mourjo.me/blog/non-tech/2024/01/03/in-memoriam/"><![CDATA[<p>The similarity was uncanny. Over the years, I remember comparing my palm side-by-side to his - it is an almost identical copy of Dadua’s. In fact, I would say it with pride – a cherished emblem that I carried with a sense of honour. When I heard the heartbreaking news at three in the morning, my immediate response was to look at my own palm in the dim light of the smartphone, not knowing what this meant or how to feel about it.</p>

<p><em>I kept staring at my palm in the engulfing darkness of the cold Dutch night.</em></p>

<p>As a child of parents with transferable jobs, my boyhood unfolded across various locations: Alipore, Birbhum, Bardhaman and Salt Lake. One place that was constant throughout was Lake Temple Road and Dadua. My earliest memories as a child were with Dadua. His cane with an elephant’s trunk curve at the end, his fast strides which were so hard for my short legs to keep up with, the crisp morning air of Rabindra Sarobar lake before day break, and of course the “notun jinish dekhbo” which was an euphemism for toys without my mother realising I am asking for something new.</p>

<p>While I was too young to fully remember the morning walks I took with Dadua, fragments of those memories linger in my mind. I recall moments such as meeting his friends by the lake, to the local chaiwalla who knew precisely what everyone wanted, to the almost superhero names I had for each of his friends (like Amloki-dadu and Bhim-dadu). Sometimes in the evenings he would take me for a walk around the lake as well, but this time, it was not to meet his friends, but to have a Vadilal ice cream and sometimes freshly roasted peanuts. To this day, the smell of warm peanuts takes me back to that time. I was old enough when I got the news of him passing away in his sleep, yet deep down, I was still the little boy who yearns for one more morning walk with his grandfather.</p>

<p><em>I kept staring at my palm in the engulfing darkness of the cold Dutch night.</em></p>

<p>In Bardhaman, we resided in an expansive estate adorned with boundless fields of crops and parks full of flowers and orchards teeming with trees. I remember Dadua took me on a tour of the estate sharing his knowledge about crops and the art of nurturing plant life. As a lifelong gardener himself, he imparted a wealth of wisdom to my uncomprehending preadolescent ears.</p>

<p>Although I may not recall the intricacies of gardening techniques, certain moments are indelibly engraved as if they were from last week. One such recollection is him showing me how to collect dried seeds from different fruits and use them as beads to play with and make little craft items of it. Of all the toys I received as gifts that birthday in Bardhaman, today I seem to only recall this: a concoction of odd plant seeds that remain etched in memory because of the loving embrace of a grandfather and the spark of creativity that was so very characteristic of Dadua.</p>

<p>He not only was creative himself, but ignited creativity in others too. I daresay, my mother’s fondness for recitation was kindled by Dadua. During one summer, I made a toy “smart” watch from a piece of black cardboard and a few hand-drawn digital dials. Mimi took me to a tailor to procure an elastic strap for the watch band, and with Dadua’s assistance, we assembled it all together. While I merely did it to emulate all the watch-wearing grown ups around me, Dadua confided in me that as a boy he also used scrap material as a child to craft things. This early inclination eventually led him to create his vast collection of handmade artefacts. I recall he said to me a few years later that art is different to each of us –  everyone looking at the same tree but since every other person is seeing it from a different vantage point, it is not really the same tree they are looking at – everyone’s impression of the same tree is different.</p>

<p><em>I kept staring at my palm in the engulfing darkness of the cold Dutch night.</em></p>

<p>Atop the four-storey building on Lake Temple Road, was a sanctuary of lush platlife – all meticulously tended to by Dadua. For the longest time, Lake Temple felt akin to the story of Charlie’s chocolate factory, only healthier – abounding with banana, papaya, cauliflower, coriander, mango, pumpkin, chillies, shojne, and the lemons. On numerous occasions, Dadua would take my brother and me to the roof to pick out lemons straight from the tree. As we plucked the fruit from the plant, the natural aroma of the gondhoraj lemons permeated the air while we helped him bag the lemons for us to take home.</p>

<p>At one point of time, there was even a water reservoir to cultivate fish on the same rooftop.
Picture this: smack in the heart of the urban grey slate of Calcutta, a green nugget of nature nestled in the unlikely location of a rooftop, tended to by one man - where plant and waterlife thrived alike. I would call that Eden on Earth, wouldn’t you?</p>

<p style="font-size: 18px; text-align: center;">
আমার মুক্তি আলোয় আলোয় এই আকাশে <br />
আমার মুক্তি ধুলায় ধুলায় ঘাসে ঘাসে
</p>

<p>Dadua was a man at one with nature, and nature reciprocated that connection. He used to often tell us that plants have feelings and plants understand when they are cared for. During his younger days, he ventured far and wide in search of plants that were uncommon and unthinkable to grow on small pots. The mango plant for instance, that grew on a pot and bore fruit all throughout the year, was an accomplishment that filled him particularly with pride.</p>

<p><em>I kept staring at my palm in the engulfing darkness of the cold Dutch night.</em></p>

<p>As I grew from a toddler to “a young man”, as he would phrase it, Dadua shared stories, folktales, Sanskrit slokas and poems with me and my brother. He tried his best to instil in us the wisdom from passages from many pieces of literature. Long before I could grasp the concept of religion, I had already committed to memory some of the verses from Ma Durga’s prayers. Even these days during Ashtami anjali, the verse “Sarbamangala Mangalyay” triggers the memory of Dadua sitting on is armchair, with his red book of Hindu Slokas in his hand reading passages out to us in the backdrop of the soft rustling of leaves from the trees he planted in the driveway of Lake Temple road.</p>

<p>Dadua was known to be a master-reciter, with the innate ability to recall thousand-line poems like he was reading an invisible paper in front of him. Once on Rabindrajayanti at the Lake, he brought me to one of his performances. Although I did not understand the poem, I did understand that everyone’s attention was pinned on his recitation. He taught me many poems from the “Sishu” collection of Tagore’s poems made specifically for children.</p>

<p style="font-size: 18px; text-align: center;">
মনে করো যেন বিদেশ ঘুরে <br />
মাকে নিয়ে যাচ্ছি অনেক দূরে <br />
তুমি যাচ্ছ পালকিতে মা চড়ে <br />
আমি যাচ্ছি রাঙা ঘোড়ার ‘পরে <br />
</p>

<p><em>I kept staring at my palm in the engulfing darkness of the cold Dutch night.</em></p>

<p>Dadua was a captivating storyteller. As I grew older, the stories he told me also took a more mature form. What were stories from the Ramayan and Mahabharat, became anecdotes from his own life and choices that defined who he was. He recounted the river next to his childhood home in Comilla where fishermen sold fish right after catching it, his boyhood days spent in his school Ishwar Pathshala, his meeting Rabindranath Tagore, about his aspirations for going to art school, fond recollections of his mother, whom he lost at an early age, of the stern yet spirited chancellor of BE college of yesteryear and of Vergese Kurian, founder of Amul, who was his classmate at National Dairy Research Institute in Bangalore.</p>

<p>His home in SN Banerjee Road was close to Anadi Cabin. On the day of his graduation from BE College, he recalled how much he enjoyed a plate of Mughlai Parathas – he fondly recalled that the owner of the restaurant (I think Anadi himself) decided not to charge him when he found out it was his graduation day.</p>

<p>I felt a profound connection to his stories, bupt none more than those centred around Kurseong and Keventer’s. Even till this day, a trip to Darjeeling is incomplete without visiting Keventer’s restaurant. His stories always took me to faraway hill stations that he visited – sometimes to supervise tea estates – sometimes to overlook another part of his business. On one occasion, he told us how he found his way to a cabin when his car had broken down in a hilly deserted forest, and in his hour of despair, he met a classmate from BE college.</p>

<p><em>I kept staring at my palm in the engulfing darkness of the cold Dutch night.</em></p>

<p>Mimi’s passing marked the end of what I recall as childhood. The house became quieter and both Dadua and Dia suddenly seemed to age overnight. Thus began a different era in Lake temple. Over the ensuing years, Dadua got ill a few times. After coming back from the hospital one time, he was quite frail and could barely make it to the dining table. Words that will forever keep ringing in my ears were “Dadua kheyecho” (he used to call me “Dadua” as well) – even in the weakest moments, he was still enquiring about my well-being. Lake temple right there, as it was, and as it is today, will always be defined by moments like these – transforming what I used to call “Daduar bari” to much more than a house and into something greater than myself, a cornerstone and source of eternal strength.</p>

<p><em>I kept staring at my palm in the engulfing darkness of the cold Dutch night.</em></p>

<p>The day after I got the news, I was looking for some photos of Dadua – I found many of Dia’s, only a few of Dadua’s. In one of them during bhai-phota, Dadua was there just in the background. I was about to scroll past it when it struck me that that was him in his true essence – ever present and away from the limelight. Even then, there was one photo on a warm summer’s noon, when he was front and centre, smiling as bright as the sun overhead. Being the eldest, I was the first in my generation to get a job. Mimi had long left for the heavenly abode and in the ensuing five years, the deepest sense of pride I ever allowed myself was when using my own money, I bought Dadua a Panjabi and Dia a saree. Oh you should have been there to see his smile. He didn’t have the habit of dressing up or going outside to restaurants but in his words “it’s to celebrate my Dadua’s first job, of course I will dress up”. One of the photos from that day captured his effervescent smile so well that it is being framed to be the photograph to remember him by. To mean as much to someone is not something I know how to put into words.</p>

<p><em>I kept staring at my palm in the engulfing darkness of the cold Dutch night.</em></p>

<p>Mohana met Dadua only after we got married. But she knew of him from our college days – till date, she recalls how awestruck she was hearing of Dadua’s technological prowess. Back in the early 2010s, we were all on the broadband bandwagon and it was liberating to have an omnipresent connection called “wifi”. It might have been considered a young man’s experiment in most households, but not in Lake Temple Road. Not only did Dadua have his own laptop, smartphone and wifi setup, he became quite famous among my friends for insisting to upgrade his poor BSNL network to a faster Airtel one! He honed new ideas for handicraft from the internet and I often got to see him trying new tools like a hot glue gun and coloured glue sticks, which he used to make desk items like pen holders.</p>

<p><em>I kept staring at my palm in the engulfing darkness of the cold Dutch night.</em></p>

<p>If you pass by Shib Mandir, you may be forgiven for not noticing the otherwise unremarkable building that stands at Lake Temple Road. To me though, it is a foundational pillar to who I was as a child and who I became as an adult, and Dadua is an integral part of that and I will forever miss him. I met Dadua for the last time on March 24, 2023. I am still grappling with the harsh reality that I will never see him again. What stays with me are his stories, his lifestyle, his teachings, and his appreciation for the arts. I recall him reciting the following passage often with glistening eyes. Today it holds a very special place as I cling to his memory.</p>

<p style="font-size: 18px; text-align: center;">
ফিরায়ে দিনু দ্বারের চাবি,  রাখি না আর ঘরের দাবি— <br />
সবার আজি প্রসাদবাণী চাই॥ <br />
অনেক দিন ছিলাম প্রতিবেশী, <br />
দিয়েছি যত নিয়েছি তার বেশি। <br />
</p>

<p><em>I kept staring at my palm in the engulfing darkness of the cold Dutch night.</em></p>]]></content><author><name>{&quot;twitter&quot;=&gt;&quot;mourjo_sen&quot;}</name></author><category term="non-tech" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The similarity was uncanny. Over the years, I remember comparing my palm side-by-side to his - it is an almost identical copy of Dadua’s. In fact, I would say it with pride – a cherished emblem that I carried with a sense of honour. When I heard the heartbreaking news at three in the morning, my immediate response was to look at my own palm in the dim light of the smartphone, not knowing what this meant or how to feel about it.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Exposing the page-view analytics of this site</title><link href="https://mourjo.me/blog/non-tech/2021/11/15/site-analytics/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Exposing the page-view analytics of this site" /><published>2021-11-15T06:37:12+01:00</published><updated>2021-11-15T06:37:12+01:00</updated><id>https://mourjo.me/blog/non-tech/2021/11/15/site-analytics</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mourjo.me/blog/non-tech/2021/11/15/site-analytics/"><![CDATA[<p>In this post, I expose the analytics of this site, mostly to convince myself that someone reads this (even if it’s my own private browser sessions)!</p>
<iframe width="100%" height="700" src="https://datastudio.google.com/embed/reporting/7f7b943a-c3a6-401e-9613-8f78b452befc/page/1jWfC" frameborder="0" style="border:0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>]]></content><author><name>{&quot;twitter&quot;=&gt;&quot;mourjo_sen&quot;}</name></author><category term="non-tech" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In this post, I expose the analytics of this site, mostly to convince myself that someone reads this (even if it’s my own private browser sessions)!]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">On building habits</title><link href="https://mourjo.me/blog/non-tech/2021/10/25/on-building-habits/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On building habits" /><published>2021-10-25T06:37:12+02:00</published><updated>2021-10-25T06:37:12+02:00</updated><id>https://mourjo.me/blog/non-tech/2021/10/25/on-building-habits</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mourjo.me/blog/non-tech/2021/10/25/on-building-habits/"><![CDATA[<p>During the last five years of my working life, I have come to realise that there are few
things that pay off in the long run as much as the ability to form habits easily. In
retrospect, starting to do something like working out every other day, reading at a
particular time of day, preparing for teaching a lesson – all have benefited from
repetitive incremental progress through habits. Here are three things that have helped me
build habits.</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Anchoring</strong>: While building habits, it is easier to associate the new activity to an
existing habit that you’re used to. For example, if going out for a run is already part
of your day, then adding a post-run task like having your pills is easier than
remembering to have it at 7 am. Once a habit becomes part of the day, it can then become
an anchor for another new habit.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Planning</strong>: Part of building a habit is repetition, and for something to be
repeatable, it should not change much. That is, chalk out a plan beforehand, maybe the
previous day (tweak it if required) but stick to it through thick and thin – take
the thinking or optionality out of the activity. If I am planning to run 5 km in the
morning, the option of cutting the run short should not even be present. A more detailed
plan, for example, a 1 km pre-run warm up and a post run cool down, takes the thinking
out of the picture and knowing it is obligatory even in those days that are
tiring, makes build the habit.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Reviewing</strong>: One of the best things a smart watch has helped me with, in so far as
workouts are considered, is a review of the last day/week’s activities. If I had been
able to do all of my workouts in the week, looking back and reviewing it is a great
sense of accomplishment, while not being able to do so is a reason to push harder in the
next day/week. In terms of general habit-building, such reviewing of past activities has
helped me make a conscious effort for those missed triggers, because as humans those are
bound to happen.</p>
  </li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name>{&quot;twitter&quot;=&gt;&quot;mourjo_sen&quot;}</name></author><category term="non-tech" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[During the last five years of my working life, I have come to realise that there are few things that pay off in the long run as much as the ability to form habits easily. In retrospect, starting to do something like working out every other day, reading at a particular time of day, preparing for teaching a lesson – all have benefited from repetitive incremental progress through habits. Here are three things that have helped me build habits.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Learning by teaching</title><link href="https://mourjo.me/blog/mentoring/2021/09/23/learning-by-teaching/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Learning by teaching" /><published>2021-09-23T06:37:11+02:00</published><updated>2021-09-23T06:37:11+02:00</updated><id>https://mourjo.me/blog/mentoring/2021/09/23/learning-by-teaching</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mourjo.me/blog/mentoring/2021/09/23/learning-by-teaching/"><![CDATA[<p>In an <a href="/blog/mentoring/2021/06/15/a-personal-challenge/">earlier post</a>, I wrote that I was embarking on a journey of teaching the fundamentals of Computer Science to Otee. The journey thus far has been incredible, and it is inspiring to think that in the span of three months, all of the following have happened.</p>

<ul>
  <li>Functional programming</li>
  <li>Advanced data structures (including Bloom filters!)</li>
  <li>Two major projects: A <a href="https://otee.dev/2021/08/24/crisp-a-simple-lisp-interpreter.html">Lisp interpreter</a> and a <a href="https://twitter.com/cardimomT">blog post tweet bot</a> that I hope will publish this post</li>
  <li>Computer architecture, all the way from the hardware to the instruction execution cycle</li>
</ul>

<p>One of the perks of being able to have the opportunity to teach the fundamentals is that I get to relearn these concepts from a very different perspective, all over again. I have had to research on my own before I feel confident enough to teach and what that has opened up for me, is to see those concepts deep down through the experience of being in the industry for five years.</p>

<p>Teaching something convincingly requires research and it is liberating to be able to learn all those things again, and I would highly recommend this to anyone who enjoys this subject. Imagine thinking from first principles and even questioning those first principles. When I was first exposed to the fundamentals, I didn’t know any better than to take things at their face value and that obviously left holes in my knowledge, not to mention all the things I didn’t even remember I had once learned. During the depths of the pandemic, learning by teaching has been one of the most rewarding exercises.</p>

<p>If you are curious about <a href="https://twitter.com/oteecodes">Otee’s</a> journey, you can follow <a href="https://otee.dev">him here</a>!</p>]]></content><author><name>{&quot;twitter&quot;=&gt;&quot;mourjo_sen&quot;}</name></author><category term="mentoring" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In an earlier post, I wrote that I was embarking on a journey of teaching the fundamentals of Computer Science to Otee. The journey thus far has been incredible, and it is inspiring to think that in the span of three months, all of the following have happened.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A personal challenge</title><link href="https://mourjo.me/blog/mentoring/2021/06/15/a-personal-challenge/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A personal challenge" /><published>2021-06-15T07:37:11+02:00</published><updated>2021-06-15T07:37:11+02:00</updated><id>https://mourjo.me/blog/mentoring/2021/06/15/a-personal-challenge</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mourjo.me/blog/mentoring/2021/06/15/a-personal-challenge/"><![CDATA[<p>Oitee is convinced that he can learn Computer Science basics as a part-time activity. I
decided to help him with this endeavour. Being from a non-technical background, his
knowledge of Computer Science is limited to high school HelloWorlds. It is both a huge
responsibility and honour for me to be part of his journey. My paramount goal is to ensure
the gets a <em>good enough</em> guidance to venture into this field. The weight of being able to
show the right path is heavy, but it is worth trying.</p>

<p>Here’s what I have in mind (it is probably going to change). I have created the following
broad headings of what I think are the most useful areas to spend time on.</p>

<ol>
  <li>CS fundamentals
    <ul>
      <li>Computer Architecture</li>
      <li>Networking</li>
      <li>Operating Systems</li>
      <li>Databases</li>
      <li>Basics of a compiler</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Programming
    <ul>
      <li>Javascript basics from <a href="https://www.freecodecamp.org/learn/javascript-algorithms-and-data-structures/#claim-cert-block">FreeCodeCamp</a></li>
      <li>Data structures</li>
      <li>Algorithms</li>
      <li>Problem solving (something like <a href="http://leetcode.com">Leetcode</a>)</li>
      <li>Functional languages / OOP</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Tooling workflows
    <ul>
      <li>Linux CLI</li>
      <li>Git</li>
      <li>Visual Studio Code</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Web Development (after 1)
    <ul>
      <li>Server / Client</li>
      <li>Web scale, components, technologies</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>I pondered a lot on which language and IDE to suggest for him to learn. Eventually I concluded
that Javascript and VS Code seem to be the most ubiquitous combination there is for web
development. <a href="https://lambdaschool.com/courses/full-stack-web-development">Lambda School</a>
also seems to be favouring Javascript.</p>

<p>The list above is biased on what I think I am good enough to guide with. Much to the same
reason, there is no mention of machine learning or frontend technologies like CSS,
although a bit of that might be necessary.</p>

<p>At the end of six months from now, based on the progress, my objective is for him to be
ready for applying to coding bootcamps like <a href="https://www.recurse.com">Recurse Centre</a>. If
not that, then with some more work, a candidate for applying to junior engineering
positions, like I did back in 2015 – only better than what I was back then.</p>

<p>In an effort to prove to myself that I could take on this long and ardous (and eventually
rewarding) journey, I hope to publish regular posts here about the progress I am making as
a guide, so stay tuned and if you’re reading this, wish me luck!</p>]]></content><author><name>{&quot;twitter&quot;=&gt;&quot;mourjo_sen&quot;}</name></author><category term="mentoring" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Oitee is convinced that he can learn Computer Science basics as a part-time activity. I decided to help him with this endeavour. Being from a non-technical background, his knowledge of Computer Science is limited to high school HelloWorlds. It is both a huge responsibility and honour for me to be part of his journey. My paramount goal is to ensure the gets a good enough guidance to venture into this field. The weight of being able to show the right path is heavy, but it is worth trying.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Medium Index</title><link href="https://mourjo.me/blog/hidden/2020/09/03/medium-index/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Medium Index" /><published>2020-09-03T03:44:11+02:00</published><updated>2020-09-03T03:44:11+02:00</updated><id>https://mourjo.me/blog/hidden/2020/09/03/medium-index</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mourjo.me/blog/hidden/2020/09/03/medium-index/"><![CDATA[<!-- BLOG-POST-LIST:START -->
<ul>
  <li><a href="https://mourjo.medium.com/three-reasons-why-developers-should-use-duckdb-0884c8e9f02a?source=rss-c69a7b7ed0c5------2">Three reasons why developers should use DuckDB</a><span class="copy"> — 14 Jul 2024</span></li>
  <li><a href="https://medium.com/booking-com-development/unlocking-observability-structured-logging-in-spring-boot-c81dbabfb9e7?source=rss-c69a7b7ed0c5------2">Unlocking observability: Structured logging in Spring Boot</a><span class="copy"> — 26 Mar 2024</span></li>
  <li><a href="https://mourjo.medium.com/building-a-secure-web-chat-with-redis-mtls-and-gcp-e52007ba362d?source=rss-c69a7b7ed0c5------2">Deep-dive on mTLS with Redis on GCP</a><span class="copy"> — 22 Feb 2023</span></li>
  <li><a href="https://medium.com/helpshift-engineering/load-shedding-in-clojure-d4857ce11588?source=rss-c69a7b7ed0c5------2">Load Shedding in Clojure</a><span class="copy"> — 21 Sep 2020</span></li>
  <li><a href="https://medium.com/helpshift-engineering/load-shedding-in-web-services-9fa8cfa1ffe4?source=rss-c69a7b7ed0c5------2">Load Shedding in Web Services</a><span class="copy"> — 04 Sep 2020</span></li>
  <li><a href="https://medium.com/helpshift-engineering/the-convoluted-magic-of-leiningen-test-selectors-2eb6c452dfcf?source=rss-c69a7b7ed0c5------2">The Convoluted Magic of Leiningen Test Selectors</a><span class="copy"> — 02 May 2020</span></li>
  <li><a href="https://medium.com/helpshift-engineering/achieving-graceful-restarts-of-clojure-services-b3a3b9c1d60d?source=rss-c69a7b7ed0c5------2">Killing me softly: Graceful shutdowns in Clojure</a><span class="copy"> — 27 Jan 2020</span></li>
  <li><a href="https://medium.com/helpshift-engineering/on-the-testability-of-ring-middlewares-in-clojure-6795eae60f2a?source=rss-c69a7b7ed0c5------2">On the testability of Ring Middlewares in Clojure</a><span class="copy"> — 06 Dec 2019</span></li>
  <li><a href="https://medium.com/helpshift-engineering/a-study-in-parallelising-tests-b5253817beae?source=rss-c69a7b7ed0c5------2">A Study in Parallelising Tests</a><span class="copy"> — 15 May 2019</span></li>
  <li><a href="https://medium.com/helpshift-engineering/scylladb-the-helpshift-story-3d332bf80ce2?source=rss-c69a7b7ed0c5------2">ScyllaDB: The Helpshift Story</a><span class="copy"> — 03 Apr 2019</span></li>
  <li><a href="https://mourjo.medium.com/a-detailed-comparison-between-autocompletion-strategies-in-elasticsearch-66cb9e9c62c4">A detailed comparison between autocompletion strategies in ElasticSearch</a><span class="copy"> — 30 Aug 2018</span></li>
</ul>

<!-- BLOG-POST-LIST:END -->]]></content><author><name>{&quot;twitter&quot;=&gt;&quot;mourjo_sen&quot;}</name></author><category term="hidden" /><category term="hidden" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Three reasons why developers should use DuckDB — 14 Jul 2024 Unlocking observability: Structured logging in Spring Boot — 26 Mar 2024 Deep-dive on mTLS with Redis on GCP — 22 Feb 2023 Load Shedding in Clojure — 21 Sep 2020 Load Shedding in Web Services — 04 Sep 2020 The Convoluted Magic of Leiningen Test Selectors — 02 May 2020 Killing me softly: Graceful shutdowns in Clojure — 27 Jan 2020 On the testability of Ring Middlewares in Clojure — 06 Dec 2019 A Study in Parallelising Tests — 15 May 2019 ScyllaDB: The Helpshift Story — 03 Apr 2019 A detailed comparison between autocompletion strategies in ElasticSearch — 30 Aug 2018]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Positive feedback loop, Darwin and the IITs</title><link href="https://mourjo.me/blog/tech/2020/06/13/positive-feedback-loop-darwin-and-the-iits/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Positive feedback loop, Darwin and the IITs" /><published>2020-06-13T03:44:11+02:00</published><updated>2020-06-13T03:44:11+02:00</updated><id>https://mourjo.me/blog/tech/2020/06/13/positive-feedback-loop-darwin-and-the-iits</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mourjo.me/blog/tech/2020/06/13/positive-feedback-loop-darwin-and-the-iits/"><![CDATA[<p>Being an engineer by profession, I have often battled with the fear of not hailing from an IIT. I cannot lie that no matter how many IITians I meet, I will never stop being self-conscious and intimidated by them. The lingering thought here is that I will never be able to be as successful or technically proficient as someone who studied at a prestigious and <strong>highly regarded</strong> institute like an IIT. Upon introspection, I have come to the conclusion that Darwin and the theory of natural selection might just be able to explain what I am feeling and ultimately why IITians <strong>are</strong> a distinguished subset of engineers in India.</p>

<p>The success of the IITs is not because of its teachers or research prowess, which is evident in the fact that the IITs never rank high in global University rankings. Any institute held in high regard by large enough number of people, will end up attracting the smartest minds. The invariant here is that <strong>most students</strong> in a country of India’s size want to study in the IITs. Because of the sheer competition for the very limited number of seats at the IITs, by virtue of the merit-based selection examinations (akin to natural selection in Darwin’s theory of evolution), only the smartest people end up in the IITs. If suddenly, by some divine intervention, all of Indian students stopped thinking of the IITs as the holy grail of undergraduate studies, then I would be very surprised if the best engineers in the country are still IITians. It is not the teachings at IIT that make great engineers, it is a direct correlation to the smartest people ending up in the IITs in the first place. Once a conglomerate of really smart people are formed at the IITs, there is no stopping, they practically shoot themselves into success. By passing the barrier to entry, the very few that get through, they have already proven to the world that they are better than the rest, what happens inside the gates of the IITs is immaterial.</p>

<p>This influences the companies that are looking to recruit engineers as well. Since the institute is perceived highly by the common people, because of competition for the few seats and the merit-based selection exams, only the best people end up there, so the probability of recruiting smart people is much higher at the IITs, so more and more companies look to recruit at the IITs, causing more interest in the IITs among aspiring engineers. The feedback loop reinforces the superiority of the IITs. It doesn’t even have to be an IIT, anything that is perceived as “good” by enough people will eventually attract enough “good people” to actually make the thing “good”.</p>

<p>In hindsight, there is perhaps no reason to be intimidated by people from the IITs or to think that one is not technically as proficient as someone from an IIT because not being from an IIT doesn’t necessarily demerit one. But it would be naive and remiss to think that those who have out-raced millions to get into the IITs are not among the distinguished subset of engineers in India.</p>]]></content><author><name>{&quot;twitter&quot;=&gt;&quot;mourjo_sen&quot;}</name></author><category term="tech" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Being an engineer by profession, I have often battled with the fear of not hailing from an IIT. I cannot lie that no matter how many IITians I meet, I will never stop being self-conscious and intimidated by them. The lingering thought here is that I will never be able to be as successful or technically proficient as someone who studied at a prestigious and highly regarded institute like an IIT. Upon introspection, I have come to the conclusion that Darwin and the theory of natural selection might just be able to explain what I am feeling and ultimately why IITians are a distinguished subset of engineers in India.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Pale blue dot: A Covid-19 perspective</title><link href="https://mourjo.me/blog/non-tech/2020/05/12/pale-blue-dot/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Pale blue dot: A Covid-19 perspective" /><published>2020-05-12T13:44:11+02:00</published><updated>2020-05-12T13:44:11+02:00</updated><id>https://mourjo.me/blog/non-tech/2020/05/12/pale-blue-dot</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mourjo.me/blog/non-tech/2020/05/12/pale-blue-dot/"><![CDATA[<p>In his famous book “The pale blue dot”, Carl Sagan <a href="https://www.planetary.org/explore/space-topics/earth/pale-blue-dot.html">wrote</a> about our unremarkable position in the Universe as human beings. This photo shows the pale blue dot; the image taken by the space probe Voyager 1 on February 14, 1990. As the spacecraft left our planetary neighborhood for the fringes of the solar system, NASA turned it around for one last look at our home planet.</p>

<p><img src="/blog/images/Pale_Blue_Dot.png" alt="Pale Blue Dot" /></p>

<p>As the world plunges into the unthinkable crisis of Covid-19, it is hard to find hope and courage to dream of a better day. Everything we know and love, our way of life, has reached a point of existential crisis. While many of our livelihoods are affected, many others are paying the dearest price of having to lose their loved ones.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Look again at that dot. That’s here. That’s home. That’s us. On it everyone you love, everyone you know, everyone you ever heard of, every human being who ever was, lived out their lives. The aggregate of our joy and suffering, thousands of confident religions, ideologies, and economic doctrines, every hunter and forager, every hero and coward, every creator and destroyer of civilization, every king and peasant, every young couple in love, every mother and father, hopeful child, inventor and explorer, every teacher of morals, every corrupt politician, every “superstar,” every “supreme leader,” every saint and sinner in the history of our species lived there–on a mote of dust suspended in a sunbeam.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>If our species reaches an end to life as we know it, what stories will we tell our children? If our lives are chained by a Virus that we cannot even see, would we be able to look back and say that our hay day on Earth was well spent?</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Think of the rivers of blood spilled by all those generals and emperors so that, in glory and triumph, they could become the momentary masters of a fraction of a dot. Think of the endless cruelties visited by the inhabitants of one corner of this pixel on the scarcely distinguishable inhabitants of some other corner, how frequent their misunderstandings, how eager they are to kill one another, how fervent their hatreds.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>We, who can fly to the moon, take photos of black holes, detect gravitational waves, have been stripped of our imaginary pedestal to be at the mercy of the littlest of the little things on Earth.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Our posturings, our imagined self-importance, the delusion that we have some privileged position in the Universe, are challenged by this point of pale light. Our planet is a lonely speck in the great enveloping cosmic dark. In our obscurity, in all this vastness, there is no hint that help will come from elsewhere to save us from ourselves.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Covid-19 is Nature’s revenge on our arrogance and narrow-mindedness.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>There is perhaps no better demonstration of the folly of human conceits than this distant image of our tiny world.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>But hope springs eternal. In our battle against the Covid-19 virus, we must become cognizant of and believe in our collective good to spend the remainder of our alloted time here on Earth, not as masters of the planet, but as children of nature.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>To me, it underscores our responsibility to deal more kindly with one another, and to preserve and cherish the pale blue dot, the only home we’ve ever known.</p>
</blockquote>]]></content><author><name>{&quot;twitter&quot;=&gt;&quot;mourjo_sen&quot;}</name></author><category term="non-tech" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In his famous book “The pale blue dot”, Carl Sagan wrote about our unremarkable position in the Universe as human beings. This photo shows the pale blue dot; the image taken by the space probe Voyager 1 on February 14, 1990. As the spacecraft left our planetary neighborhood for the fringes of the solar system, NASA turned it around for one last look at our home planet.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">[recurrent] Stuff I am reading</title><link href="https://mourjo.me/blog/tech/2019/09/20/reading-list/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="[recurrent] Stuff I am reading" /><published>2019-09-20T19:44:11+02:00</published><updated>2019-09-20T19:44:11+02:00</updated><id>https://mourjo.me/blog/tech/2019/09/20/reading-list</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mourjo.me/blog/tech/2019/09/20/reading-list/"><![CDATA[<p>This is a list of readings I have found to be extremely useful and
hence I am bookmarking them here, for my future self mostly. This is
an ever-increasing unordered list, which I am constantly trying to keep up with.</p>

<p>Last update: April 15, 2020.</p>

<h1 id="conceptual">Conceptual</h1>
<ul>
  <li>Critical Rendering Path <a href="https://developers.google.com/web/fundamentals/performance/critical-rendering-path/" target="_blank">https://developers.google.com/web/fundamentals/performance/critical-rendering-path/</a></li>
  <li>Algebraic Effects for the Rest of Us <a href="https://overreacted.io/algebraic-effects-for-the-rest-of-us/" target="_blank">https://overreacted.io/algebraic-effects-for-the-rest-of-us/</a></li>
  <li>Cryptographic Attacks: A Guide for the Perplexed <a href="https://research.checkpoint.com/cryptographic-attacks-a-guide-for-the-perplexed/" target="_blank">https://research.checkpoint.com/cryptographic-attacks-a-guide-for-the-perplexed/</a></li>
  <li>Introduction to Transaction Isolation Levels <a href="http://dbmsmusings.blogspot.com/2019/05/introduction-to-transaction-isolation.html" target="_blank">http://dbmsmusings.blogspot.com/2019/05/introduction-to-transaction-isolation.html</a></li>
  <li>Stop using JWT for sessions <a href="http://cryto.net/~joepie91/blog/2016/06/13/stop-using-jwt-for-sessions/" target="_blank">http://cryto.net/~joepie91/blog/2016/06/13/stop-using-jwt-for-sessions/</a></li>
  <li>What every computer science major should know <a href="http://matt.might.net/articles/what-cs-majors-should-know/" target="_blank">http://matt.might.net/articles/what-cs-majors-should-know/</a></li>
  <li>Introduction to HTTP/2 <a href="https://developers.google.com/web/fundamentals/performance/http2" target="_blank">https://developers.google.com/web/fundamentals/performance/http2</a></li>
  <li>Latacora - A Child’s Garden of Inter-Service Authentication Schemes <a href="https://latacora.micro.blog/a-childs-garden/" target="_blank">https://latacora.micro.blog/a-childs-garden/</a></li>
  <li>Javascript Object Signing and Encryption is a Bad Standard That Everyone Should Avoid <a href="https://paragonie.com/blog/2017/03/jwt-json-web-tokens-is-bad-standard-that-everyone-should-avoid" target="_blank">https://paragonie.com/blog/2017/03/jwt-json-web-tokens-is-bad-standard-that-everyone-should-avoid</a></li>
  <li>Password expiration is dead, long live passwords <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=20077967" target="_blank">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=20077967</a></li>
  <li>CPU Clocks and Clock Interrupts, and Their Effects on Schedulers <a href="https://accu.org/index.php/journals/2185" target="_blank">https://accu.org/index.php/journals/2185</a></li>
  <li>WebSockets - A Conceptual Deep-Dive <a href="https://www.ably.io/concepts/websockets" target="_blank">https://www.ably.io/concepts/websockets</a></li>
  <li>Sticky Sessions are Evil – Chaos in Computing <a href="http://www.chaosincomputing.com/2012/05/sticky-sessions-are-evil/" target="_blank">http://www.chaosincomputing.com/2012/05/sticky-sessions-are-evil/</a></li>
  <li>Why You Don’t Roll Your Own Crypto <a href="https://www.vice.com/en_us/article/wnx8nq/why-you-dont-roll-your-own-crypto" target="_blank">https://www.vice.com/en_us/article/wnx8nq/why-you-dont-roll-your-own-crypto</a></li>
  <li>The Hard Parts of JWT Security Nobody Talks About <a href="https://www.pingidentity.com/en/company/blog/posts/2019/jwt-security-nobody-talks-about.html" target="_blank">https://www.pingidentity.com/en/company/blog/posts/2019/jwt-security-nobody-talks-about.html</a></li>
  <li>Distributed consensus revised – Part I <a href="https://blog.acolyer.org/2019/05/07/distributed-consensus-revised-part-i/" target="_blank">https://blog.acolyer.org/2019/05/07/distributed-consensus-revised-part-i/</a></li>
  <li>Advanced Data Structures - MIT OpenCourseWare <a href="https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/electrical-engineering-and-computer-science/6-851-advanced-data-structures-spring-2012/lecture-videos/" target="_blank">https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/electrical-engineering-and-computer-science/6-851-advanced-data-structures-spring-2012/lecture-videos/</a></li>
  <li>A Generalised Solution to Distributed Consensus <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1902.06776" target="_blank">https://arxiv.org/abs/1902.06776</a></li>
  <li>Making reliable distributed systems in the presence of software errors <a href="http://erlang.org/download/armstrong_thesis_2003.pdf" target="_blank">http://erlang.org/download/armstrong_thesis_2003.pdf</a></li>
  <li>Linux Kernel Teaching — The Linux Kernel  documentation <a href="https://linux-kernel-labs.github.io/refs/heads/master/index.html" target="_blank">https://linux-kernel-labs.github.io/refs/heads/master/index.html</a></li>
  <li>Quantum computing for the very curious <a href="https://quantum.country/qcvc" target="_blank">https://quantum.country/qcvc</a></li>
  <li>Overview of Consistency Levels in Database Systems <a href="http://dbmsmusings.blogspot.com/2019/07/overview-of-consistency-levels-in.html" target="_blank">http://dbmsmusings.blogspot.com/2019/07/overview-of-consistency-levels-in.html</a></li>
  <li>The Wrong Abstraction — Sandi Metz <a href="https://www.sandimetz.com/blog/2016/1/20/the-wrong-abstraction" target="_blank">https://www.sandimetz.com/blog/2016/1/20/the-wrong-abstraction</a></li>
  <li>Christopher Batey - DYNAMO: the paper that changed the database world <a href="https://youtu.be/hMt9yFp0JKM" target="_blank">https://youtu.be/hMt9yFp0JKM</a></li>
  <li>CQRS <a href="https://martinfowler.com/bliki/CQRS.html" target="_blank">https://martinfowler.com/bliki/CQRS.html</a></li>
</ul>

<h1 id="infrastructure">Infrastructure</h1>
<ul>
  <li>Vulcanizer: a library for operating Elasticsearch <a href="https://github.blog/2019-03-05-vulcanizer-a-library-for-operating-elasticsearch/" target="_blank">https://github.blog/2019-03-05-vulcanizer-a-library-for-operating-elasticsearch/</a></li>
  <li>Modern applications at AWS <a href="https://www.allthingsdistributed.com/2019/08/modern-applications-at-aws.html" target="_blank">https://www.allthingsdistributed.com/2019/08/modern-applications-at-aws.html</a></li>
  <li>What comes after Serverless? <a href="https://medium.com/@doctor_julz/what-comes-after-serverless-840032dd4ba8" target="_blank">https://medium.com/@doctor_julz/what-comes-after-serverless-840032dd4ba8</a></li>
  <li>IPA: invariant-preserving applications for weakly consistent replicated databases <a href="https://blog.acolyer.org/2019/09/02/ipa/" target="_blank">https://blog.acolyer.org/2019/09/02/ipa/</a></li>
  <li>DDSketch: a fast and fully-mergeable quantile sketch with relative-error guarantees <a href="https://blog.acolyer.org/2019/09/06/ddsketch/" target="_blank">https://blog.acolyer.org/2019/09/06/ddsketch/</a></li>
  <li>Isolating workloads with Systemd slices <a href="https://www.scylladb.com/2019/09/25/isolating-workloads-with-systemd-slices/" target="_blank">https://www.scylladb.com/2019/09/25/isolating-workloads-with-systemd-slices/</a></li>
  <li>Dark emerges from stealth with unique ‘deployless’ software model <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2019/07/29/dark-emerges-from-stealth-with-unique-deployless-software-model/" target="_blank">https://techcrunch.com/2019/07/29/dark-emerges-from-stealth-with-unique-deployless-software-model/</a></li>
  <li>We had issues with Monzo on 29th July. Here’s what happened, and what we did to fix it. <a href="https://monzo.com/blog/2019/09/08/why-monzo-wasnt-working-on-july-29th/" target="_blank">https://monzo.com/blog/2019/09/08/why-monzo-wasnt-working-on-july-29th/</a></li>
  <li>Using GraphQL to Improve Data Hydration in our Customer Care Platform and Beyond <a href="https://eng.uber.com/graphql-data-hydration-customer-care/" target="_blank">https://eng.uber.com/graphql-data-hydration-customer-care/</a></li>
  <li>One Misconfig (JIRA) to Leak Them All- Including NASA and Hundreds of Fortune 500 Companies! <a href="https://medium.com/@logicbomb_1/one-misconfig-jira-to-leak-them-all-including-nasa-and-hundreds-of-fortune-500-companies-a70957ef03c7" target="_blank">https://medium.com/@logicbomb_1/one-misconfig-jira-to-leak-them-all-including-nasa-and-hundreds-of-fortune-500-companies-a70957ef03c7</a></li>
  <li>Netflix: What Happens When You Press Play? - High Scalability -  <a href="http://highscalability.com/blog/2017/12/11/netflix-what-happens-when-you-press-play.html" target="_blank">http://highscalability.com/blog/2017/12/11/netflix-what-happens-when-you-press-play.html</a></li>
  <li>Streaming Cassandra at WePay - Part 1 <a href="https://wecode.wepay.com/posts/streaming-cassandra-at-wepay-part-1" target="_blank">https://wecode.wepay.com/posts/streaming-cassandra-at-wepay-part-1</a></li>
  <li>Streaming Cassandra at WePay - Part 2 <a href="https://wecode.wepay.com/posts/streaming-cassandra-at-wepay-part-2" target="_blank">https://wecode.wepay.com/posts/streaming-cassandra-at-wepay-part-2</a></li>
  <li>The boring technology behind a one-person Internet company <a href="https://broadcast.listennotes.com/the-boring-technology-behind-listen-notes-56697c2e347b" target="_blank">https://broadcast.listennotes.com/the-boring-technology-behind-listen-notes-56697c2e347b</a></li>
  <li>Zen and the Art of Scaling - A Koan and Epigram Approach - High Scalability -  <a href="http://highscalability.com/blog/2012/2/27/zen-and-the-art-of-scaling-a-koan-and-epigram-approach.html" target="_blank">http://highscalability.com/blog/2012/2/27/zen-and-the-art-of-scaling-a-koan-and-epigram-approach.html</a></li>
  <li>Software/site reliability of distributed systems <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=grEgDJVNIS0&amp;list=PL279M8GbNsesB7sxLO5zNbBHkOVvb7uvy&amp;index=5&amp;t=0s" target="_blank">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=grEgDJVNIS0&amp;list=PL279M8GbNsesB7sxLO5zNbBHkOVvb7uvy&amp;index=5&amp;t=0s</a></li>
  <li>Cloud Native DevOps With Kubernetes <a href="https://www.nginx.com/resources/library/cloud-native-devops-with-kubernetes/" target="_blank">https://www.nginx.com/resources/library/cloud-native-devops-with-kubernetes/</a></li>
  <li>Everything You Need To Know About Networking On AWS <a href="https://grahamlyons.com/article/everything-you-need-to-know-about-networking-on-aws" target="_blank">https://grahamlyons.com/article/everything-you-need-to-know-about-networking-on-aws</a></li>
  <li>PostgreSQL vs. fsync <a href="https://fosdem.org/2019/schedule/event/postgresql_fsync/" target="_blank">https://fosdem.org/2019/schedule/event/postgresql_fsync/</a></li>
  <li>Supercell – Scaling Mobile Games (GAM301) <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=wqz7AunrzcU" target="_blank">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=wqz7AunrzcU</a></li>
  <li>How to Scale WebSockets <a href="https://hackernoon.com/scaling-websockets-9a31497af051" target="_blank">https://hackernoon.com/scaling-websockets-9a31497af051</a></li>
  <li>How to scale a distributed system <a href="https://cdn.oreillystatic.com/en/assets/1/event/244/How%20to%20scale%20a%20distributed%20system%20Presentation.pdf" target="_blank">https://bit.ly/2msquzp</a></li>
  <li>A Brief History of High Availability - Cockroach Labs <a href="https://www.cockroachlabs.com/blog/brief-history-high-availability/" target="_blank">https://www.cockroachlabs.com/blog/brief-history-high-availability/</a></li>
  <li>Elastic Scaling in the Streams API in Kafka - Confluent <a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/elastic-scaling-in-kafka-streams/" target="_blank">https://www.confluent.io/blog/elastic-scaling-in-kafka-streams/</a></li>
  <li>Open Distro for Elasticsearch <a href="https://opendistro.github.io/for-elasticsearch/" target="_blank">https://opendistro.github.io/for-elasticsearch/</a></li>
  <li>New – Open Distro for Elasticsearch – AWS <a href="https://aws.amazon.com/blogs/aws/new-open-distro-for-elasticsearch/" target="_blank">https://aws.amazon.com/blogs/aws/new-open-distro-for-elasticsearch/</a></li>
  <li>Smart sticky sessions using HAProxy for Apache Phoenix <a href="https://medium.com/helpshift-engineering/smart-sticky-sessions-using-haproxy-for-apache-phoenix-911bdca7e2c" target="_blank">https://medium.com/helpshift-engineering/smart-sticky-sessions-using-haproxy-for-apache-phoenix-911bdca7e2c</a></li>
  <li>How to get HTTPS working on your local development environment in 5 minutes <a href="https://www.freecodecamp.org/news/how-to-get-https-working-on-your-local-development-environment-in-5-minutes-7af615770eec/" target="_blank">https://www.freecodecamp.org/news/how-to-get-https-working-on-your-local-development-environment-in-5-minutes-7af615770eec/</a></li>
  <li>Elle: Inferring Isolation Anomalies from Experimental Observations <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2003.10554" target="_blank">https://arxiv.org/abs/2003.10554</a></li>
  <li>The Quest for the master algorithm <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=qIZ5PXLVZfo" target="_blank">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=qIZ5PXLVZfo</a></li>
  <li>What we learnt building BHIM in just 3 weeks - Vimal Kumar <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=uaQ_jNgw6F0" target="_blank">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=uaQ_jNgw6F0</a></li>
  <li>JVM Anatomy Quarks <a href="https://shipilev.net/jvm/anatomy-quarks/" target="_blank">https://shipilev.net/jvm/anatomy-quarks/</a></li>
  <li>(A few) Ops Lessons We All Learn The Hard Way <a href="https://www.netmeister.org/blog/ops-lessons.html" target="_blank">https://www.netmeister.org/blog/ops-lessons.html</a></li>
  <li>Managing the development of large systems <a href="http://www-scf.usc.edu/~csci201/lectures/Lecture11/royce1970.pdf" target="_blank">http://www-scf.usc.edu/~csci201/lectures/Lecture11/royce1970.pdf</a></li>
  <li>Load Testing Back to Basics: Avoiding the KeepAliveTimeout Race Condition - Web Performance <a href="https://www.webperformance.com/load-testing-tools/blog/2011/01/load-testing-back-to-basics-avoiding-the-keepalivetimeout-race-condition/" target="_blank">https://www.webperformance.com/load-testing-tools/blog/2011/01/load-testing-back-to-basics-avoiding-the-keepalivetimeout-race-condition/</a></li>
  <li>Sharing SQLite databases across containers is surprisingly brilliant <a href="https://medium.com/@rbranson/sharing-sqlite-databases-across-containers-is-surprisingly-brilliant-bacb8d753054" target="_blank">https://medium.com/@rbranson/sharing-sqlite-databases-across-containers-is-surprisingly-brilliant-bacb8d753054</a></li>
  <li>Nubank’s basic Microservice example <a href="https://github.com/nubank/basic-microservice-example" target="_blank">https://github.com/nubank/basic-microservice-example</a></li>
  <li>Microservices and the First Law of Distributed Objects <a href="https://martinfowler.com/articles/distributed-objects-microservices.html" target="_blank">https://martinfowler.com/articles/distributed-objects-microservices.html</a></li>
  <li>What do you mean by “Event-Driven”? <a href="https://martinfowler.com/articles/201701-event-driven.html" target="_blank">https://martinfowler.com/articles/201701-event-driven.html</a></li>
</ul>

<h1 id="architecture">Architecture</h1>
<ul>
  <li>Why our team cancelled our move to microservices <a href="https://medium.com/@steven.lemon182/why-our-team-cancelled-our-move-to-microservices-8fd87898d952" target="_blank">https://medium.com/@steven.lemon182/why-our-team-cancelled-our-move-to-microservices-8fd87898d952</a></li>
  <li>Architecture of a Database System <a href="http://db.cs.berkeley.edu/papers/fntdb07-architecture.pdf" target="_blank">http://db.cs.berkeley.edu/papers/fntdb07-architecture.pdf</a></li>
  <li>Event Sourcing You are doing it wrong by David Schmitz <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=GzrZworHpIk" target="_blank">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=GzrZworHpIk</a></li>
  <li>Stateful stream processing with Apache Flink <a href="https://www.infoworld.com/article/3267966/stateful-stream-processing-with-apache-flink.html" target="_blank">https://www.infoworld.com/article/3267966/stateful-stream-processing-with-apache-flink.html</a></li>
  <li>Improving key expiration in Redis <a href="https://blog.twitter.com/engineering/en_us/topics/infrastructure/2019/improving-key-expiration-in-redis.html" target="_blank">https://blog.twitter.com/engineering/en_us/topics/infrastructure/2019/improving-key-expiration-in-redis.html</a></li>
  <li>Distributed systems for fun and profit <a href="http://book.mixu.net/distsys/intro.html" target="_blank">http://book.mixu.net/distsys/intro.html</a></li>
  <li>Goodbye Microservices: From 100s of problem children to 1 superstar <a href="https://segment.com/blog/goodbye-microservices/" target="_blank">https://segment.com/blog/goodbye-microservices/</a></li>
  <li>Notes on Distributed Systems for Young Bloods – Something Similar <a href="https://www.somethingsimilar.com/2013/01/14/notes-on-distributed-systems-for-young-bloods/" target="_blank">https://www.somethingsimilar.com/2013/01/14/notes-on-distributed-systems-for-young-bloods/</a></li>
  <li>The Software Architects Newsletter <a href="https://assets.infoq.com/newsletter/architect/en/newsletter_sample/21Architects_NL-April2019.html" target="_blank">https://assets.infoq.com/newsletter/architect/en/newsletter_sample/21Architects_NL-April2019.html</a></li>
  <li>How to Design a Good API &amp; Why it Matters  <a href="https://www.infoq.com/presentations/effective-api-design" target="_blank">https://www.infoq.com/presentations/effective-api-design</a></li>
  <li>Online Event Processing - ACM Queue <a href="https://queue.acm.org/detail.cfm?id=3321612" target="_blank">https://queue.acm.org/detail.cfm?id=3321612</a></li>
  <li>Mastering Chaos - A Netflix Guide to Microservices <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=CZ3wIuvmHeM" target="_blank">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=CZ3wIuvmHeM</a></li>
  <li>Data-Driven Storytelling <a href="http://learn.stanford.edu/data-driven-storytelling-live-reg-0420.html" target="_blank">http://learn.stanford.edu/data-driven-storytelling-live-reg-0420.html</a></li>
  <li>How to Build a Cloud Data Platform Part 1 Architecture <a href="https://youtu.be/uhVpLwjEOKU" target="_blank">https://youtu.be/uhVpLwjEOKU</a></li>
  <li>Snap: a microkernel approach to host networking <a href="https://blog.acolyer.org/2019/11/11/snap-networking/" target="_blank">https://blog.acolyer.org/2019/11/11/snap-networking/</a></li>
</ul>

<h1 id="programming">Programming</h1>
<ul>
  <li>On the Perils of Dynamic Scope <a href="https://stuartsierra.com/2013/03/29/perils-of-dynamic-scope" target="_blank">https://stuartsierra.com/2013/03/29/perils-of-dynamic-scope</a></li>
  <li>Secure Programming HOWTO <a href="https://dwheeler.com/secure-programs/Secure-Programs-HOWTO/index.html" target="_blank">https://dwheeler.com/secure-programs/Secure-Programs-HOWTO/index.html</a></li>
  <li>Mockers - overcoming testing challenges at Grab <a href="https://engineering.grab.com/mockers" target="_blank">https://engineering.grab.com/mockers</a></li>
  <li>Python at Netflix <a href="https://medium.com/netflix-techblog/python-at-netflix-bba45dae649e" target="_blank">https://medium.com/netflix-techblog/python-at-netflix-bba45dae649e</a></li>
  <li>Zen of Python <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zen_of_Python" target="_blank">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zen_of_Python</a></li>
  <li>Is It Time to Rewrite the Operating System in Rust? <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=HgtRAbE1nBM" target="_blank">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=HgtRAbE1nBM</a></li>
  <li>Clojure Compilation: Parenthetical Prose to Bewildering Bytecode <a href="https://blog.ndk.io/clojure-compilation.html" target="_blank">https://blog.ndk.io/clojure-compilation.html</a></li>
  <li>Organizing Functional Code for Parallel Execution; or, foldl and foldr Considered  Slightly Harmful <a href="https://vimeo.com/6624203" target="_blank">https://vimeo.com/6624203</a></li>
  <li>Software disenchantment <a href="http://tonsky.me/blog/disenchantment/" target="_blank">http://tonsky.me/blog/disenchantment/</a></li>
  <li>Lockfree Algorithms - 1024cores <a href="http://www.1024cores.net/home/lock-free-algorithms/" target="_blank">http://www.1024cores.net/home/lock-free-algorithms/</a></li>
  <li>Why Why Functional Programming Matters Matters <a href="http://raganwald.com/2014/12/20/why-why-functional-programming-matters-matters.html" target="_blank">http://raganwald.com/2014/12/20/why-why-functional-programming-matters-matters.html</a></li>
  <li>Java at Speed <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ot3PESmNXhE" target="_blank">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ot3PESmNXhE</a></li>
  <li>Java SE Lesson: Concurrency <a href="https://docs.oracle.com/javase/tutorial/essential/concurrency/" target="_blank">https://docs.oracle.com/javase/tutorial/essential/concurrency/</a></li>
  <li>What Clojure needs to grow — a boring web framework and boring data science <a href="https://lispcast.com/clojure-needs-grow-boring-web-framework-boring-data-science/" target="_blank">https://lispcast.com/clojure-needs-grow-boring-web-framework-boring-data-science/</a></li>
  <li>Working Effectively with Legacy Code <a href="http://ptgmedia.pearsoncmg.com/images/9780131177055/samplepages/0131177052.pdf" target="_blank">http://ptgmedia.pearsoncmg.com/images/9780131177055/samplepages/0131177052.pdf</a></li>
  <li>The Best Refactoring You’ve Never Heard Of <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20190719160744/http://www.pathsensitive.com/2019/07/the-best-refactoring-youve-never-heard.html" target="_blank">https://web.archive.org/web/20190719160744/http://www.pathsensitive.com/2019/07/the-best-refactoring-youve-never-heard.html</a></li>
  <li>Lets make a Binary Search Tree <a href="https://medium.com/reasontraining/lets-make-a-reasonable-binary-search-tree-35628b2c78f7" target="_blank">https://medium.com/reasontraining/lets-make-a-reasonable-binary-search-tree-35628b2c78f7</a></li>
  <li>Clojure Compilation: Parenthetical Prose to Bewildering Bytecode <a href="https://blog.ndk.io/clojure-compilation.html" target="_blank">https://blog.ndk.io/clojure-compilation.html</a></li>
  <li>Refactoring the Worst Code I’ve Ever Written <a href="https://dev.to/jnschrag/refactoring-the-worst-code-i-ve-ever-written-42c7" target="_blank">https://dev.to/jnschrag/refactoring-the-worst-code-i-ve-ever-written-42c7</a></li>
  <li>Clean Coder Blog <a href="https://blog.cleancoder.com/uncle-bob/2012/08/13/the-clean-architecture.html" target="_blank">https://blog.cleancoder.com/uncle-bob/2012/08/13/the-clean-architecture.html</a></li>
  <li>Complex Made Bearable - Lucas Cavalcanti <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ct5aWqhHARs" target="_blank">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ct5aWqhHARs</a></li>
  <li>Programming Algorithms Book <a href="http://lisp-univ-etc.blogspot.com/2019/07/programming-algorithms-book.html" target="_blank">http://lisp-univ-etc.blogspot.com/2019/07/programming-algorithms-book.html</a></li>
  <li>Building an Effective Test Pipeline in a Service Oriented World <a href="https://medium.com/airbnb-engineering/building-an-effective-test-pipeline-in-a-service-oriented-world-6968c513c6bd" target="_blank">https://medium.com/airbnb-engineering/building-an-effective-test-pipeline-in-a-service-oriented-world-6968c513c6bd</a></li>
  <li>The Missing Semester of Your CS Education <a href="https://missing.csail.mit.edu/" target="_blank">https://missing.csail.mit.edu/</a></li>
  <li>The Practical Test Pyramid <a href="https://martinfowler.com/articles/practical-test-pyramid.html" target="_blank">https://martinfowler.com/articles/practical-test-pyramid.html</a></li>
  <li>The Birth &amp; Death of JavaScript <a href="https://www.destroyallsoftware.com/talks/the-birth-and-death-of-javascript" target="_blank">https://www.destroyallsoftware.com/talks/the-birth-and-death-of-javascript</a></li>
  <li>Unit, Functional, Integration? You are doing it wrong <a href="https://blog.7mind.io/constructive-test-taxonomy.html" target="_blank">https://blog.7mind.io/constructive-test-taxonomy.html</a></li>
  <li>The inflection point hypothesis: a principled approach to finding the root cause of a failure <a href="https://blog.acolyer.org/2019/11/08/the-inflection-point-hypothesis/" target="_blank">https://blog.acolyer.org/2019/11/08/the-inflection-point-hypothesis/</a></li>
  <li>William Byrd on “The Most Beautiful Program Ever Written” <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=OyfBQmvr2Hc" target="_blank">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=OyfBQmvr2Hc</a></li>
  <li>Beating C with 80 lines of Haskell: wc <a href="https://chrispenner.ca/posts/wc" target="_blank">https://chrispenner.ca/posts/wc</a></li>
  <li>Practical Common Lisp <a href="http://www.gigamonkeys.com/book/" target="_blank">http://www.gigamonkeys.com/book/</a></li>
</ul>

<h1 id="miscellaneous">Miscellaneous</h1>
<ul>
  <li>TextRank for Text Summarization <a href="https://nlpforhackers.io/textrank-text-summarization" target="_blank">https://nlpforhackers.io/textrank-text-summarization</a></li>
  <li>It was a really bad month for the internet <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2019/07/05/bad-month-for-the-internet/" target="_blank">https://techcrunch.com/2019/07/05/bad-month-for-the-internet/</a></li>
  <li>7 absolute truths I unlearned as junior developer <a href="https://monicalent.com/blog/2019/06/03/absolute-truths-unlearned-as-junior-developer/" target="_blank">https://monicalent.com/blog/2019/06/03/absolute-truths-unlearned-as-junior-developer/</a>
p- Designing Data-Intensive Application and its related books <a href="https://anvaka.github.io/greview/ddia/1/" target="_blank">https://anvaka.github.io/greview/ddia/1/</a></li>
  <li>Get your work recognized: write a brag document <a href="https://jvns.ca/blog/brag-documents/" target="_blank">https://jvns.ca/blog/brag-documents/</a></li>
  <li>Human-Centric Machine Learning Infrastructure @Netflix <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=XV5VGddmP24" target="_blank">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=XV5VGddmP24</a></li>
  <li>Correctness proofs of distributed systems with Isabelle - Strange Loop <a href="https://thestrangeloop.com/2019/correctness-proofs-of-distributed-systems-with-isabelle.html" target="_blank">https://thestrangeloop.com/2019/correctness-proofs-of-distributed-systems-with-isabelle.html</a></li>
  <li>Feature Toggles (aka Feature Flags) <a href="https://martinfowler.com/articles/feature-toggles.html" target="_blank">https://martinfowler.com/articles/feature-toggles.html</a></li>
  <li>Finding the Order in Chaos <a href="https://www.usenix.org/conference/srecon16/program/presentation/lueder" target="_blank">https://www.usenix.org/conference/srecon16/program/presentation/lueder</a></li>
  <li>A Note About Git Commit Messages <a href="http://tbaggery.com/2008/04/19/a-note-about-git-commit-messages.html" target="_blank">http://tbaggery.com/2008/04/19/a-note-about-git-commit-messages.html</a></li>
  <li>Michelangelo Palette: A Feature Engineering Platform at Uber  <a href="https://www.infoq.com/presentations/michelangelo-palette-uber" target="_blank">https://www.infoq.com/presentations/michelangelo-palette-uber</a></li>
  <li>Visualizing Systems with Statemaps <a href="https://www.slideshare.net/bcantrill/visualizing-systems-with-statemaps" target="_blank">https://www.slideshare.net/bcantrill/visualizing-systems-with-statemaps</a></li>
  <li>Numbers Every Programmer Should Know By Year <a href="https://people.eecs.berkeley.edu/~rcs/research/interactive_latency.html" target="_blank">https://people.eecs.berkeley.edu/~rcs/research/interactive_latency.html</a></li>
  <li>Things I Learnt from a Senior Software Engineer <a href="https://neilkakkar.com/things-I-learnt-from-a-senior-dev.html" target="_blank">https://neilkakkar.com/things-I-learnt-from-a-senior-dev.html</a></li>
  <li>The Rise and Fall of Server-Side Sessions <a href="http://codematters.tech/the-rise-and-fall-of-server-side-sessions-part-1-when-the-cookie-crumbles/">http://codematters.tech/the-rise-and-fall-of-server-side-sessions-part-1-when-the-cookie-crumbles/</a></li>
  <li>The Weird Rules I Set Myself That Got Me a Job <a href="https://dev.to/healeycodes/the-weird-rules-i-set-myself-that-got-me-a-job-2g9m?fbclid=IwAR2xKqcEAEKJBE08CFRekWorouNWNN19WKb392qf0urhDjimVWUnqdyV0Rs" target="_blank">https://dev.to/healeycodes/the-weird-rules-i-set-myself-that-got-me-a-job-2g9m?fbclid=IwAR2xKqcEAEKJBE08CFRekWorouNWNN19WKb392qf0urhDjimVWUnqdyV0Rs</a></li>
  <li>Technical Writing Google Developers <a href="https://developers.google.com/tech-writing/" target="_blank">https://developers.google.com/tech-writing/</a></li>
  <li>Conway’s law is real <a href="https://goodroot.ca/post/2018/10/13/practicality-metaphysics-conways-law/" target="_blank">https://goodroot.ca/post/2018/10/13/practicality-metaphysics-conways-law/</a></li>
  <li>What it’s like to work for Stripe <a href="https://blog.alexmaccaw.com/stripes-culture" target="_blank">https://blog.alexmaccaw.com/stripes-culture</a></li>
  <li>Notation as a Tool of Thought  <a href="http://www.eecg.toronto.edu/~jzhu/csc326/readings/iverson.pdf" target="_blank">http://www.eecg.toronto.edu/~jzhu/csc326/readings/iverson.pdf</a></li>
  <li>A Large Scale Study of Programming Languages and Code Quality in Github <a href="https://web.cs.ucdavis.edu/~filkov/papers/lang_github.pdf" target="_blank">https://web.cs.ucdavis.edu/~filkov/papers/lang_github.pdf</a></li>
  <li>Why Devs (Should) Like Estimates - Stack Overflow Blog <a href="https://stackoverflow.blog/2019/10/23/why-devs-should-like-estimates/" target="_blank">https://stackoverflow.blog/2019/10/23/why-devs-should-like-estimates/</a></li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name>{&quot;twitter&quot;=&gt;&quot;mourjo_sen&quot;}</name></author><category term="tech" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This is a list of readings I have found to be extremely useful and hence I am bookmarking them here, for my future self mostly. This is an ever-increasing unordered list, which I am constantly trying to keep up with.]]></summary></entry></feed>